<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Hale'-Ta Series: HeStorian Taotao Tano': HISTORY OF THE CHAMORRO PEOPLE</title>
                <author>Political Status Education Coordinating Commission</author>
                <affiliation>Insider</affiliation>
                <place>Guam</place>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Political Status Education Coordinating Commission</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Agana, Guam</pubPlace>
                <date>1994</date>
                <idno type="ISBN">1-883488-00-1</idno>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <p>All rights reserved. No part of this book may be reproduced or transmitted in
                    any form or by any means, electronic or mechanical, including photocopying,
                    recording, or by any information storage and retrieval system, without the
                    written permission of the Publisher, except where permitted by law.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>The Hale'-Ta Series</title>
                    <editor>Political Status Education Coordinating Commission</editor>
                    <pubPlace>Agana, Guam</pubPlace>
                    <date>1994</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="dedication">
                <head>Dedicated to the Children of Guam</head>
                <p>To The Student</p>
                <p>When we say, "Once upon a time," we think about fairy
                tales and make believe stories. But when we say, "At one time,"
                we think about stories that really happened. We think about
                history.</p>

                <p>Fairy tales teach us about the make believe world. History
                stories teach us about the real world and about our past. There
                are heroes and villains in both kinds of stories. Both kinds can
                also be filled with mystery, romance and adventure, but history
                stories are the only ones that are true.</p>

                <p>History stories help us learn about past events and how
                these events have shaped our world today. They are about all
                the yesterdays that have gone by. By explaining all that has
                happened along the way to today, history stories help us
                understand our beginnings, our roots. They help us discover
                who we are, where we came from and why we live the way we
                do. 'This is an important reason for studying history, but it is not
                the only one.</p>

                <p>There is wisdom in the past. There is valuable information
                about actions and decisions that proved to be correct and those
                that proved to be damaging. Knowing and understanding
                what made the difference is important. It can shape the future.</p>

                <p>Shaping the future in good ways is the best reason for
                studying the past. Someday, you will make the actions and
                decisions for the island and the people of Guam. You will add
                your own stories to its history. We hope this book prepares you
                to do it well.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="contents">
                <head>CONTENTS</head>
                <list>
                    <item>PART I: CHAMORRO PREHISTORY</item>
                    <item>UNIT 1: The Quest for a Home and Identity</item>
                    <item>UNIT 2: The Life of the Ancient Chamorros</item>
                    <item>PART II: CONTACT WITH THE EUROPEANS</item>
                    <item>UNIT 1: Contact with the Europeans</item>
                    <item>UNIT 2: Bringing Christianity to the Chamorros</item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="part" n="1">
                <head>PART I: CHAMORRO PREHISTORY: INTRODUCTION</head>
                <p>Where did the first Pacific island people
                come from? When did they arrive? How did they get 
                into the region? Why did they leave their old homes? These 
                are just some of the questions that serious students and 
                teachers of Guam and the Pacific have been asking. The origins 
                of the people of the Pacific is part of a great puzzle. The 
                origins of the Chamorro people of Guam and the Marianas, 
                hale'-ta, is an important part of that puzzle.</p>

                <p>Thousands of years ago, the ancient people of Guam,
                the Chamorros, set out for a new homeland. They
                discovered the Mariana Islands. These islands became
                their new home. Today, many years later, present-day
                Chamorros and the other people who live in Guam are on
                another quest. This time we are looking for a new kind of
                partnership with the United States of America. As we go
                on this new quest, we should learn all we can about the
                first quest. It is important for us to know about our
                ancestors and how they managed to survive so well on a
                small island.</p>

                <p>The spirit of the ancient navigators who conquered
                the Pacific Ocean made us who we are today.</p>

                <div type="unit" n="1">
                    <head>THE QUEST FOR A HOME AND IDENTITY</head>
                    <div type="sections" n="a">
                        <head>Clues to the Puzzle</head>
                        <p>There are many clues that tell us about the origin of our ancient Chamorro
                        people, where they possibly carne from, how they made their ocean voyage to
                        their new home, and the way they lived in their new-found homeland. Some of
                        the most important clues come from studying their physical remains, their
                        language, their tools and handicrafts, and the plants they used. Some very good
                        clues can be found in the knowledge the Chamorros still have about the plants,
                        animals and fish around them. By comparing the Chamorro people's language,
                        tools, and plants with those from other areas, we can begin to see a picture in the
                        puzzle. When we add what we know about ourselves, the picture becomes
                        even clearer.</p>

                        <p>Clues from Ancestral Remains</p>

                        <p>The actual physical remains - the bones - of our ancestors provide us
                        with a direct link between their lives and ours. They also provide us with
                        many important clues as to how long the Chamorro people inhabited the
                        Marianas.</p>

                        <p>By studying ancient bones, scientists can estimate the age and general
                        health condition of individuals, and from this information, they can also
                        learn much about the population as a whole. Where bones are found, and
                        the condition in which they are found, can tell us about settlement patterns
                        and burial practices.</p>

                        <p>Bones can tell us about what the ancient Chamorros looked like and
                        about their health and diet. We know, for example, that ancient Chamorros
                        were not the giants described by early explorers. Our ancient ancestors
                        were of average height. The men were around five-and-a-half feet tall and
                        the women were just a little shorter.</p>

                        <p>Curiously, the bones of some ancient individuals have unusual lumps at
                        the base of the skull near the neck and shoulder. These bone lumps have
                        puzzled scientists. The lumps were probably caused by some kind of pro-
                        longed activity, but scientists are not sure what that activity was. In a sense,
                        it is a mystery that is not solved yet.</p>

                        <p>Bones and teeth are often used as clues to tell us about the lifestyle of the
                        ancient Chamorros. Chewing pugua, for instance, is a very old Chamorro
                        practice. The teeth of many ancient Chamorros are worn down and stained
                        red. Some Chamorros also scratched designs onto their teeth.</p>

                        <p>The etching of teeth and the chewing of betelnut are common practices
                        in Southeast Asia. This clue points to origins or contacts with people from
                        this region.</p>

                        <p>Today many people have strong feelings about the study of human
                        remains. Some feel that ancestral remains, especially those found in burial
                        sites, should never be disturbed. Others feel that study is necessary to add
                        to our knowledge. Most people feel that if research needs to be done, it
                        should be conducted in more sensitive and respectful ways.</p>

                        <p>Clues from Language</p>

                        <p>There are many people and many different languages. People have been
                        studying their own language and those of others for many years. The people
                        who study languages are called linguists. Some linguists are trained in school,
                        others become language experts on their own. You may know someone - a
                        teacher or a relative - who can teach you a lot about the Charnorro language.</p>

                        <p>In order to study all the many different languages in the world, linguists
                        group together those that share certain similarities into "language families." A
                        language family may contain languages that seem very different from one
                        another, but they are members because they descend from an original "mother"
                        language.</p>

                        <p>One of the largest and oldest language families is called Austronesian.
                        Some experts believe its mother language originated in a vast region known as
                        Southeast Asia. The present-day languages of Southeast Asia and the Pacific are
                        members of the Austronesian family. This tells us that all the indigenous people
                        of this region are like relatives. They are related by a common ancestral
                        language. The Charnorro language is one of the oldest in Micronesia. If shares
                        many of the same words and has a grammar similar to languages from the
                        Philippines, Indonesia and the Pacific. Do you know any words that link the
                        Chamorro language with those of other people from other places?</p>

                        <p>The evidence from language studies suggests that the Chamorros and other
                        Pacific islanders originally came from somewhere in Southeast Asia thousands
                        of years ago. But they did not come all at once, nor did they all come from the
                        same place. Many groups of people moved from different areas at different
                        times and went in different directions. The ancestors of the Chamorros were
                        among the first to settle in Micronesia.</p>

                        <p>Clues from Tools and Pottery</p>

                        <p>Another clue to the puzzle comes from the things ancient people used in
                        everyday life. The early settlers of Guam and Micronesia made and used
                        different kinds of tools. These tools tell us much about their daily lives. They
                        made tools to build canoes and to fish and plant. They also made weapons for
                        hunting and fighting or to use in ceremonies. Many of these tools were made of
                        hard materials like bones, stones, and shells. They last a very long time and can
                        be found in the places where ancient people lived, worked, and played. Ancient
                        tools can also tell us if people on different islands had contact with each other.</p>

                        <p>Like tools, pottery can help us know about the lives of ancient people. The
                        ancient Chamorros knew how to make pottery. They probably brought this
                        knowledge with them when they came to Guam. Making pottery was probably
                        done by women. Over many hundreds of years they made thousands of bowls
                        and jars. They made so many that broken pieces can still be found in parts of
                        Guam today.</p>


                        <p>Chamorro pottery is found only in the Marianas. Chamorro pottery mak-
                        ers used their special knowledge with the clays and sand found in the Marianas
                        to develop their own style of pottery. The earliest form of Chamorro pottery is
                        called "Marianas red ware" because it was usually red in color. Some of the
                        oldest pottery dates back to more than three thousand years ago (1500 B.C.). The
                        bowls and jars of Marianas red ware were sometimes decorated with lines and
                        circles that were filled in with "afok," a chalky white substance made by burning
                        limestone rocks until they become soft. Afok was very important to the society
                        and was used for many other purposes. Afok is still made today and used for
                        making konsetba and eskomme and for chewing with pugua.</p>

                        <p>Pottery similar to Marianas red ware has been found in the Philippines and
                        other parts of Southeast Asia. This is another clue that tells us the ancient
                        Chamorros came from Southeast Asia and that they may have maintained trade
                        in the region.</p>

                        <p>Clues from Plants</p>

                        <p>Besides language and tools, we can also study island plants. Some plants
                        grow naturally on islands, but others are not native to small islands. The seeds
                        of native plants were probably brought to the islands by the wind and the ocean
                        currents. They might even have been carried in the stomachs of sea birds and
                        deposited on the ground near their nests. But how did other non-native plants
                        get to the islands? People must have brought them here.</p>

                        <p>When the ancient canoe travellers set out to find new homelands, they
                        surely brought items necessary for their survival. In addition to a good supply
                        of food and water, they may also have brought tools for making new homes.
                        They may also have brought the seeds, sprouts and tree saplings of the plants
                        that were important in their customs and lifestyle.</p>

                        <p>Some of these plants were aga (bananas), sUlli (taro), dagu (yams) and Iemmai
                        (breadfruit) which were used for food. Large trees like lemmai, ifet (ifil), gago
                        (ironwood), dn'ok (palo maria) and pago (wild hibiscus) were important for
                        building houses and canoes. Other plants were needed for making medicine
                        and magic. And some were just used for color and decorations. The tronkon
                        niyok, or coconut tree, is a special example. It can be used in many different
                        ways. The trunks can be used for building. The leaves can be woven into
                        baskets, mats, roof covers and other useful things. Coconuts provide food,
                        drink and medicine. Other parts of the tree also have uses. Can you think of
                        other uses for the coconut tree?</p>


                        <p>Putting the Clues Together</p>

                        <p>The clues from human remains, language, tools, and plants tell us that our
                        ancestors came from some region in Southeast Asia around three to four thou-
                        sand years ago. As more clues are discovered, the ideas regarding the origins of
                        our people may become clearer. Today, these clues are not enough to tell us
                        why they decided to leave.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" n="b">
                        <head>LOOKING FOR A HOME</head>
                        <p>There are many reasons why people move to new places. People are still
                        moving, even today. Chamorros and other Pacific islands people may have left
                        their original homelands because they were forced to do so. Maybe their old
                        home was too crowded and food was scarce. Maybe they were not being
                        treated fairly by other groups of people. Or maybe they were adventurous. We
                        may never know why the Chamorro people moved, but we can use our imagi-
                        nations. Can you think of other reasons why they might have left?</p>

                        <p>We do know that thousands of years ago groups of people in Southeast
                        Asia began building bigger and better canoes, and sailing farther out into the
                        ocean. These ancient people became very skillful ocean navigators. They could
                        sail their canoes from place to place over great distances. In time they decided
                        not to return but to settle permanently on the islands they discovered.</p>

                        <p>Many different groups of people did this many times over thousands of
                        years. They chose different paths and eventually found all the islands of the
                        Pacific. They settled on some of the larger islands, where fresh water, plants and
                        small animals were available, and sailed to the smaller ones whenever they
                        chose.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" n="c">
                        <head>THE PACIFIC</head>
                        <p>The islands of the Pacific are divided into three areas called Micronesia,
                        Polynesia, and Melanesia. These names were given by French explorers almost
                        two hundred years ago. The suffix "nesia" comes from the Greek word "nesos,"
                        which means "islands." The prefixes "micro," "poly," and "melanin" are also
                        Greek words that mean "tiny," "many" and ''black.'' The names served as a</p>

                        <p>warning system for other European explorers. For example, "Poly (many) nesia
                        (islands)" was where many islands with fresh supplies could be found. "Micro
                        (tiny) nesia" was where islands were very small and hard to find. "Melan
                        (black) nesia" warned of "black" people who the Europeans believed were
                        savage and uncivilized.</p>

                        <p>The Europeans believed these names reflected the true nature of the island
                        people. They considered the Polynesians the most civilized islanders because
                        their skins looked golden and they had kingdoms that seemed almost better
                        than the kingdoms of Europe. The Europeans were fearful of the dark-skinned
                        Melanesians and considered them savage and dangerous because they were
                        warlike and did not seem to have rulers of any kind. The Micronesians were
                        considered "tiny" and unimportant because they were so few and scattered so
                        far apart.</p>

                        <p>These were some of the ways Europeans viewed the people and islands of
                        the Pacific in earlier times. But islanders never viewed themselves in those
                        ways. The people called "Melanesians" saw nothing wrong with their dark
                        skins, nor did they consider themselves savages. They had their own ideas of
                        right and wrong and what was civilized behavior. The "Polynesians" also had
                        their own rules of good behavior and social order. The "Micronesians" did not
                        think of themselves as unimportant,nor did they think that their world was tiny
                        at all. Their navigational skills made them masters of a huge ocean world. When
                        we consider traditional navigational technology, we see a very different picture
                        of our island world around us.</p>

                        <p>Although we still use the terms Melanesia, Polynesia, and Micronesia
                        toda~, these old European names are artificial and meaningless. The peoples of
                        the Pacific represent many different cultural traditions. And they have main-
                        tained their own distinct identities. They cannot truly be lumped together and
                        called by one, two or three names.</p>

                        <p>We live in Micronesia, the region of tiny islands. Our family of islands was
                        named the Marianas by Spanish missionaries. There are fifteen Mariana islands.
                        Guam is the largest and southernmost. We think the ancient Chamorros
                        named it Guahan, which means "we have." The islands north of Guam are:
                        Rota, Aguigan, Tinian, Saipan, Farallon de Medinilla, Anatahan, Sariguan,
                        Guguan, Alamagen, Pagan, Agrigan, Asuncion, Maug, and Fara\lon de Pajaros.</p>
                    </div>   
                    <div type="section" n="d">
                        <head>THE NAVIGATORS</head>
                        <p>To prepare for long and dangerous ocean journeys, the ancient people had
                        to think ahead. They had to decide how many people would go, how many
                        canoes they would need, and how much food and water to bring. They also
                        had to decide what things they would need to start their new lives in a new
                        place. These decisions were very important. Any mistake could cost them their
                        lives. The canoe would sink if they brought too much, and they would run out
                        of supplies if they brought too little. They had to plan very carefully and
                        everyone had to agree and cooperate. Everyone had to be willing to work
                        together to make a safe and successful journey.</p>

                        <p>The navigators may have been the first true leaders of the group. The
                        navigators were the people who knew much about the ocean and the sky. They
                        were the ones who knew how to find their way on the open sea. In some island
                        societies, only a select group of boys are taught to master the skills of canoe
                        building and ocean navigation.</p>

                        <p>The ancient navigators used many different signs to guide them on. the
                        open sea. The sky, the clouds, the stars, the wind, the currents, the waves and
                        even the movement of sea creatures and birds told them much about where they
                        were on the ocean. They were careful observers of everything around them.
                        They could "read" the clouds in the sky and the ripples of current on the surface
                        of the water. They could even tell by the color of the water if land was nearby.
                        They would also watch for floating debris which meant that land was close. The
                        navigators may have carried birds in cages. When they thought land was
                        nearby they would release the birds and watch where they flew.</p>

                        <p>The ancient travelers had to rely on the navigator's skills and knowledge to
                        get them to their destination. When they were at sea, the navigators were the
                        masters in the canoes. Everyone followed their orders. Imagine what it was like
                        to spend many days in a canoe crowded with people and their belongings and
                        supplies. It must have been very uncomfortable. There would be no space to
                        walk around. A person could not just get off and go home. If a storm came up,
                        or if the seas got rough, everyone would be in great danger. The navigators
                        were the ones to maintain order and keep everyone calm.</p>


                        <p>The ancient Chamorro navigators were very bold and daring. They were
                        also very good at their work. They found the island of Guam and brought the
                        first people to settle here.</p>

                        <p>Imagine how happy and excited the travelers were when they spotted
                        land. They could finally get out of the crowded canoes and walk around on land
                        again. But remember that the island was new and strange to them. They would
                        have had to look for fresh water and a safe campsite. They would have had to
                        go to work right away to build shelters, find water and explore the island.</p>

                        <p>Since the travelers were accustomed to taking orders from the navigators,
                        they may have called upon the navigators to make other important decisions for
                        them. The navigators may have decided where to set up camp. They may have
                        organized the first work details and sent out the first scouting parties.
                            In time, these sea-faring pioneers learned all about their new island home.
                        They eventually built permanent homes and canoe houses and established
                        permanent settlements for themselves and others who followed after them.</p>
                    </div> 
                    <div type="section" n="e">
                        <head>SETTLEMENTS</head>
                        <p>People usually settle where water and natural resources are easily available.
                        The ancient Chamorros followed the same pattern. They established settle-
                        ments along the coasts of Guam and near rivers and streams. Although there
                        are no rivers in northern Guam, there are small streams and many freshwater
                        springs and ponds along the coast. The remains of ancient settlements have
                        been found in these areas, especially in caves. In central and southern Guam
                        ancient settlements have been found along the coasts, along rivers and streams,
                        and even in the hills and valleys where the soil is good for farming. The ancient
                        Chamorros may have lived in coastal villages and tended farms and gardens in
                        the hinterlands, a practice still common to modern-day Chamorros.</p>

                        <p>Scientists and historians believe the ancient Chamorros divided the island
                        into districts. The early Spanish missionaries wrote about these districts and
                        said that the Chamorros in the northern Marianas followed the same practice.
                        These "districts," however, may have represented land owned by family clans.
                        Some were quite large and contained several small villages. Coastal districts
                        included beaches, reefs and even the ocean beyond. Any land that was not part
                        of a district was open for anyone to use.</p>

                        <p>District boundaries were marked by natural features of the land, like hills,
                        rivers and rocks, or by certain large trees. Everyone recognized and respected
                        these natural boundaries, which also served as direction markers. Even today
                        people identify their location by using such markers. Someone's land, for
                        example, might begin at the puntall acho' and extend all the way to the
                        liyangfanihi.</p>
                    </div> 
                </div>       
                <div type="unit" n="2">
                    <head>THE LIFE OF THE ANCIENT CHAMORROS</head>
                    <div type="section" n="a">
                        <head>ECONOMICS AND SOCIETY</head>
                        <p>The ancient Chamorros did not record their knowledge and history in
                        writing but in their folklore. These are the songs, stories and legends people tell
                        about themselves. Ancient Chamorro knowledge of magic, medicine and fami-
                        lies, and the tales of their actions and deeds were preserved in songs,
                        chants, and stories that have been told and retold throughout the ages.</p>

                        <p>Experts sometimes dismiss the information from folklore. They think it is
                        just imaginary and not really true. They rely instead on ancient artifacts and the
                        written records of outsiders to learn about our ancestors. They have used these
                        sources to develop several theories about how the Chamorros organized their
                        communities. While these theories have become widely accepted, we
                        think our Chamorro folklore can add valuable new information to help us
                        understand the past and the present. We have used the theories and the
                        folklore in this discussion of ancient Chamorro life.</p>


                        <p>After settling down in their new island home, the Chamorros prospered
                        and their numbers grew. Some people believe there were more than a hundred
                        thousand people in the Marianas when the Spaniards arrived. Others think
                        there were only about half that number. Whatever the case, it is clear that the
                        Chamorros were very successful at building a good life for themselves.</p>

                        <p>They further developed their farming and fishing skills and technology and
                        adapted them to their new environment. They took advantage of the island's
                        natural resources and cultivated rice, taro, sweet potatoes, bananas, yams and
                        other kinds of foods. They learned how to make medicines and discovered
                        cures for various sicknesses. They became expert fishermen and exploited the
                        ocean, catching large fish and turtles in the open sea and small fish and shell fish
                        inside the reefs. They also changed the way they built canoes. Instead of large,
                        ocean-going vessels, they perfected smaller, sleeker, faster and-more efficient
                        craft for fishing inside and outside the reefs, and for traveling between islands.</p>


                        <p>The Chamorros also refined their skills in pottery and tool making. They
                        used volcanic clay and sand to make pottery, and used igneous rocks from the
                        hills and mountains and hard shells from the ocean to make tools, jewelry, and
                        other useful and decorative items. In fact, they left a trail of their handiwork all
                        over the island. Some of their pottery, tools and implements can still be found in
                        the jungles and along the beaches. There are large tools for pounding and
                        grinding, called /using, and plenty of small cutting and carving tools. There
                        are stone hammers, adzes, awls, and rasps for building canoes and making
                        fishhooks, stone sinkers, feeders, and slings tones. And of course there are the
                        latte, but the ancient Chamorros did not build latte until about a thousand
                        years ago.</p>

                        <p>Making and using these implements and tools were important skills that
                        took many years to learn. Training would begin in childhood and the
                        knowledge would be passed on from generation to generation. Can you think
                        of anything we do today that can be traced to these ancient traditions?</p>


                        <p>The ancient Chamorros were traders. They traded their crops and catches,
                        and their tools, crafts and pottery among themselves and with people from
                        other islands. They also traded articles of traditional value, such as the rare, orange
                        spondylus shells and turtle shell, in exchange for other items of traditional value.</p>

                        <p>Our ancestors developed a society built around the concept of innfo'mnolek.
                        It was organized and had rules that governed their lives and relationship to each
                        other. In ancient Chamorro society, men and women had their own chores to do,
                        but they also shared some work. While men chose the trees and carved the wood
                        to build canoes, women gathered and prepared pandanus leaves to weave into
                        sails. Men fished in the open ocean while women fished inside the reefs. Men
                        made spears, fishing nets and fish hooks while women made pottery, baskets
                        and mats. Men probably did the work of clearing and preparing the land, but
                        both men and women planted and tended the crops together. Men and women
                        also practiced magic and herbal medicine.</p>

                        <p>Inafa'maolek is a value system still practiced today. It means sharing with one
                        another, helping one another and caring for one another.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" n="b">
                        <head>HOME AND FAMILY</head>
                        <p>Families were the most lmpuHdm part ot ancient Chamorro society.
                        Chamorro families in ancient times were very close. They did things together.
                        Every family member could count on the others for love, companionship, help
                        and security. From birth until death, family members had important parts to
                        play. Everyone had obligations and responsibilities to everyone else. Some of
                        these obligations and responsibilities were based on social rules, but most of
                        them were because families loved and cared for each other.
                            Today the term familia comes closest to what families were in ancient times.
                        Although the term is borrowed from the Spanish language, it describes an
                        "extended" family that includes brothers, sisters, parents, grandparents, great
                        grandparents, uncles, aunts, cousins, and "adopted" brothers and sisters. The
                        familia could also include close friends who were treated the same way as
                        other members of the family. The familia was not only a family of families,
                        it was a whole world in and of itself.</p>

                        <p>Whether by birth, marriage or adoption, once a person became a member
                        of a familia, he or she stayed a member forever. If a family member did
                        something very bad, that person might become an outcast That means every-
                        one would ignore him and treat him meanly, or even drive him away. But that
                        person was still considered a member of the familia. He could return if he
                        made up for the wrongs he did.                                             .</p>

                        <p>In ancient Chamorro society, the familia lived close to each other. A group
                        of families is called tronglwn rasa, or a clan. The rasa owned all the land in
                        ancient times. That is why the familia lived close to each other. When several
                        families live close together, their settlement is called a village. Depending on
                        the size of the land owned by the rasa, and the number of families in it, there
                        could be several villages in one rasa's land.</p>

                        <p>Today, you can buy land or you can inherit it from your relatives. That
                        was not the case in ancient times. Back then, only clans could own land.
                        Furthermore, women were the only people who could inherit land. The eldest
                        and highest ranking women in a clan determined who could use clan land and
                        where new homes were to be built As such, women had a great deal of power.</p>

                        <p>Women played a very important role in Chamorro society. Ancient
                        Chamorro life revolved around the role of women. Although they were very
                        influential, women were governed by rules of behavior and conduct Some of
                        these rules also applied to children. In ancient Chamorro society children
                        belonged to their mothers. They were members of their mother's clan and
                        carried her clan's name, not their father's. An example of this will be given
                        later, but first you must know some other important details of ancient Chamorro
                        social organization. It will help clarify the example.</p>

                        <p>Ancient Chamorro society grouped people according to their rank. This
                        kind of grouping is called a class system. A person automatically became a
                        member of a class at birth. His rank was not based on his wealth but on his clan
                        ties and his personal achievements. Ancient Chamorro society was divided
                        into three classes. Some experts believe there were only two classes and that the
                        third group was not a true part of ancient Chamorro society. Whatever the
                        case, we know that the ancient Chamorros were very concerned about rank and
                        class. That concern is still evident in Chamorro society today. Modem
                        Chamorros still think of themselves as "mannakhilo' " (high people) or
                        "mannakpapa'" (low people).</p>

                        <p>In ancient Chamorro sOciety, the mannakhilo class was called the Matua or
                        Chamorri. The leaders of the Chamorro people, the maga'lahi and maga'haga,
                        came from this class. The members of the Matua class were very powerful and
                        influential. They were greatly admired and highly respected, especially by
                        anyone of lesser rank.</p>

                        <p>The second class was called the Acha'ot. The members of this class were
                        the lower ranking relatives of the Matua. They could rise to the Matua class if
                        they possessed great wisdom or performed a great deed. Similarly, if a Matua
                        did not perform well, he or she could be lowered to an Acha'ot. The Matua and
                        the Acha'ot lived in the better parts of the island. Their villages were usually
                        located beside the ocean.</p>

                        <p>The lowest ranking people were known as the Manachang. We do not
                        really know their place in Chamorro society. The Spanish missionaries who
                        wrote about the Chamorro class system viewed the Manachang as small, dark
                        and weak. It is important to note that the Europeans were suspicious of dark
                        skinned "wild" people. In describing the Manachang, the missionaries may
                        have been influenced by their own fears.</p>


                        <p>Whatever their size or
                        skin color, the Mana-
                        chang were considered un-
                        civilized and inferior
                        people. The Matua and
                        Acha'ot are said to have
                        looked down upon them
                        and treated them with dis-
                        dain. Upon encountering
                        a Matua or an Acha'ot, a
                        Manachang had to bow to
                        the ground. A Mana-
                        chang, it is said, could not
                        even speak to a Matua.</p>

                        <p>The Manachang were not allowed to go near the ocean or to fish there. They
                        could only fish in the rivers and eat itu (catfish) and asuli (freshwater eels).
                        Matua and Acha'ot would never consider eating such foods. The homes of the
                        Manachang were located in the halomtano, the rough, inland jungles.</p>

                        <p>It is hard to under-
                        stand why the Chamorros,
                        who are always described
                        as friendly, generous and
                        hospitable, would treat a
                        group of people so meanly.
                        Their behavior toward the
                        Manachang is so uncharac-
                        teristic that some people
                        today question the accuracy
                        of the information about the
                        ancient Chamorro class
                        system. Some people even
                        wonder if the Manachang
                        were Chamorros at all.
                        They think the Manachang</p>

                        <p>might have been Guam's original settlers and were conquered by the early
                        Chamorros, or that they came to Guam later and refused to settle with the
                        Chamorros. The infonnation about the Chamorro cJass system comes from the
                        writings of outsiders who did not understand Chamorro culture, language and
                        SOciety. In deSCribing the Manachang, the missionaries might have
                        misunderstood what they were seeing. The Manachang may have been just a
                        group of shipwrecked people or the prisoners of a recent war. There may be
                        other explanations as to their place in Chamorro society.</p>

                        <p>In addition to their system of social ranking, the ancient Chamorros also
                        ranked the lands on which they lived. The best lands were reserved for people
                        of high rank. These lands were along the coasts, river banks, fertile hills, and
                        plains. The people of lesser rank lived in the lands surrounding these choice
                        areas. The lowest ranking people, the Manachang, lived on the least desirable
                        lands in the island's rough interior. Knowing their rank and class, clan members
                        always knew where they would live on dan land.</p>

                        <p>Now, let's go to our imaginary example: Nipa and Napu are siste.r and
                        brother. They are Matua who belong to the Niyok dan ofNomfia. Their mother
                        is a maga'haga, a first daughter, of the Niyok Oan. Uke her mother, Nipa is a
                        maga'haga. Nipa and her mother do not live in Nomfia. Although they married
                        into other dans and were required to move to their husbands' villages, they will
                        always be Niyok dan members. Napu lives in Nomfia with his wife, a woman
                        from Tokcha'. As his mother's first son, Napu is a maga1ahi of the Niyok clan.
                        He is a high ranking member of the clan.</p>

                        <p>Nipa has two sons and two daughters. All four children are Niyoks. Napu
                        also has four children, but they are members of their mother's clan in Tokcha'.
                        When Nipa's two sons are ready to become men, they will go to Nomfia to live
                        among the Niyoks. likewise, Napu's sons will return to Tokcha'. Napu will
                        then take care of Nipa's sons and teach them what they need to know. Someday
                        Nipa's oldest son will take Napu's place as the maga1ahi of Nomfia. If he
                        proves unfit, the honor and duty will go to his brother. Nipa's daughters will
                        marry men from other dans and move away, but their sons will also return to
                        Nomfia.</p>


                        <p>Napu loves his children, but he has no say in what happens to them because
                        they are not members of the Niyok clan. He does have everything to say in what
                        happens to Nipa's children, so he is closer to them. In ancient Chamorro society,
                        the relationship between uncles and their nieces and nephews was more
                        important then the relationship between fathers and their children.</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" n="c">
                        <head>THE MANMAGA'LAHI AND MANMAGA'HAGA</head>
                        <p>In our imaginary story about Napu and Nipa, Napu is the maga'lahi, the
                        chief, of Nomfia. He makes all the important decisions for the people in his
                        village, but he takes his orders regarding the clan's land from the maga'haga,
                        the highest ranking woman in the Niyok clan. The maga'haga could be his
                        grandmother or one of his mother's sisters, but in this example she is his mother.
                        Napu rules only in his own village. The other villages in the clan's district have
                        their own maga'lahi. These chiefs are Napu's uncles, brothers and nephews.
                        The highest ranking men in the clan must look after the land because their
                        mothers, aunts, sisters and nieces live in other villages.</p>

                        <p>We do not know how or why women became so important in ancient
                        Chamorro Society, but we do know that the ancient Chamorros traced their
                        family connections through their mothers. As a result, women commanded as
                        much power and respect as men. The firstborn sons and daughters of high
                        ranking women inherited their places in society. In fact, the terms maga'lahi
                        and maga'haga mean first son and first daughter. Daughters usually.moved
                        away from clan land when they got married, but sons always returned to
                        preserve the clan's control of the land. Some sons became the maga'lahi, the
                        chief.</p>

                        <p>The maga'lahi was like the village mayor, but he was not elected to this
                        position. It became his when he was born. The maga'lahi was responsible for
                        the welfare of all the farnilias in his village. The villagers came to him when they
                        needed help of any kind. The maga'lahi settled arguments between familias
                        and decided the punishment for anyone who broke the rules. He also led the
                        men of his village in battles or competitions against rival clans.</p>

                        <p>The ancient Chamorros had disputes among themselves, but they did not
                        often go to war. They often settled their disputes by challenging each other to
                        tests of skill. They would stage pretend battles or hold canoe races or sling and
                        spear throwing competitions. They would also compete in singing, story
                        telling, debates and teasing. The singing contests, such as one called the knntan
                        Chamorrita, featured opposing sides which would take turns making up
                        verses. Each side would try to outdo the other with wittier, more clever lines.
                        The kantan Chamorrita is still sung today.</p>

                        <p>When someone in the village died, the maga'lahi would perfonn the fu-
                        neral ceremony, or he would give the honor to someone who deserved a
                        reward. When important village matters needed to be discussed, the maga'lahi
                        would assemble everyone and preside over the meeting. Even children would
                        be included. All the elders of the village would sit in a large circle around the
                        maga1ahi. Behind them would sit the village's high ranking men and their
                        wives. These women were members of other clans, but they had an important
                        say in matters of village life. Unmarried young men and boys who were in
                        training and unmarried young girls would sit behind the married couples.</p>

                        <p>The ancient Chamorros had a great deal of respect for age, rank and
                        authority, and for each other. As people grew older, greater respect would be
                        paid to them by anyone who was younger. Highly respected leaders received
                        even more respect as they got older.</p>

                        <p>Because the maga'lahi was the most important person in the village, he
                        was treated in very special ways. When he came home from fishing, his people
                        would run to meet him. They would take his canoe out of the water and store it
                        for him. They would carry his catch, or his fruits and vegetables if he was
                        coming home from his gardens. When a big ocean fish was caught, the maga1ahi
                        would receive the largest and best part of it. If the maga'lahi or someone in his</p>


                        <p>family got sick, all the villagers would be very concerned. They would try to
                        help the maga1ahi by bringing the finest foods and medicines for his family.
                        They would even perform the family's chores and tend to the maga'lahi's
                        gardens until the sick person got better.
                            The maga1ahi and maga'haga were given special burials when they died.
                        Their bodies would be washed and rubbed with perfumed coconut oil. Then
                        they would be placed on fine mats made especially for them. The bodies would
                        be covered with flowers and the bark from a special tree and then wrapped in
                        the mat. The body of a maga1ahi might be placed inside his canoe along with
                        his favorite belongings. A maga'haga's body would be returned to her home
                        village to be buried in her own clan's land. Their bodies were then buried
                        beneath their houses or in caves. After a certain time, relatives would dig up
                        the graves, take the skulls and place them in a special basket inside the house.</p>

                        <p>If a maga1ahi was extraordinary, his reputation would spread far and
                        wide. People from other villages and other clans would admire him and make
                        up stories about him. Some of these stories have lasted until today, and have
                        become popular legends. One of them is about the great strength of the
                        maga'1ahi of Ina1ahan. His name was Gadao. Here is one version of his story:</p>

                        <p>One day Gadao and the men from his village went fishing beyond the reef.
                        After several hours they caught many fish and filled all their baskets. As they
                        started for shore, a huge shark appeared. The ancient Chamorros did not fear
                        sharks, but they did not like them because sharks often tore their nets, damaged
                        their fishing equipment and stole their catches. Drawn by the smell of the fish,
                        the shark began to circle Gadao's canoe. Gadao picked up his spear and waited
                        for the shark to attack. As the shark swam at them with its mouth wide open,
                        Gadao plunged the spear down its throat, killing it instantly.</p>

                        <p>When Gadao reached shore, word of his deed began to spread throughout
                        the village. It then spread throughout the island. People were 50 impressed
                        that they began to make up beautiful songs and stories about Gadao's great
                        strength. The chiefs of all the other villages became jealous. They called a
                        meeting among themselves and decided to put Gadao to the test. They gave
                        him three challenges: the first was to swim around the island twenty-five
                        times without stopping or using any help; the second was to break a coconut
                        tree into ten pieces with his bare hands; and the third was to level the
                        highest mountain on the island.</p>

                        <p>Maga'lahi Gadao accepted the challenge without blinking an eye. He
                        jumped into the water and swam around the island twenty-five times in one
                        hour! He then came ashore, grabbed a very tall coconut tree and pulled it
                        up by its roots. He cracked the trunk against his knee until it was broken into
                        ten even pieces. Afterwards, Gadao pulled up another coconut tree, stripped
                        off its nuts and leaves and sharpened it into a giant digging stick. Then he
                        climbed a mountain that was two times taller than Mount Lamlam. He
                        spent seven days and seven nights breaking it down. When he was done,
                        nothing was left but a wide, flat plain, ready for planting.</p>

                        <p>The people rejoiced and said Gadao was the strongest maga'lahi ever. This
                        made MaIaguafia, the maga'lahi of Tomhom, very jealous. The title had been
                        his before Gadao came along. Now his reputation was at stake. Not wanting
                        to lose the title, Malaguafia challenged Gadao to a showdown. They would
                        go to Orote, climb into one canoe and sit at opposite ends. Malaguafia would
                        face north and paddle toward Tomhom. Gadao would face south and
                        paddle toward Inalahan. The chief who managed to reach his own village
                        would be the winner.</p>


                        <p>On the morning of the contest, a great crowd gathered at Orote to watch
                        the two chiefs. From high on the point, they could see MaIaguafia and Gadao
                        sitting in the canoe. As the sun rose into the sky, both men began paddling as
                        hard as they could. They strained for many hours, but the canoe did not move
                        an inch. When the sun began to set, both chiefs grew more determined. They
                        paddled harder and harder. The ocean around them became white with the
                        foam of their splashing oars. Then slowly, a strange sound began to fill the air.
                        The wood of the canoe began to screech and groan. The people on the point
                        watched in amazement as the canoe began to stretch apart. Suddenly, with a
                        mighty snap, the canoe broke in two. Malaguana, sitting in one half, rowed
                        away to the north. Gadao, sitting in the other half, rowed away in the opposite
                        direction.</p>

                        <p>Neither man won the contest. It was considered a tie. But Gadao proved
                        to be the wiser of the two. After reaching Inalahan, Gadao went into a cave at
                        the edge of his village. On the walls of the cave, he drew pictures of his
                        accomplishments. His drawings are still there, even today.</p>

                        <p>Since much of ancient Chamorro history and knowledge are recorded in
                        the songs, stories, myths, and legends of Chamorro folklore, we can use folklore
                        to help us understand ancient Chamorro society. We are so used to looking for
                        answers in written sources, such as books, that we forget how to listen and
                        learn from the stories and songs that are still with us. Where can we go to hear
                        these "speaking books"? Can we remember the stories and remember how to
                        listen to the songs?</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="section" n="d">
                        <head>THE GUMA' URITAO</head>
                        <p>When they became teenagers, most boys were sent to live in their mothers'
                        villages. There they would enter the Guma' Uritao, the young men's house.
                        Remember Nipa's sons? When it came their time to return to Nomiia, they
                        would not live with Uncle Napu. Instead, they would enter the Gurna' Uritao to
                        live with all the other returning young men of the village.</p>

                        <p>The Guma' Uritao was a place for boys who were too old to live with their
                        mothers but not old enough to get married. The Guma'Uritao was a communal
                        school where they learned to become men. The grown men of Nomiia would
                        conduct the training of these boys and young men. They would teach them all
                        the skills necessary to be considered adult men.</p>

                        <p>By the time they entered the Guma' Uritao, the boys would already know
                        many skills, like hunting, fishing, swimming, sailing, planting, harvesting and
                        tool making. They would have learned these skills from their elders and from
                        observing village crafts people, as well as from the games they played as
                        children. But it was in the Gurna' Uritao that they would learn to master these
                        skills. They would learn how and when to fish beyond the reefs, how to use
                        special fishing methods, what and when to plant, and how to ensure good
                        harvests. They would also learn how to build canoes and how to navigate the
                        open sea.</p>

                        <p>The boys would also be taught about their responsibilities as men. They
                        would learn what is expected of them as husbands, uncles and members of the
                        village. They would be taught to be good storytellers and debaters. They
                        would also learn about their family and clan history, and about the clan's land.
                        These were important skills and knowledge because it was the way the Chamorro
                        people maintained and preserved their history. If the boys were destined to
                        become maga'lahi, their uncles would teach them how to be good leaders.</p>

                        <p>There were other activities that occurred at the Gurna' Uritao, some of
                        which were strictly opposed by the Spanish missionaries.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="section" n="e">
                        <head>MARRIAGE AND HOME</head>
                        <p>Although young men and women could associate freely in the Guma'
                        Uritao, they usually did not marry each other. This was because marriage was a</p>

                        <p>serious matter arranged by clan leaders. Depending on their needs and re-
                        sources, clan leaders decided who would marry who.</p>

                        <p>Marriages were not usually based on love and romance but on the benefits
                        that could result for the clans involved. For this reason, men married women
                        from other clan districts. Through marriages, clans could gain hunting, fishing
                        and gardening rights in other clan districts. They also provided a way for clans
                        to increase their influence and improve their social status. Marriages provided a
                        good way for rival clans to make peace and cement ties with each other.</p>

                        <p>When a man was ready for marriage, his mother would approach the
                        selected girl's mother with a proposal. If the proposal was accepted, the man
                        would present himself to the girl's mother in person. He would bring her gifts
                        and ask to take her daughter as his wife. This is called mamaisensaina and it is
                        still practiced today.</p>

                        <p>Because women were important in ancient Chamorro society, taking a wife
                        was an expensive matter for a groom's clan. Every girl of marrying age
                        commanded a "bride price." A bride price is what the groom's family can afford
                        to give as gifts to the bride's family for a marriage. Girls from high ranking clans
                        and girls who were already mothers commanded high bride prices. If the
                        groom's clan offered gifts worthy of the bride's rank, her clan would accept
                        them and consider the couple married. Both clans would then celebrate with a
                        great feast. Can you think of some gifts a groom's clan might offer?</p>

                        <p>Upon his marriage the groom would be assigned a piece of clan land and
                        his familia would help him build a house. The maga'haga, the highest ranking
                        woman in the groom's clan, would determine where the house was to be built,
                        and the maga'lahi would oversee its construction.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="section" n="f">
                        <head>BELIEFS</head>
                        <p>Every society has certain beliefs about the natural world and the spirit
                        world and how people fit into the picture. These beliefs help people explain and
                        understand themselves and the world around them. Some beliefs explain how
                        the world was created and how man came to live in it. Other beliefs explain the
                        difference between good and evil, and between right and wrong. All people
                        have these kinds of beliefs. They are part of what is called a people's "world
                        view."</p>


                        <p>A society's "world view" can be found in different places. It is in a society's
                        myths and legends. It is in their songs, dances and music. It is in their behavior
                        toward each other, toward outsiders, and toward their environmenl It is also in
                        the way they live their lives and in the rules they make for themselves.</p>

                        <p>Our ancestors had a "world view" in which they were in the center. They
                        believed that all life began in Guam and spread to the rest of the world. This
                        belief is contained in the legend of Puntan and his sister Fu'una. Puntan was a
                        powerful being who lived before there was an earth or a sky. Before he died,
                        Puntan gave all his powers to Fu'una and told her what to do with his body. He
                        wanted her to tum his eyes into the sun and the moon and to make his eyebrows
                        into rainbows. He told her to use his chest to make the sky and his back to make
                        the earth.</p>

                        <p>Fu'una did as she was told. When she was finished, she was amazed by the
                        beauty she had created. But the world was empty, and Fu'una was very lonely.
                        So she used her brother's power to tum herself into a large rock which fell to the
                        earth near a beautiful island. The rock split open and out came hundreds of
                        people who looked just like Fu'una and Puntan. Some of the people sailed away
                        to other lands, others stayed on the island and named it Guahan. There are
                        other versions of this legend.</p>

                        <p>The legend of Puntan and Fu'una reveals that the ancient Otamorros
                        considered themselves better than all others. The Spaniards who came to Guam
                        laughed at this idea, but the Otamorros did not change their minds. The
                        Chamorros thought the Spaniards were inferior people with strange ideas and
                        small, pale, hairy bodies, but they tried to treat them with respecl</p>

                        <p>Respect, or respetu, is very important to Chamorros. They respected each
                        other and their dead ancestors. They respected strangers. And most of all, they
                        respected nature. This respect for nature still shows in the Chamorros' belief in
                        taotaomo'na. Our practice of asking permission fromguel/a and guello to enter or
                        use the jungle comes from this ancient belief. The Otamorros believed that bad
                        things would happen to anyone who did not show proper respect for the land or
                        the sea. The Chamorros considered themselves the greatest people on earth, but
                        they believed nature was even greater.</p>

                        <p>When a people's "world view" includes a belief in someone or something
                        that is greater than themselves, it is a sign that they had some kind of religion. A</p>

                        <p>religion is a system of rules, rituals and practices that must be followed in order
                        to please the god or gods who control the natural world and the spirit world.
                        Some societies believe in one very powerful god. Other societies believe in
                        many different gods. The Chamorros believed that everything in nature had its
                        own power. They respected the powers in nature, but they did not worship
                        nature. The Chamorros worshipped their ancestors. The familia was so impor-
                        tant to them that they believed family members could affect them in good or bad
                        ways, even after death. Their religion was based on this belief. They also
                        believed that everyone had a spirit or soul, and that this spirit did not die. They
                        believed the spirit lived in a person's head. That is why they took the skulls of
                        certain dead family members and kept them in special baskets in their homes.
                        They would perform rituals over these skulls and ask their ancestors to protect
                        and guide them or help them with their problems.</p>


                        <p>The Chamorros believed that after a person died, his or her spirit stayed on
                        earth to finish any unfinished tasks and make amends for all their wrongs.
                        Afterward, the spirit would return to its place in the skull. The Chamorros also
                        believed in a "heaven" and a "hell," but not the kind of heaven and hell we
                        know today. They believed that if a person died peacefully, his spirit would go
                        to a paradise underground. Ifhe died violently, his spirit would go to a p~ce in
                        the sky called SasaIaguan, where a terrible person named Chaifj kept a roaring
                        fire. Chaifj was like a blacksmith, but instead of pieces of metal, Chaifj heated
                        spirits over the fire and hammered them into new shapes.</p>

                        <p>The early Spanish missionaries forced the Chamorros to abandon their
                        religion, but allowed some beliefs to remain. These beliefs were similar to
                        Christian beliefs. The missionaries made them fit into Christian beliefs. In
                        today's Chamorro Christian beliefs, Sasalaguan is the same as Hell. "Langit,"
                        which is the ancient Chamorro word for sky, also means Heaven. And "aniti,"
                        the ancient Chamorro word for soul, is similar to "anti," the modern Chamorro
                        word for soul. The terms "langit" and "aniti" also occur in other Southeast
                        Asian languages.</p>

                        <p>Our Chamorro ancestors also had names for a supreme being and for evil
                        spirits. These words are Yu' as and manganiti. These are not Spanish words. We
                        do not know who Yu'os was in ancient Chamorro times because the missionar-
                        ies erased this being from Chamorro memory and used the name to mean God.
                        In ancient Chamorro times, manganiti meant evil spirits. Today it means devil.
                            Our ancestors were very religious. They practiced their ancient religion,
                        and it served them well for thousands of years. But because the ancient
                        Chamorro religion was so very different from the Spanish Catholic religion, the
                        Spanish missionaries called the Chamorros pagans and heathens. And they
                        did everything they could to stamp it out. Yet, despite hundreds of years of
                        Christian missionary work, some aspects of the ancient Chamorro religion still
                        survive. The sing-song way modern Chamorros say the rosary or a nubena, for
                        instance, is similar to the way ancient Chamorros chanted in sorrow over the
                        death of a loved one.</p>
                    </div>

                    <div type="section" n="g">
                        <head>MAGIC AND MEDICINE</head>
                        <p>Before the Spaniards came to Guam, the Chamorros were healthy people.
                        In fact, the Spaniards were impressed by their size and shape. The Chamorros</p>

                        <p>were much taller and had bigger muscles. They were very strong and could do
                        things that the Spaniards could not do. The Spaniards, on the other hand, were
                        smaller and shorter. The muscles on their bodies were not well-developed.
                        They were not as physically fit as the Chamorros.</p>

                        <p>Because they were isolated on a tiny island, the ancient Chamorros did not
                        suffer from diseases like smallpox, influenza or the plague until after they came
                        in contact with foreigners. Before then, however, they did get sick sometimes.
                        They also got injured and hurt. Sometimes these illnesses or injuries would
                        heal by themselves, sometimes they would not. When this happened, the
                        Chamorros would seek specialized help.</p>


                        <p>The Chamorros blamed their ills and misfortunes on bad luck, evil spirits
                        and, sometimes, on being disrespectful. They believed that if someone got hurt
                        in an accident or got sick, it was because he or she either had offended nature or
                        because an evil spell had been cast on them. Because there were two ways to
                        get sick, there were two kinds of healers. In ancient Chamorro society, there
                        were sunmanu and suru/umQ. These men and women practiced herbal medicine
                        and massage. Then there were makahna and kalalhna. These men and women
                        practiced good and bad magic.</p>

                        <p>If someone broke a leg or had a fever, he would go to the suruhanu, a male
                        healer, or suruhana, a female healer, in his village. The suruhanu or suruhana
                        could set broken bones and take care of other injuries and sickness. They used
                        different kinds of plants and natural materials to make medicines. They also
                        massaged their patients and told them what to do to get rid of bad luck or the
                        evil spirits that caused them to get sick. The suruhanu and suruhana kept their
                        mixtures and methods secret They would share this information only with
                        apprentices who were chosen because of the way they were born.</p>

                        <p>The makahna and kakahna were shamans. They would perform certain
                        rituals over the skulls of their own ancestors to ensure good harvests, or good
                        fishing for their villages. They also cast spells to bring bad luck or misfortune to
                        someone. The makahna and kakahna used a person's body wastes to cast evil
                        spells or seek revenge on that person. As a result of this potential danger, the
                        ancient Chamorros were very careful about disposing their wastes.</p>

                        <p>In the religious system of ancestor worship, the makahna and kakahna
                        were like high priests. The ancient Chamorros were very much afraid of their
                        magical powers. As a result, the makahna and kakahna were highly influential
                        people. They did not have the same kind of power that the maga'haga and
                        maga'lahi had, but their ideas and opinions carried a lot of weight.</p>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part" n="2">
                <head>CONTACT WITH THE EUROPEANS</head>
                <div type="unit" n="1">
                    <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
                    <p>From the moment they set out in search of a new
                    home land, the ancient Chamorros knew what they
                    wanted. They wanted to live in peace and freedom.
                    And they wanted to live this way in a place they could call their
                    own. They found that place when they discovered the islands
                    that we now call the Marianas.</p>

                    <p>Life was not easy for them when they first came to these
                    islands, but they worked hard to establish homes and settle-
                    ments on many of the islands in the chain. After a while, their
                    lives became easier and better. They developed a way of life in
                    harmony with their environment. They had their own way of
                    thinking about the world and their own way of living with
                    each other. They became a peaceful, happy people who were
                    very proud of their accomplishments and very proud of them-
                    selves.</p>

                    <p>And they had good reason to be proud. They developed a
                    civilization that met all their social, religious and political needs.
                    Nature provided for all their other needs so they were careful
                    to appreciate and respect it. They developed friendly and
                    peaceful relations with other Pacific islands. And they were
                    looked upon with high esteem by their island neighbors.</p>

                    <p>The lives of our ancestors changed significantly when the
                    first Europeans came to our islands. Some people welcomed
                    the changes, others opposed them. Many of the changes brought
                    about by the Europeans were not good ones.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="a">
                    <head>A Tale about How it might have Happened</head>
                    <p>The eerie cry of the utak woke the makahna from his fitful sleep. He sat up
                    immediately and listened to the night sotmds, hoping the utak's cry was just a
                    bad dream. The utak was a bird of the night. lis strange and mournful call was
                    a bad omen. No one had ever seen an utak. but everyone knew that hearing one
                    meant something awful was about to happen. As the makahna strained to
                    listen,. the utak's cry sounded again. Worry and uncertainty troubled the
                    makahna for the rest of the night.</p>

                    <p>Early the next morning the makahna started out for the maga'lahi's house.
                    He felt he had to tell the chief about hearing the utak. But it was still dark when
                    he arrived and the makahna wondered if he had been too hasty; after all, he
                    could not say what kind of misfortune was in store, nor could he advise the
                    maga'lahi as to the precautions he should take. Before the makahna could tum
                    and walk away, the maga'lahi appeared in his doorway. The maga'lahi was the
                    taller but younger of the two. As such, the makahna paid homage to the
                    maga'lahi's rank and status, and the maga'lahi paid homage to the ~'s
                    age and wisdom.
                        After greeting each other, the maga'lahi invited the makahna to join him in
                    a meal of fish and dago which had been steamed in an underground oven by the
                    chiefs wife the day before. The makahna politely accepted the invitation, but he
                    was too worried to eat. While the maga'lahi ate heartily, the makahna nibbled a
                    few bils and pieces, enough to show his gratitude for the chiefs hospitality.
                    Afterwards, they began to discuss the utak's call and what it might have meant.</p>

                    <p>As the two men spoke, the rest of the village began to come alive with
                    activity. The air was soon filled with the sounds of laughter and voices as
                    people greeted each other and prepared their morning meal. Some women
                    were starting cooking fires in underground ovens while others spread out the
                    materials for the day's weaving. A few others were mending fish traps near the
                    canoe houses, where a new canoe was being built. The canoe builders would
                    return to the task as soon as they were done eating. Other men, too, would soon
                    get their canoes ready for a day of deep-sea fishing, which meant that later there
                    would be fish to clean and salt and spread out in the sun to dry.
                        The children, who ate their meal after the men, would soon come tumbling
                    out of their houses, eager to start their day's play. Their older brothers and
                    sisters, of course, would have chores to do first.</p>

                    <p>The maga'lahi gazed at the people of his village and wondered why misfor-
                    tune should befall them. They were a good people, very respectful, very kind to
                    each other. Oh sure, there were a couple of regrettable incidents, but nothing
                    that could anger the ancestors. The makahna's news was disturbing indeed, but
                    it made no sense. Until that moment, everything seemed fine.</p>

                    <p>The rains had been very good - not too much, not too little. And their
                    gardens had produced a generous harvest. The ocean, too, had been extra
                    generous with its bounty of fish, crabs, clams and turtles. The village had plenty
                    of food, and even more was on the way when the maiiahak (baby rabbitfish)
                    arrived. The fourth full moon was just twenty-five days away, and everyone
                    was looking forward to several days of manahak fishing. What fun it was!
                    Everyone - men, women and children - working the nets and hauling in the
                    tiny, tasty fish by the basketfuls. Some of it would be cooked on the spot to feed
                    the hungry fishermen; the rest would be packed in salt and stored or given or
                    traded away.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorros counted time by the phases of the moon. There were
                    thirteen phases to every sakkan (year). In the European calendar, it was March 6,
                    1521, but this date meant nothing to the maga'lahi who still pondered the utak's
                    warning. Did it mean that the maiiahak would not come? Was their good
                    fortune about to end? Would the dry time linger?</p>

                    <p>Just then, among the men who were getting ready to put their canoes into
                    the water, someone shouted and pointed to the horizon. Three strange shapes
                    had come into view. Someone else sounded a kulu, a shell tnunpet, to announce
                    the arrival of visitors. Excitement raced through the village. People rushed to
                    the beach to watch as the shapes drew closer. Moments later, the villagers saw
                    what looked like three fat canoes with high sides and many masts and sails.</p>

                    <p>As experienced sailors and traders, the Chamorros were accustomed to
                    receiving visitors from other islands. The funny looking ships, however, did not
                    belong to any islanders they knew. The strange ships, they decided, must have
                    come from another part of the world. Since the Chamorros believed the story of
                    Puntan and his sister, they knew they were not alone in the world. Yet, except
                    for their island neighbors, they had never received anyone else. Until today.</p>

                    <p>The word soon spread that some very new visitors had arrived. Curious to
                    see what they looked like and what strange new things they might have to trade,
                    the villagers hurriedly gathered some fruits and vegetables, some mats and
                    pottery jars and whatever else they had on hand to offer in trade. They loaded
                    their proas and began heading out to meet the ships.</p>
                        <p>Watching from a hilltop, the maga'lahi spied a large red symbol on the
                    ships' sails. It was a cross. A chill came over him. With sudden but uncertain
                    urgency, he shouted a warning to his people. But it was too late. Dozens of
                    proas were already well away from shore. Adahi hamyu, the maga'1ahi whis-
                    pered as the first wave of proas reached the ships. Was the utak's warning ah?ut
                    these strangers, the chief wondered. Were they bringing bad luck?</p>
                        <p>The Chamorros in the proas laughed as they approached the bulky, slow-
                    moving ships. The ships were big and clumsy, like sea turtles on the sand. They
                    were not at all1ike a proa, which was sleek and light and very swift. On board
                    the strange ships stood even stranger looking men with hairy faces and sun-
                    darkened pale skin. The men were watching the Chamorros with wide-eyed
                    amazement. Dozens of proas were skimming about with a speed and grace that
                    they had never seen before. In fact, they were so impressed that they called the
                    island "Isla de los Velas Latinas," the Island of Lateen Sails.</p>

                        <p>This was the beginning of the first encounter between the Chamorros and
                    Europeans.</p>

                        <p>Curious and eager to trade, the Chamorros climbed onto the great wooden
                    ships with their trade offerings. The pale strangers seemed eager to trade and
                    were most interested in the Chamorros' fresh fruits and vegetables and jars of
                    fresh water. Since neither side understood the other's language, it must have
                    been difficult to communicate. Did the strangers really want to trade, or were
                    they just hungry and thirsty?</p>

                    <p>The strangers turned out to be Spaniards. The commander of their expedi-
                    tion was a Portuguese navigator named Ferdinand Magellan. According to
                    their own version of the story, they were looking for way to reach Asia by sea
                    and had been sailing for many months. They eventually ran out of supplies and
                    were left with only rats and leather to eat, and dirty, stinking water to drink.
                    Many crewmen had gotten sick and many had died before they spotted the
                    islands of the Chamorros. They truly needed the food and water brought to
                    them by the Chamorros. But they wanted even more.</p>

                    <p>Since we only have the Spaniards' side of the story, we may never know
                    exactly what happened, but a fight broke out between the islanders and the
                    visitors. The Spaniards claimed that the Chamorros stole one of their skiffs, a
                    small boat, and tried to steal some nails and other pieces of iron. Several
                    Chamorros were wounded and killed in the fight.</p>

                    <p>Angered by the Chamorros' behavior, Magellan sent a group of soldiers
                    ashore to punish the people of the village. The soldiers burned down many
                    houses and killed at least seven more Chamorros. The Spaniards also helped
                    themselves to more supplies of food and fresh water. It is not likely that they
                    asked the Chamorros for permission to do so.</p>

                    <p>Magellan changed his mind about a name for the Chamorros' islands.
                    Instead of the Island of the Lateen Sails, Magellan called it "Isla de Los Ladrones,"
                    the island of thieves. For many centuries, the Europeans used this name to refer</p>


                    <p>to all of the Mariana islands. To this day, many people feel that Magellan did a
                    terrible injustice. Some people feel that the Spaniards were ungrateful for the
                    help they received from the Chamorros, and that the Spaniards were the real
                    thieves.</p>

                    <p>For the Chamorros of that time, their first contact with Europeans proved
                    unpleasant and dangerous. They encountered many others over the next one
                    hundred and forty years, and learned much about their customs and ways.
                    They continued to sail their proas out to greet new arrivals, but they were more
                    cautious.</p>

                    <p>On January 22, 1565, forty-four years after Magellan's visit, three new
                    ships arrived in the islands of the Chamorros. They were commanded by
                    Miguel Lopez de Legazpi, who had come to plant Spain's flag and claim the
                    islands for the King of Spain. Legazpi's first encounter with the Chamorros
                    went smoothly because he ordered his crew not to harm the Chamorros. He
                    also promised to punish anyone who did.</p>

                    <p>The Legazpi expedition stayed until February 13, 1565. On the fourth day,
                    Legazpi went ashore to plant Spain's flag. The Chamorros, of course, did not
                    understand what Legazpi's actions meant. They did not know that their island
                    had become the property of the King of Spain and that he was about to take
                    control of their lives and future as well. And the Spaniards were not about to
                    explain the details.</p>

                    <p>No one knows exactly what happened, but on February 4, a fight broke out
                    between some islanders and some of the crew who had been assigned to refill
                    the expedition's water supply. One of the crewmen was killed in the fight. 1his
                    made Legazpi very angry. Despite his orders not to harm the Charnorros,
                    Legazpi sent a hundred soldiers ashore to punish the villagers. He wanted the
                    Charnorros to know how fearsome and terrible the Spaniards could be if they
                    wanted. He also wanted to teach them a lesson so that the next set of visitors
                    would be treated with respect. Some people today feel that it was really the
                    Spaniards who were disrespectful.</p>

                    <p>Legazpi's troops marched through the village, setting fire to homes and
                    canoes, and killing anyone who tried to stop them. Many Chamorros were
                    wounded and killed. At the urging of the missionaries on board the ships,
                    Legazpi took a Charnorro prisoner. He was taken away from his home and
                    families in Guam, and sent to Mexico.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="b">
                    <head>The Search for Wealth and Power</head>
                    <p>The foreign ships that first visited Guam were searching for a
                    trade route to enrich their mother countries. Early explorers wanted
                    to find the safest sea routes to Asia, where riches like spices,
                    precious gems, silk, porcelain, gold and silver were plentiful.
                    Europeans could get to Asia by land, but the path was very
                    treacherous. It was filled with many dangers, like great moun-
                    tains and deserts, and people who were considered hostile.
                    There was a sea route around Africa, but it was controlled
                    by Portugal, Spain's arch rival. Spain wanted to find its
                    own route to the riches of Asia. Spices were among the most valuable of these
                    riches. 
                        
                        In Europe, spices like cloves, cinnamon, pepper
                    and nutmeg were as valuable as gold. Europeans
                    wanted these spices because they preserved food
                    and made it taste better. They were also usedas
                    medicines. But spices grew mainly in a distant
                    land called the Moluccas, which the Europeans
                    knew as the Spice Islands. Great wealth was in
                    store for anyone who could bring spices to
                    European markets. Countries like Spain, Por
                    tugal and the Netherlands were competing
                    to find the fastest, safest route.</p>

                    <p>Christopher Columbus was one of
                    the navigators who set out to find Asia,
                    which was then known as the Indies.
                    He believed he could find a new route
                    by sailing westward from
                    Europe.</p>

                    <p>Columbus was an Italian navigator, but he was sailing for Spain. During his voyage he
                    stumbled upon a strange new land, thinking he had reached the Indies. This
                    "new world," of course, was the Americas. For the native people living there,
                    it wasn't really new.</p>

                    <p>When everyone realized that Columbus did not find the Indies, another
                    navigator, Ferdinand Magellan, decided to continue the westward search. Like
                    Columbus, Magellan was not a Spaniard. He was Portuguese. But rather than
                    sail for his native country of Portugal, Magellan sailed for Portugal's arch rival,
                    Spain.</p>

                    <p>Magellan found a passage around the southern tip of South America, then
                    sailed into the vast Pacific Ocean. After several months at sea, his small fleet of
                    three ships arrived at Guam. We have already witnessed his encounter with
                    the Chamorro people. Magellan was killed in the Philippines, but his expedi-
                    tion eventually completed the first circumnagivation of the globe. That is, it was
                    the first to sail all the way around the world. The location of "new" lands and
                    islands, including Guam, was carefully plotted on the expedition's
                    navigational charts. This new information was added to maps of the ,Pacific so
                    that other explorers would know how and where to find these places. That is
                    how Guam became known to other explorers.</p>


                    <p>Despite Magellan's accomplishment, Spain lost the race to control the
                    spice trade. The Portuguese and the Dutch beat them to it. So Spain turned its
                    attention to the Philippines, which was rich with natural resources like timber.
                    Ahnost fifty years after Magellan's expedition, and after passing through Guam,
                    Legazpi's expedition successfully established a trade route between Mexico
                    (then known as New Spain) and the Philippines. 1his route was called the
                    Manila Galleon Trade. Guam, the largest island of the Chamorro archipelago,
                    lay directly on this route. And so the homeland of the Chamorro people, the
                    "Ladrones," as named by Magellan, became a Spanish possession.
                        But the Spaniards did not establish a permanent colony in the Ladrones
                    because the islands had no riches to exploit. The Spaniards' main interest was in
                    expanding the Spanish Empire and in exploiting the lands they had acquired in
                    North, South and Central America and in Africa, Asia and the Pacific. They
                    used Guam as a supply stop for the Spanish galleons coming from New Spain.
                    As a result, the relationship between the Chamorros and the Spaniards was
                    limited to small scale trading.</p>


                    <p>For one hundred and forty-seven years the galleons came to Guam regu-
                    larly, bringing traders, adventurers, sailors, soldiers, and the clergy, as well as
                    trade goods. These people introduced the Chamorros to many new kinds of
                    goods and to many new ideas. The Chamorros also learned much about the
                    ways of the foreigners. They did not give up all of their old ways, of course, but
                    they did adopt the foreign goods and ideas that appealed to them. One of these
                    was the love for "pika," or hot, spicy foods.</p>

                    <p>Of all these visitors, the clergymen took the most interest in the Chamorro
                    people. Some of the priests who visited wanted to stay and live among the
                    Chamorros. They wanted to teach them about the God of the Europeans. Two
                    priests actually did live with the Chamorros for brief periods. They were Fray
                    Antonio Angeles, who came in 1596, and Fray Juan Pobre de Zamora, a
                    Franciscan priest who came in 1602. These priests did not start missions among
                    the Chamorros but they did learn much about their customs and practices.
                    They recorded some of this information in their jouma1s.</p>

                    <p>From 1521 until 1668, the Spaniards did not really interfere with the
                    Chamorros' daily lives and cultural habits. The Chamorros were free to practice
                    their customs and beliefs, or to change them as they wished. They adjusted to
                    the regular visits of foreigners, and learned how to make the best of the situation.
                    Their lives, customs, beliefs and lifestyle were not subjected to change until a
                    Jesuit missiOnary named Diego Luis de San Vitores decided to bring Christianity
                    to them.</p>
                </div>

                <div type="section" n="c">
                    <head>Conversion, Conquest and Colonization</head>
                    <p>After a brief visit to Guam in 1662, Padre San Vito res became determined
                    to help the Chamorros. He had been on his way to his new assignment in the
                    Philippines when his ship stopped in Guam. As usual, the Chamorros in their
                    proas surrounded the ship, eager to trade. As he watched them, Padre San
                    Vitores began to feel sorry for them. He saw "naked" islanders who, in his way
                    of thinking, were not only without clothes but also without the knowledge
                    of the true God. Padre San Vitores felt that the Chamorros were like little
                    children who did not know right from wrong.</p>

                    <p>When Padre San Vitores discovered that a mission had not yet been estab-
                    lished in Guam, he vowed to return and start one someday. He felt that the
                    Chamorros needed his guidance and Spain's as well. Padre San Vitores went on
                    to the Philippines and became famous there. He also worked very hard in the
                    Philippines to secure the permission, support and money to return and establish
                    a mission in Guam.</p>

                    <p>Padre San Vitores encountered many stumbling blocks in his quest to
                    establish the mission because the Spanish government did not want to waste
                    any money or effort in Guam. But Padre San Vitores would not give up. He
                    finally managed to make an appeal to Mariana de Austria, the queen of Spain.
                    The queen granted his request and San Vitores received money and some
                    troops to start his mission.</p>

                    <p>San Vitores' efforts to convert the Chamorro people to Ouistianity, and
                    their response to this new religion, brought about many major changes in
                    Chamorro life. Some people think the Christianization of the islands brought
                    about some of the biggest, most dramatic and most painful changes that ever
                    took place in Chamorro society.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="d">
                    <head>The Religion of the Chamorros</head>
                    <p>Religion can be described as
                    the formal organiza tion of
                    rituals and ceremonies for
                    worshipping a supreme be-
                    ing or beings, and a way of
                    living and behaving based
                    on the beliefs of what is good
                    or bad. The first missionar-
                    ies who came to Guam had
                    their own ideas about reli-
                    gion. They believed their
                    ideas were the only true and
                    correct ones, and that any
                    others were false and wrong.</p>

                    <p>Believing finally in these ideas, the missionaries decided that the Chamorros had
                    no religion.</p>

                    <p>They looked at the Chamorros with "missionary" eyes and decided that
                    some Chamorro beliefs were "good" and others were "bad." Using their
                    European way of thinking, the missionaries even thought that some Chamorro
                    rituals and practices were the work of the devil. The Spanish padres felt they
                    had to correct ail that was "bad" about the Chamorro people. They believed it
                    was their holy duty and responsibility to teach the Catholic faith to the Chamorros
                    so that their souls could go to Heaven.</p>

                    <p>Although the padres thought the Chamorros had no religion, their writings
                    and observations tell us that the Chamorros believed in one or more supreme,
                    spiritual beings. The reports also show that the Chamorros behaved with each
                    other in a kind, loving and peaceful way. The writings of Fray Juan Pobre, for
                    instance, record many fine examples of the way Chamorros cared very much for
                    each other.</p>

                    <p>Fray Juan wrote about Chamorro acts of charity toward the sick and the
                    unfortunate, and about true acts of community fellowship in the way they
                    helped each other to rebuild homes and celebrate one another's good fortune.
                    He wrote about how food was shared generously among friends and neighbors
                    during celebrations and how people were helped in times of illness or death.
                    These descriptions showed that the Chamorros were peaceful, compassionate
                    and generous, and that
                    they behaved in a
                    "Christian-like" manner
                    before they became
                    Christians.
                    The Chamorros had
                    their own system of be-
                    liefs and rituals and had
                    practiced them long be-
                    fore the missionaries ar-
                    rived. The Chamorros
                    had their own ideas
                    about religion and about</p>

                    <p>what was right and wrong. These ideas were different in many ways from those
                    of the Europeans, but similar in many others. In his report about the missionary
                    work in the Ladrones, Andres de Ledesma wrote that the Chamorros consid-
                    ered acts of violence, cruelty and murder wrong. and that anyone who commit-
                    ted these acts was dishonorable. We can gather from this description that the
                    Chamorros respected human life and that they valued peace and gentleness
                    toward one another.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorros believed that after death a spirit would go either to a hell or
                    a place of paradise. To the Chamorros, hell was up in the sky where the winds
                    would blow the spirit around like a fallen leaf and the sun would beat down on
                    it with aU its heat They believed this to be a terrible fate. Heaven to them was
                    underground, where it was safe and secure and beautiful. They believed there
                    was a land more beautiful and more wonderful than Guam itself. And it waited
                    for them underground, if they lived a good life and died a good death.</p>

                    <p>Chamorro ideas about how the earth was made, and how men and women
                    were created were preserved in songs and stories that were sung and told
                    during celebrations. Some creation myths still survive today. They do not piace
                    importance on any particular god or gods.</p>

                    <p>A5 we have learned earlier, the Chamorros worshipped their ancestors and
                    kept some of their skulls in places of honor in their homes. They believed that
                    the spirits of the dead were to be respected and feared because they could affect
                    the lives of the living. The Chamorros also believed in the power of the
                    makahna to heal sickness, foretell the future, make rains come and bring about
                    good fortune or misfortune. The missionaries considered these beliefs and
                    practices to be very bad.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="unit" n="2">
                <head>BRINGING CHRISTIANITY TO THE CHAMORROS</head>
                <div type="section" n="a">
                    <head>Padre San Vitores and the Chamorros</head>
                    <p>Padre Luis de San Vitores is an im-
                    portant person in the political history
                    of the Marianas. 'Through his desire to
                    bring Christianity to the Chamorros he
                    steered the political history of Guam
                    into the strong winds of Spanish rule.
                    And yet, we must also consider how
                    the Chamorro people themselves
                    battled against these winds.
                    Padre San Vitores saw himself as a
                    soldier of the Catholic Church. He sin-
                    cerely believed he had to fight the forces
                    of evil and win souls for the Kingdom of God. He also believed that anyone
                    who did not share his religion could not enter Heaven. In his mind, the
                    Chamorros practiced many evil ways and were not Christians, therefore the
                    Kingdom of God was closed to them. Padre San Vitores sincerely believed that
                    his special mission in life was to come and live among the Chamorros, to turn
                    them from their evil ways, to teach them his religion and to save their souls for
                    God.</p>

                    <p>Padre San Vitores returned to Guam on June 15, 1668 with four other
                    priests, four brothers (men who were studying to become priests) and thirty-
                    two soldiers led by Captain Juan de Santa Cruz.</p>

                    <p>The sun had already set when Chamorros in the villages along Apotguan
                    Bay spotted a ship off shore. It was San Vitores' ship, the San Diego. The
                    islanders recognized the ship's Spanish banners and quickly gathered up items
                    to trade. Then they set their proas into the water. Soon there were dozens, zig-
                    zagging to and fro and racing toward the San Diego.</p>

                    <p>Like many of their countrymen before them, San Vitores' men were amazed
                    at the swiftness and agility of the Chamorro canoes, and the skill of the brown-
                    skinned natives who piloted them. Unlike San Vitores, who had seen the</p>

                    <p>impressive display during his first visit, the others in his party had never
                    witnessed anything so wonderful. There were proas everywhere around the
                    ship, and hundreds of natives shouting gleefuJJy for attention.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorros, or Indios, as the Spaniards called them, were big, strong
                    men, much taller and heavier than any Spaniard. The San Diego's passengers
                    and crew had no doubt heard many stories about the Chamorros. Indeed,
                    earlier accounts described them as very large and very strong. The stories also
                    told of how friendly the Chamorros were, but also of how fierce they could
                    become when angered. The stories also warned that the Chamorros were sly
                    and tricky, and very clever. To get a better deal for themselves they sometimes
                    traded baskets of rice weighted down with rocks.</p>

                    <p>All these stories must have been on the minds of the men on the San Diego
                    as they watched the Chamorros around them. They also must have been a little
                    afraid, but they had come to do a job and were determined to do it. They
                    believed God would keep them safe. To give themselves strength and courage,
                    Padre San Vitores and his companions began to sing and pray.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorros heard the sounds floating across the water. How unusual
                    this must have been - strange yet familiar. Although the Chamorros were
                    familiar with the Spaniards, they had never heard the Spaniards sing and chant
                    in such a manner. As they listened, someone on the ship called out to them in
                    the Chamorro language. This surely sparked their curiosity because not many
                    of the visiting foreigners bothered to learn their language. The man calling to
                    them seemed different. He seemed more open and friendly. He also seemed to
                    be in charge of all the others, but he spoke in a soft, gentle voice. The man, of
                    course, was Padre San Vitores.</p>

                    <p>Padre San Vitores beckoned again to the Chamorros, inviting them to come
                    aboard the ship. He seemed to want to talk with them, something other
                    Spaniards did not often try to do. Usually they only wanted to trade with the
                    Chamorros from on board their ships, with no invitation to come on board.</p>

                    <p>Curious about Padre San Vitores, the Chamorros responded to his friendli-
                    ness and climbed onto the ship, eager to look at him more closely and to start
                    trading with the ship's passengers.</p>

                    <p>San Vitores was more than willing to meet the Chamorros. In the Chamorro
                    language, which he had learned while in the Philippines, San Vitores asked
                    about their villages and their chiefs. He told them that he and his companions
                    had come to live among them and teach them the Christian faith.</p>

                    <p>The next morning, there were more proas surrounding the ship. The
                    soldiers with San Vitores must have been uneasy. Although they were armed
                    with muskets, the soldiers were vastly outnumbered by the hearty Indios. San
                    Vitores had forbidden them from harming any of the natives, except in self-
                    defense. As head of the new mission, Padre San Vitores had complete authority
                    over the soldiers. Later, we shall learn how this authority changed hands.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="b">
                    <head>Trouble Over Differences</head>
                    <p>We must remember that like the encounters with Magellan and Legazpi.
                    the accounts of this time were recorded by Spaniards and others. These ac-
                    counts do not always agree, nor do they include the Chamorros' side of the
                    story; therefore, the picture of what began in 1668 is unbalanced. Chamorro oral
                    and other traditions, which were handed down from one generation to another,
                    are what we have to help us understand the events more clearly.
                        On the day after his arrival, San Vitores went ashore on the beach in
                    Hagama. Earlier, he had sent two padres to introduce themselves to the leaders
                    of this village and to inform them of their mission of peace and their desire to
                    live among the islanders. A Spaniard named Pedro, who had survived a</p>


                    <p>shipwrecked Spanish galleon in 1638 and remained in Guam, heard that mis-
                    sionaries had landed. He hurried out to greet them and offer his help as
                    translator. Pedro accompanied the two padres to Hagatfia.</p>

                    <p>According to San Vitores' writings, the padres and Pedro reached Hagatfia
                    and were introduced to Kepuha, Hagatfia's highest ranking maga'lahi. But was
                    he really? Kepuha may have been just one of several chiefs in the area. Using his
                    influence, Kepuha tried to encourage his fellow chiefs to extend a characteristic
                    "Chamorro welcome" to the padres. The padres must have been quite relieved
                    to have been received in such a peaceful and friendly manner. In return for the
                    warm welcome, the padres presented the chief with iron rings and a hat that
                    pleased Kepuha very much. After their meeting with Kepuha, the padres
                    returned to San Vitores with the good news that their mission was welcome.</p>

                    <p>When San Vitores came ashore, he immediately celebrated Mass. The
                    Chamorros in the area were very curious and turned out in large numbers to
                    watch this new ritual. Their presence must have inspired San Vitores to view
                    Chamorros in a kinder light. He no longer saw Magellan's thieving natives;
                    instead he saw a gentle and generous people willing to listen to the Word of
                    God. Later, San Vitores requested and was granted permission by the queen of
                    Spain to change the name of Guam and her sister islands from Islas de los
                    Ladrones to Islas de Marianas, in honor of the queen and the Blessed Virgin
                    Mary.</p>


                    <p>ChiefKepuha was very in-
                    terested in the missionar-
                    ies and decided to help
                    them. Why do you think
                    he was interested? He
                    allowed them to build a
                    church on his clan's land.
                    Do you suppose Chief
                    Kepuha received permis-
                    sion from the maga'haga
                    to do this? The church
                    building was destroyed
                    and rebuilt many times in
                    four hundred years, but it
                    is still there. It is the Dulce
                    Nombre de Maria Cathe-
                    dral-Basilica.</p>

                    <p>And so the missionaries began their work. Chief Kepuha was among the
                    first to be baptized. His baptismal name was Juan. The missionaries believed
                    that everyone - Matua, Acha'ot and Manachang - should have the benefit of
                    baptism. In addition, they thought Kepuha's baptism would set a good ex-
                    ample for all the other Chamorros.</p>

                    <p>But Kepuha's baptism caused a great stir. According to the missionaries,
                    other chiefs became jealous of what was happ~g to Kepuha. Also, the chiefs
                    felt that only high ranking people should be baptized. This was very much
                    against the rules of Chamorro society. The idea that upper and lower class
                    people should equally participate in something angered many Chamorros. The
                    missionaries also insisted on many other changes that broke Chamorro social
                    rules. The relationship between the Chamorros and the missionaries is a very
                    important aspect of Guam's political history.</p>

                    <p>At first the Chamorros were willing to listen to the padres, but when the
                    padres began telling the Chamorros to stop doing certain things, the
                    missionaries began to lose the people's favor and trust.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorros practiced many things that the missionaries thought were
                    evil. They did not wear clothes; they encouraged unmarried young women to
                    have babies; they worshipped the skulls of their ancestors; and they believed in
                    the magical powers of the makahnas. These practices were part of the Chamorro
                    way of life, but the priests disapproved of them. They told the Chamorros that
                    their practices were evil and had to stop. The priests were neither patient nor
                    understanding about their demands, either. The padres wanted the Chamorros
                    to change immediately. They began to scold the Chamorros and criticize their
                    practices and beliefs. They told the Chamorros that they could never go to
                    Heaven and would bum in Hell forever if they did not change their evil ways.</p>

                    <p>We know that imposing one people's view on another is not acceptable.
                    But that is exactly what the missionaries did. As a result, many Chamorros
                    became bitter and angry and turned away from the missionaries.</p>

                    <p>According to San Vito res, a Chinese man named Choco, who was married to
                    a Chamorro woman, spread rumors that the water used in baptisms was poison
                    and that it caused babies to die. Choco also claimed that the missionaries
                    were evil men who were trying to harm the Chamorros, not help them. In fact,
                    people were dying. The arrival of outsiders and perhaps introduced disei\ses
                    may have been causing these deaths.</p>

                    <p>Chief Kepuha died in 1669. Since the chief was a baptized Catholic, Padre
                    San Vitores insisted on giving him a Christian burial. But Kepuha's family
                    protested this idea. As a high-ranking chief, Kepuha was supposed to be buried
                    between the latte rows under his house, or in a cave. Later, his skull was
                    supposed to be kept in a basket in a place of honor inside his home. Burying him
                    any other way would have been dishonorable and unthinkable. According to
                    San Vitores, Kepuha was buried in the churchyard. San Vitores also reported
                    that the burial not only "pleased" the chiefs family, but it also helped destroy
                    the bad habit of burying people in caves or underneath their houses.</p>

                    <p>Unfortunately for the Chamorros, the missionaries used soldiers to make
                    everyone meet their demands. The Spanish soldiers who came with San Vitores
                    were supposed to protect the missionaries. They were also supposed to make
                    sure that the Chamorros obeyed orders. Although some Chamorros accepted
                    the teachings of the missionaries, many others refused to change their beliefs.
                    These Chamorros began to tum against the missionaries.</p>

                    <p>Two months after the mission was established, a group of Chamorros
                    attacked one of the missionaries, Padre Morales, while he was preaching in</p>



                    <p>Tmian. Five days later, two more members of the mission were attacked as they
                    travelled between Saipan and Tinian. Padre Morales survived his attack, but the
                    other two did not. The incidents made the Spaniards realize that the Chamorros
                    were not going to submit to Ouistianity peacefully. The missionaries were not
                    afraid to die for their faith, but the soldiers were not eager to die. Instead, they
                    got ready to kill, too, if necessary.</p>

                    <p>As the tensions mounted between the islanders and the missionaries, open
                    confrontation began. Five months after Kepuha's death, one of San Vitores'
                    assistants was killed. The assistant had baptized a baby who later died. A few
                    months later in Tinian, San Vitores' dear friend, Padre Medina, was killed as he
                    tried to baptize a sick infant. Saddened by the death of his friend, San Vitores
                    became angry. When an old feud between two rival villages in Tinian erupted
                    in violence, San Vitores sent troops to put down the fighting. This interference
                    sparked several battles between Chamorro warriors and the Spanish troops.
                        After several months of violence, San Vitores decided to use force, but he
                    did not have enough soldiers. He wrote to the Queen of Spain and asked her to
                    send two hundred more. She again granted his request The soldiers arrived
                    after San Vitores' death.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="c">
                    <head>Chamorro Leaders Who Rebelled</head>
                    <p>The Spaniards who wrote about Spanish actions and deeds in Guam de-
                    scribed how bravely the soldiers fought and how courageous the missionaries
                    were in spite of all the troubles the Chamorros caused them. These writers
                    sometimes described the Chamorros as either murderous savages or as loyal
                    friends of the Church.
                        According to Spanish accounts, the Chamorros who helped the mission
                    were good natives. The ones who opposed the mission were bad. Today, of
                    course, we know that the Chamorros who resisted the foreigners were not
                    necessarily bad individuals, but were brave people. They cared deeply for their
                    island and their way of life, and did not want anything to change. For example,
                    there was a "rebel" chief named Hurao, who proved to be very troublesome
                    during a period of fighting in 1670.</p>

                    <p>Hurao gathered together two thousand Chamorro warriors and led them
                    on raids on Spanish camps. Olief Hurao took this action after a Chamorro
                    nobleman, a friend of his, was killed while in the custody of Spanish soldiers.
                    According to their own accoW1ts, the Spaniards were investigating the murder
                    of a boy. They arrested several suspects, including Hurao's friend, and placed
                    them under armed guard. A fight broke out between the prisoners and the
                    guards. Hurao's friend was killed. The accoW1ts do not say what happened to
                    the guard who did the killing. Perhaps he went W1punished, and perhaps this is
                    what angered Hurao. Whatever the case, Hurao decided to take action.</p>

                    <p>Olief Hurao wanted to drive out the Spaniards once and for all. He
                    mobilized his kinsmen and warriors from other clans and began attacking the
                    Spanish troops. Chamorro spears and slings, however, were no match against
                    Spanish firearms. There were many Chamorros who helped the Spaniards in
                    defending the mission. After many weeks of periodic fighting, many of the
                    Chamorros were killed or wOW1ded.</p>

                    <p>According to an early accoW1t of the period, Olief Hurao is said to have
                    made an important speech to his people. According to that accoW1t, this is
                    Hurao's speech:</p>

                    <p>The Spaniards would have done better to remain in their own country. We
                    have no need of their help to live happily. Satisfied with what our islands furnish us.
                    we desire nothing. The knowledge which they have given us has only increased our
                    needs and stimulated our desires. They find it evil that we do not dress. If that were
                    necessary. nature would have provided us with clothes. They treat us as gross people
                    and regard us as barbarians. But do we have to believe them? Under the excuse of
                    instructing us, they are corrupting us. They take away from us the primitive
                    simplicity in which we live.</p>

                    <p>They dare to take away our liberty which should be dearer to us than life itsel
                    They tty to persuade us that we will be happier, and some of us have been blinded
                    into believing their words. But can we have such sentiments if we reflect that we
                    have been covered with misery and illness ever since these foreigners have come to
                    disturb our peace?</p>

                    <p>Before they arrived on the island, we did not know insects. Did we know lats,
                    flies, mosquitoes, and all the other little animals which constantly torment us?
                    These are the beautiful presents they have made us. And what have their floating</p>



                    <p>machines brought us? Formerly, we did not have rheumatism and inflammations.
                    If we had sickness, we had remedies for them. But they have brought us their
                    diseases and do not teach us the remedies. Is it necessary that our desires make us
                    want iron and other uifles which only render us unhappy?</p>

                    <p>The Spaniards reproach US because of our poverty, ignorance and lack of
                    industry. But if we are poor, as they tell us, then what do they search for? If they
                    didn't have need of us, they would not expose themselves to so many perils and
                    make such effortS to establish themselves in our midst. For what purpose do they
                    teach us except to make tis adopt their customs, to subject us to their laws, and to
                    remove the precious liberty left to us by our ancestors? In a word, they try to make
                    us unhappy in the hope of an ephemeral happiness which can be enjoyed only after
                    death.</p>


                    <p>They treat our history as fables and fiction.       
                            
                        Haven't we the same right concerning that which they teach us as incontestable truths? 
                    They exploit our simplicity and good faith. All their skill is directed towards tricking 
                    us; all their knowledge tends only to make us unhappy. If we are ignorant and blind, as they
                    would have us believe, it is because we have learned their evil plans too late and have
                    allowed them to settle here.    
                    
                        Let us not lose courage in the presence of our misfortunes. They are only a handful. 
                    We can easily defeat them. Even though we don't have their deadly weapons which spread destruction all over, we can overcome them by our larger numbers. We are stronger than we 
                    think! We can quickly free ourselves from these foreigners!</p>

                    <p>We must regain our former freedom!</p>

                    <p>Hurao survived the battles in 1670 and continued to strike back against the
                    Spaniards throughout 1671.</p>

                    <p>Another chief, Mata'pang of Tomhom, would also come to earn a place in
                    Guam's history. Like Kepuha of Hagatfta, Mata'pang also accepted Christianity
                    and was baptized by Padre San Vitores. Unlike Kepuha, however, Mata'pang
                    later changed his mind and turned against the missionaries. The Spanish
                    accounts do not say why Mata'pang changed his mind, but they do say that
                    Padre San Vitores was disappointed.</p>

                    <p>After learning that a baby girl had been born in Mata'pang's village, San
                    Vitores decided to speak to the chief about his change of heart and to ask
                    permission to baptize the
                    newborn baby. With his
                    Filipino mission worker,
                    Pedro Calangsor, Padre
                    San      Vito res     travelled
                    overland from Pago to
                    Tomhom.        They reached
                    Mata'pang's       viIIage     on
                    the morning of April 2,
                    1672. As was the custom,
                    Padre San Vitores imme-
                    diately went to the chief's
                    house, but according to the records, Mata'pang greeted him in a very unfriendly
                    and angry manner. He refused the padre's request, then left the village.</p>



                    <p>Perhaps hoping to change the chiefs mind, San Vitores and his companion
                    remained in the viIIage, waiting for Mata'pang to return. In the meantime,
                    Mata'pang sought out his friend, Irao. Together, they planned to kill San Vitores.
                    Anned with spears and a sword, Mata'pang and Irao returned to Tomhom. As
                    soon as they spotted San Vitores and Calangsor, Mata'pang and Irao hurled
                    their spears. Calangsor was kied first. San Vitores, who wanted to die a
                    martyr's death, did not try to run away. Instead, he held up his crucifix and
                    prepared for death. Mata'pang and Irao ran toward him. Mata'pang drove a
                    spear into the padre's chest while Irao struck the back of San Vitores' head with
                    the sword. Within minutes, Padre San Vitores lay dead in a pool of blood.</p>

                    <p>Mata'pang and Irao then stripped the bodies and tied heavy stones to their
                    feet. They dragged the bodies to a canoe, dumped them inside and rowed out to
                    sea. They then threw the bod-
                    ies overboard and returned         t~l!~~
                    to the village. Later, they
                    would flee to Rota and
                    hide. They knew soldiers
                    would be after them.</p>

                    <p>The other missionaries
                    and the Spanish soldiers were
                    horrified and angered when
                    they learned of Padre San           
                    Vitores' death. The Christian                                                     
                    Chamorros were also greatly
                    saddened. It is important to                                         
                    know that while some Chamorros rejected the new Christian religion, many
                    others accepted it for various reasons. Perhaps if a the Chamorros had felt the
                    same way, they could have indeed driven the Spaniards out. But that was not
                    the case. Many Chamorros fought alongside the Spaniards to protect the
                    mission.</p>

                    <p>Today the Catholic Church considers San Vitores a martyr and a hero of the
                    Church. Most Catholics in Guam accept this. There are some people, however,
                    who do not consider San Vitores a hero because the mission he started led to
                    conflicts and the deaths of many Chamorros and Spaniards.</p>

                    <p>San Vitores's death brought about an important change in the way Guam
                    was treated as a Spanish colony. Although he was a man of the Church, San</p>

                    <p>Vitores was also in charge of the garrison of soldiers. After his death, Spanish
                    officials appointed first a commander of troops, and then later, a governor to
                    deal with the islanders. Even the missionaries felt more military force was
                    needed to protect the mission and punish those who refused to accept Ouistian-
                    ity, although the missionaries and the commander of the troops often had deep
                    conflicts among themselves.</p>

                    <p>One month after San Vitores' death, the additional soldiers that he had
                    requested arrived in Guam. Under the command of Captain Juan de Santiago,
                    they had orders to hunt down the padre's killers. Santiago's men marched into
                    Mata'pang's village and killed severa! of its inhabitants, then they burned it
                    down. In the meantime, Mata'pang and Irao and their men laid traps for the
                    soldiers. They cut down trees and blocked the road back to Hagatfia. With the
                    road blocked, the soldiers were forced to march along the beach at high tide. As
                    the Spaniards struggled in the water with their heavy armor, the warriors
                    attacked. Some of the warriors attacked from the beach, others attacked from
                    their canoes. Many of the soldiers were killed. The few who survived struggled
                    to Puntan Satpon (Hospital Point) while their Chamorro attackers paddled
                    away to Rota.</p>

                    <p>The successful ambush embarrassed and angered the Spaniards. In re-
                    venge, the Spanish soldiers attacked and burned several Chamorro villages. In
                    1674, Captain Damian de Esplana became the new commander of the troops.
                    Under Esp!afla, more Chamorros were killed and more villages were burned.
                    Still, the Chamorro "rebels" refused to give up, even though their numbers were
                    growing sma!ler and sma!ler.</p>

                    <p>In 1676, Captain Francisco de Yrrisarri was assigned as the new military
                    commander of Guam. He became the man in charge of the colony. Unlike
                    Padre San Vitores, who tried to rule with a firm but gentle hand, Captain
                    Yrrisarri was a military man. He would follow his orders until his mission was
                    accomplished, even if it meant more bloodshed.</p>

                    <p>Under this new system of military rule, the Spanish soldiers stepped up
                    their efforts to tame the Chamorros and turn them into obedient subjects of the
                    Spanish Crown. Yrrisarri's brutal treatment of the Chamorros inspired another
                    chieftain to rise up in anger. His name was Aguarin. After gathering five
                    hundred warriors together, Chief Aguarin attacked the Spanish stronghold in
                    Hagatfia. But again, their spears and slings were no match for Spanish guns.</p>



                    <p>After a fierce and bloody battle, the uprising was put down. Aguarin was
                    captured and put on trial. Captain Yrrisarri then ordered him hanged.</p>

                    <p>Of these early military governors, none was more ruthless than Captain
                    Jose de Quiroga, who governed in 1680 and again in 1688. During his first term,
                    Governor Quiroga did not wait for the Chamorro rebels to cause trouble.
                    Instead, he sent troops into the villages to track down Mata'pang and Irao, who
                    were still on the loose. Quiroga's men set fire to many villages and killed
                    hundreds of Chamorros in their search for rebel chiefs.</p>

                    <p>Quiroga later learned that Mata'pang and Irao were in Rota, along with
                    several other rebel chiefs and warriors. He sent troops there immediately. A
                    fierce battle took place. Mata'pang was captured, but was later killed in the
                    canoe ride back to Guam.</p>


                    <p>Despite the deaths of their strongest and bravest leaders, the rebel Chamorro
                    warriors continued to fight. Their numbers were growing fewer and they were
                    slowly being driven northward from island to island, but they kept fighting.
                    Fina11y, in 1695, they made one last stand on the island of Aguigan. After a short
                    battle, the Chamorros were defeated. They were given two choices: surrender
                    and return to Guam or die.</p>

                    <p>After many years of fighting and bloodshed, the Chamorro rebels realized
                    that their cause was hopeless. They could not drive out the Spaniards. With
                    defeated spirits, the Chamorro warriors surrendered. They were taken back to
                    Guam.</p>

                    <p>Shortly afterwards, the Spaniards gathered up the Chamorros who were
                    living in the other islands of the Marianas. In defeat, the Chamorro people were
                    herded together and resettled into new villages in Guam. The Spaniards had
                    established these new villages in order to keep the Chamorros under control.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorros were finally beaten. The great Chamorro nation, which
                    once numbered in the thousands and inhabited all the islands of the Marianas,
                    was reduced to a heartsick few living miserably in designated villages in Guam.
                    According to missionary accounts, there were only about five thousand Chamorro
                    people left alive by 1699.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="d">
                    <head>Guam in the Eighteenth and Nineteenth Centuries</head>
                    <p>This section is about Guam's fina1 two hundred years under Spain. We will
                    take a look at the common story about this period and identify some of the
                    problems with the story. More importantly, we will present new ways to look
                    at this period of Chamorro history and new ways to understanding.</p>

                    <p>Historians say that Guam's last two hundred years under Spain was a time
                    of isolation and decline. They say it was a time when Chamorro society declined
                    steadily. They describe Guam like a sleepy little Spanish outpost. They write as
                    if nothing important happened after the Chamorro-Spanish Wars. Except for
                    the Spanish-American War in 1898, the only events that were considered impor-
                    tant were the visits made by outsiders and certain actions made by colonial
                    officials.</p>

                    <p>This version of the story is not complete. The long period of isolation and
                    "neglect" by Spain turned out to be a valuable time and space for the Chamorros.
                    They used it to rebuild their own society.</p>

                    <p>The common story says that Guam was neglected and even forgotten by
                    Spain in the nineteenth century. This was because Spain was having many
                    problems. Its colonies in the Americas were rebelling and fighting for indepen-
                    dence. Meanwhile, inside Spain itself, the Spaniards were quarreling with each
                    other. These troubles made it difficult for Spain to pay attention to a tiny island
                    possession far away in the Pacific-especially one that had no natural resources
                    to exploit</p>

                    <p>The great Spanish Empire was already falling apart when San Vitores
                    brought his mission to Guam in 1668. Spain was already having trouble
                    maintaining its colonies then. This is a big reason why Spanish officials did not
                    support San Vitores' plan to start a mission in Guam. Officials in New Spain
                    (Mexico) and in the Philippines were not eager to help San Vitores because they
                    did not want to waste money on a tiny, faraway island.</p>

                    <p>These officials often did not help even after San Vitores received royal
                    permission. They sometimes conspired with galleon captains to bypass the
                    Marianas and to keep for themselves the money and supplies meant for Guam.
                    The Spanish officials in Guam, of course, were depending on Guam's share of the
                    Crown's money and supplies to run the little island colony.                    .'</p>

                    <p>As we saw in the last section, many Chamorros were killed in the Chamorro-
                    Spanish Wars. In defeat, the surviving Chamorros were very unhappy. Deadly
                    diseases and epidemics also claimed many lives. These epidemics, which killed
                    manypeopleata time, began in 1693 and flared up every now and then until 1900.</p>

                    <p>After the Chamorro-Spanish wars, the Chamorros were gathered from all the
                    islands of the Marianas and placed in new settlements on Guam. Bringing the
                    Chamorros together in one place made it easier for the Spaniards to control and
                    manage them. The activities in these new settlements centered around the
                    Catholic Church. The people were made to concentrate on church rituals and
                    beliefs.</p>

                    <p>Some historians believe the resettlement and subjugation of the Chamorros
                    by priests and dishonest colonial officials set the pattern for Chamorro life for the
                    next two hundred years. During this period the Chamorros suffered many
                    hardships and their lives changed in drastic ways. This is why some historians
                    think Chamorro society began to "decline." But did it really decline? We think
                    the Chamorros found new ways to enrich their culture.</p>


                    <p>In eighteenth century, Jesuits all over the world were being removed from
                    their mission stations by order of the King. This was because Spain, and even
                    the Catholic Church itself, felt that the Jesuits had become too politically power-
                    ful. San Vitores and his fellow missionaries were Jesuit priests. The King's
                    decree arrived in Guam in 1769, more than fifty years after the Chamorro-
                    Spanish Wars. Guam's Jesuits were then replaced by the Augustinian Recol-
                    lects, priests who belong to the Augustinian Order.</p>

                    <p>It is believed that the removal of the Jesuits contributed to the decline of
                    Guam's society and economy. The Jesuits since San Vitores' time were said to
                    have introduced good things like education and agricultural skills to the
                    Chamorros.</p>

                    <p>Many historians believe that the combination of wars, diseases and changes
                    in lifestyle nearly wiped out the Chamorro people. In fact, there are some
                    people who wrongly believe that all the real Chamorros disappeared in the
                    eighteenth century. They believe that was was left was a mixed race of half-
                    breeds, or mestisos, who were not truly Chamorros. This idea, which still exists
                    today, allowed colonial officials to ignore the rights of the Chamorro people.
                    This idea was also used to make it appear as if the Chamorros didnot survive
                    colonial rule.</p>

                    <p>These versions of Guam History say that Guam in the eighteenth and
                    nineteenth centuries was a forgotten and very poor colony whose inhabitants
                    were becoming more and more backward.</p>

                    <p>Much of what we know of this period comes from the writings and reports
                    of visiting explorers, missionaries and Spanish government officials. These
                    works tell of corrupt governors and officials and of the great difficulties of
                    running a colony with little or no money. For instance, in writing about the
                    eighteenth century, one historian names only one Spanish governor, Major
                    Mariano Tobias (1771-1774), who did not obstruct Guam's social economic
                    affairs.</p>

                    <p>The nineteenth century is also characterized as a period of desolation and
                    economic and social stagnation. This description was used by the few Spanish
                    governors who tried desperately to improve local conditions.</p>

                    <p>Little is written about the Chamorros themselves, except to say that most
                    were living in great poverty. Some accounts say the Chamorros were happy
                    and contented with their poor conditions; others say there were miserable and
                    dispirited.</p>

                    <p>In the common story
                    about the decline of
                    Chamorro society, the vis-
                    its of pirates, scientists,
                    whalers, convicts and po-
                    litical prisoners are told as
                    interesting highlights. The
                    story tells about what
                    these visitors did, but not
                    always about how the
                    Chamorros interacted
                    with them.
                    Indeed these visits are
                    interesting. For example,
                    English pirates often anchored their ships near Guam, waiting for the Spanish
                    galleons to make their stop. Eager for treasure, the pirates knew that the
                    westbound galleons carried gold and silver and the supplies for Guam'and the
                    Philippines. The galleon trade flourished for hundreds of years. It came to an
                    end in the nineteenth century, after the Spanish colonies in Central and South
                    America gained their independence.</p>

                    <p>The visits of French and Russian explorers and scientists are interesting
                    also. The records of scientific expeditions, such as the Malaspina expedition in
                    1792, the Kotzebue expedition in 1817 and 1825, and the Freycinet and d'Urville
                    expeditions in 1819 and 1828, include important information about life in Guam
                    at the time.</p>

                    <p>In the nineteenth century, British and American whalers also began to stop
                    in Guam and Saipan to replenish their supplies. In a year, sometimes as many as
                    sixty whaling ships would stop and stay about a month. Although many
                    whalers came to Guam, Hawaii became better known as the whaling capital of
                    the Pacific.</p>

                    <p>Before the nineteenth century, Spanish often punished certain people by
                    sending them away to a small, faraway place. Often that place was the
                    Marianas. In the nineteenth century, Spain stepped up this practice of banish-
                    ing undesirable people to our islands. These people were convincted criminals</p>



                    <p>and Mexican and Filipino political prisoners who had tried to overthrow the
                    Spaniards in their homelands.</p>

                    <p>Among aJJ these foreign visitors, some decided to stay in Guam. They
                    introduced their language, customs and ideas to the Chamorros. The staying
                    visitors also learned much from the Chamorros. Learning takes place both
                    ways. The interactions between the visitors and the Chamorros often led to
                    pennanent legacies. Today, there are many Chamorro families who trace their
                    roots to British, American, Gennan, Japanese, Otinese, Mexican and Filipino
                    visitors who became part of the community.</p>

                    <p>Throughout this book we have tried to give you a local understanding of
                    Guam history. In looking back on the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries, we
                    can now see certain noteworthy events from a local viewpoint. The visits of
                    foreigners, for instance, are not just interesting incidents during an otherwise
                    troubled or boring time. There is a direct, living connection between these
                    visitors and many Chamorros today.</p>


                    <p>For example, although Hawaii's whaling history is better known than ours,
                    the whalers who came and stayed in Guam made an important mark in our
                    history. There are Chamorro families who get their last names from whalers
                    who made Guam their home.</p>

                    <p>The whalers also introduced the English language and provided Chamorros
                    with opportunities to travel. The Chamorros who wanted to trade with the
                    whalers learned to speak English. In fact, there were Chamorros who could
                    speak English long before the Americans came and took possession of Guam in
                    1898. Some even went to live in the United States. The young Chamorro men
                    who went away to sea were called bayuneros. According to one report, eight
                    hundred bayuneros were living in Hawaii by the end of the nineteenth century.
                    Some also settled in California.</p>

                    <p>The political prisoners from Mexico and the Philippines also left their mark
                    in our history and culture. The Mexicans, for example, introduced us to com
                    and the metate , the stone tool for grinding it. The Mexicans and Filipinos
                    introduced us to foods that have become important in our culture. We ~ve
                    taken these foods - tortillas, tamales, and lechon, to name a few - and made up
                    our own way to make them. Chamorro titiyas, for example, are larger and
                    thicker than Mexican tortillas. Some historians think the Filipinos and Mexican
                    political prisoners influenced the Chamorros with radical political views. In
                    fact, several Chamorro members of the local militia were executed for political
                    crimes in 1885. The Spanish colonial government established the militia in the
                    1770s. According to the Spaniards, some militia men had conspired to over-
                    throw the colonial government of Guam and had assassinated Governor Angel
                    de Pazos Vela-Hidalgo.</p>

                    <p>The Spanish records make the incident sound like a political rebellion, but
                    some Chamorros did not believe it was. A very learned Chamorro, Pale Jose
                    Palomo (1836-1919), believed the political charges were false. Pale Palomo, the
                    first Chamorro to be ordained a Catholic priest, was a respected community
                    leader when the incident took place. He believed that certain colonial officials
                    invented the charges to make themselves look important. What actually hap-
                    pened? Why were the militia men executed? For answers, we must compare
                    what was written with the stories that recall the incident.</p>


                    <p>Another way to understand the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries from a
                    local perspective is to look at Carolinian navigators and traders who had visited
                    Guam since prehistoric times. Although their visits became infrequent during
                    the Spanish times, the Carolinians tried to re-establish traditional ties with the
                    Chamorros during the eighteenth and nineteenth centuries. By the middle of
                    the nineteenth century, there were about a thousand Carolinians settled in
                    Saipan. Another hundred or so settled in Guam in Tamuning. The records
                    mention only these two settlements. There may have been others during this
                    period.</p>

                    <p>The folklore of present day Carolinians may still contain information about
                    their ancient and modem encounters and exchanges with the Chamorros of the
                    Marianas. Among other things, their stories about being among the Chamorros
                    in the last two hundred years are not about "social decay" and "backwardness"
                    but about the makings of new lives and new homes.</p>

                    <p>From the examples of interactions between Chamorros and other visitors,
                    we can view the last two hundred years of Spanish rule differently. Rather than
                    accept the usual stories of backwardness, poverty and bad colonial administra-
                    tion, we can think of the final years of Spanish rule as a time when the Chamorro
                    people adjusted and survived. Left to themselves, they enjoyed the time and
                    space to redefine and enrich their culture and society without changing their
                    sense of peoplehood in their own homeland.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section" n="e">
                    <head>The Continuing Role of Chamorro Women</head>
                    <p>The descendants of the ancient Chamorros survived colonial rule by adapt-
                    ing to new ways.</p>

                    <p>Under the Spanish system, men replaced women as the most important
                    members of society. This was because the Spaniards imposed laws that made
                    men more important than women. In the European way of thinking, men were
                    "better" than women. Men were strong and women were weak. The word of
                    men counted more than the word of women in official community matters.
                    Men were the heads of families and households. Wives belonged to their
                    husbands. Children belonged to their fathers and carried their fathers' names.
                    The Spanish forced the Chamorros to accept these European ideas. But, as you
                    may recall, this was not what the Chamorros believed.</p>

                    <p>Although women lost much of their official power under Spanish rule,
                    their traditional importance in Chamorro society remained the same. Chamorros
                    of the eighteenth and nineteenth century slowly began to accept the importance of
                    men over women in political matters, but they did not give up the importance of
                    women in family and home matters. As a result, women continued to
                    have great influence in social and community matters as well.</p>

                    <p>In their own special way, women also continued to head Chamorro families
                    and clans. Because many Chamorro men were killed in the early battles, or died as
                    a result of introduced diseases, Chamorro women began to marry men of
                    other nationalities. But they held on to their own Chamorro ways and passed them
                    on to their children. In this way the Chamorro bloodlline and culture were
                    passed on from one generation to the next, to this very day.</p>

                    <p>Chamorro women remained the life force of the Chamorro people. As
                    wives, mothers and homemakers, they became the anchor for the Chamorro
                    family. Chamorro mothers taught their children the Chamorro language and
                    how to be Chamorro. They preserved the importance of the familia in Chamorro
                    society by maintaining powerful roles as decision makers in family matters.
                    Theytaughtfamilymembersaboutfamilyandcommunityobligatiohsandrespon-
                    sibilities, and about how to behave properly and how to be good adults. These
                    lessons, of course, were based on Chamorro values and ideas.</p>

                    <p>It was in these leadership roles that women ensured the survival of present day
                    Chamorros and their culture.</p>

                    <p>The Chamorro people continue to exist, even now. Their history is far from
                    over. This text covered only a small part of that history. The full story of Chamorros
                    is one of endurance and survival from pre-contact times to the
                    present. However, because of nearly four hundred years of colonial rule,
                    present day Chamorros do not know what it is truly like to govern themselves.
                    After so many years of being told what to do and how to think by colonial rulers,
                    some Chamorros feel that Guam should continue to be led by a higher government
                    Others feel that the Chamorro people can and should govern themselves and their
                    island.</p>

                    <p>At this time, the people of Guam are trying to arrange a new political relation-
                    ship with the United States of America. They are seeking a relationship that lets
                    them govern themselves more fully than they are presently allowed. As</p>

                    <p>this effort continues, it is important to know that we all playa part in it. TItat is
                    why we must study Guam history. Knowing what happened to our ancestors
                    and forefathers will help us decide what will happen to our children and
                    grandchildren.</p>

                    <p>Our early ancestors were said to be strong and robust. We have seen how
                    their strength and courage allowed them to survive many centuries of hardships
                    and changes. Now we can say that present day Chamorros can be as strong and
                    robust as their ancestors.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="english_glossary">
                <head>English Glossary</head>
                <p>Ancestors - Persons who lived before and have died.</p>

                <p>Ancient Chamorro Navigators - The sea-faring pioneers (those) who used the knowledge of
                nature's signs and forces to guide and direct canoes across the vast ocean and settle the
                Marianas.</p>

                <p>Apprentices - Learners or beginners.</p>

                <p>Archipelago - A group of islands in the sea.</p>

                <p>Arch rival- A competitor.</p>

                <p>Artifacts - Material objects made by human work or art.</p>

                <p>Austronesian Language Family - The family of languages which originated in the area of
                Southeast Asia.</p>

                <p>Authority - The power or right to give orders and make others obey.</p>

                <p>Beliefs - What is held to be true or correct.</p>

                <p>Bride price - In marriage, a practice where the groom's family provides gifts to the bride's
                family.</p>

                <p>Circumnavigation - To travel completely around the earth especially by water.</p>

                <p>Civilized - Behavior that is considered polite; has rules that showed the difference between
                good and unacceptable behaviors within a social group.</p>

                <p>Clan - A group of families.</p>

                <p>Class system, Chamorro - A grouping of people according to their rank in society.</p>

                <p>Colonization - Being controlled and governed by another nation.</p>

                <p>Colony - A place that is owned, controlled and governed by another nation.</p>

                <p>Communal - Belonging to the community.</p>

                <p>Conquest - The act of gaining or winning something by force.</p>

                <p>Conversion - A change of religion.</p>

                <p>Culture - The way oflife of a group of people including their customs, traditions and values.</p>

                <p>Custom - A long established way of doing things.</p>

                <p>Desolation - A miserable condition.</p>

                <p>Disdain - To consider unworthy.</p>



                <p>Districts - Spanish description for the grouping of villages of certain land areas marked by
                boundaries such as hills, rivers, rocks or large trees.</p>

                <p>Environment - Influences or surroundings that affect the existence or development of a
                people.</p>

                <p>Exploited - Made the most use of something.</p>

                <p>Folklore - Songs, stories and legends people tells about themselves handed down in time.</p>

                <p>Heathens - Those who are not Christians.</p>

                <p>Hinterland - Area of land behind a coastal district; inland area.</p>

                <p>Hospitable - Friendly.</p>

                <p>Igneous rocks - Rocks produced by intense heat.</p>

                <p>Imposing - Forcing someone to accept.</p>

                <p>Inferior - Not as good as.</p>

                <p>Injustice - Unfairness.</p>

                <p>Language Family - A group of related languages that share similarities.</p>

                <p>LaUe - Stone formations cut from limestone rock. The latte stone had two parts; the base
                called the haligi and the cap on top is called the tasa.</p>

                <p>Legends, local- Stories from early times, preserved by tradition which explain some local
                customs, geography.</p>

                <p>Limestone - Coral rock</p>

                <p>Linguists - People who study languages.</p>

                <p>Manila Galleon Trade Route - A path across the ocean between Mexico and Philippines for
                trading.</p>

                <p>Marianas - The group of 15 islands named by Padre Diego Luis de San Vitores in honor of
                Queen Mariana of Spain. These islands include: Guam, Rota, Aguigan, Tinian, Saipan
                Farallon de Medinilla, Anatahan, Sariguan Guguan, Guguan, Alamagen, Pagan, Agrigan,
                Asuncion, Maug, and Farallon de Pajaros.</p>

                <p>Marianas red ware - Earliest form of Chamorro pottery made from a type of red clay.</p>

                <p>Missionaries, Spanish - Persons sent to spread the Ca tholic religion to the native population.</p>

                <p>Mother Language - Original language from which other languages have developed; a parent
                language.</p>



                <p>Myths - Stories that explain natural events, ancient times or religious beliefs; legends about
                super beings.</p>

                <p>Nation - A community of people having a common history, tradition, culture, language and
                fonn of government uniquely to themselves.</p>

                <p>Non-native plants - Plants brought to the Marianas by the early Chamorro when they settled
                the area.</p>

                <p>Omen - A happening believed to be a warning of a future event.</p>

                <p>Oral History - The history or tradition of a people handed down from one generation to
                another by word of mouth.</p>

                <p>Pagans - Those who are not Christians.</p>

                <p>Prehistory - A period of time before written records of a people's culture.</p>

                <p>Preserved - Protected from 1055 or destruction.</p>

                <p>Proa - A smaIl fast moving Chamorro canoe.</p>

                <p>Quest - A search made in order to obtain something considered important.</p>

                <p>Rank - To hold a specific place of order in society.</p>

                <p>Refined - Made improvements, more developed.</p>

                <p>Religion - A system of rules, rituals and practices that must be foIlowed in order to please
                a god or gods.</p>

                <p>Rituals - A set of practices.</p>

                <p>Shamans - Religious specialists who get their power from supernatural forces.</p>

                <p>Society - A system of community life of individuals possessing a distinct culture.</p>

                <p>Stagnation - Not making progress; standing still.</p>

                <p>Status - Position or rank in a SOciety.</p>

                <p>Technology- The ways in which a social group provide themselves with the material objects
                to maintain, advance their culture and lifestyle.</p>

                <p>Unbalanced - Not equal.</p>

                <p>Uncivilized - Behaviors that show a lack of social rules.</p>

                <p>World View - How a person or a society views and understands the world and their place
                in it.</p>

                <p>Worshipped - Gave adoration and reverence to.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chamorro_glossary">
                <head>Chamorro Glossary</head>
                <p>Acha'ot - The second class of people in ancient Chamorro society; the relatives of the Matua.</p>

                <p>Acho' - Rock or stone.</p>

                <p>Adahi - Be careful; watch out.</p>

                <p>Afok - A creamy white substance made from roasted limestone rocks; also called lime.</p>

                <p>Aga' - Banana.</p>

                <p>Aguarin - The Chamorro maga'iahi who mobilized 500 warriors and led them on raids on
                the Spanish mission.</p>

                <p>Aniti - The ancient Chamorro word for spirit; in modem Chamorro it means evil spirit.</p>

                <p>Asuli - Eel.</p>

                <p>Bayuneros - The Chamorros who went to sea with the whalers during the 18th and 19th
                centuries.</p>

                <p>Chaife - The legendary Chamorro figure who rules Sasalaguan and molds human souls into
                new shapes.</p>

                <p>Chamorri - The highest ranking chiefs in ancient Chamorro society.</p>

                <p>Chamorro - The name of the race of people who settled the Mariana Islands; the indigenous
                people of these islands.</p>

                <p>Dagu - Wild yams.</p>

                <p>Da'ok - The palo maria tree.</p>

                <p>Eskomme - Com kernels that have been soaked in a mixture of lime and water to remove the
                hulls.</p>

                <p>Fanihi - The fruit bat; also known as "flying fox."</p>

                <p>Familia - All the members of a family, including aunts, uncles, cousins and their families.</p>

                <p>Irao - The Chamorro chief who was a friend of Chief Mata'pang.</p>

                <p>Itu - Freshwater catfish.</p>

                <p>Fu'una - The sister of Puntan in Chamorro legend; a large rock in southern Guam where
                legend says life began.</p>

                <p>Gadao - The Chamorro chief of Inalahan who had superhuman strength.</p>

                <p>Guella - A grandmother.</p>


                <p>Guello - A grandfather.</p>

                <p>Hale'-ta - Our roots or origins; how we became who we are.</p>

                <p>Hamyu - The second person (you) plural; all of you.</p>

                <p>Hurao - The Chamorro chief who mobilized 2,000 warriors to fight against the Spaniards,</p>

                <p>!fet - The ifil tree and its wood.</p>

                <p>lnafa'maolek - The Chamorro value which means taking care and getting along with one
                another.</p>

                <p>Inalahan - The southernmost village in the island of Guam.</p>

                <p>Kakahna - A kind of "medicine man" who practiced magic to bring about good or bad luck.</p>

                <p>Kantan Chamorrita - A kind of singing contest in which two groups of people take turns
                making up verses.</p>

                <p>Kepuha - The chief of Hagama who welcomed the first Spanish missionaries to Guam.</p>

                <p>Konsetba - Food that has been preserved in sugar; candied.</p>

                <p>KiJu - A shell hom.</p>

                <p>Kompaire - A godbrother.</p>

                <p>Lemmai - Breadfruit.</p>

                <p>Liyang - A cave or cavern.</p>

                <p>Lisayu - A rosary or necklace; the act of reciting the rosary.</p>

                <p>Lusong - A large heavy stone with a small, cup-shaped hole in the surface, used for pounding
                or grinding; a mortar.</p>

                <p>Maga'haga - "First daughter;" the highest ranking woman in ancient Chamorro society; the
                mother or sister of a maga'lahi. One of the important leaders in a Chamorro clan.</p>

                <p>Maga'lahi - "First son;" the highest ranking man in ancient Chamorro society; the son or
                brother of a maga'lahi. One of the important leaders in a Chamorro clan.</p>

                <p>Makahna - Another kind of magic practitioner similar to a kakahna.</p>

                <p>Malaguaiia - The Chamorro chief of Tomhom who challenged Chief Gadao to a contest of
                strength.</p>

                <p>Manachang - The lowest class in ancient Chamorro society; people who were considered
                inferior,</p>



                <p>Mamaisensaina - The formal request of a groom and his family to the parents of the bride for
                permission to get married.</p>

                <p>Maiiahak - Baby rabbit fish.</p>

                <p>Manganiti - Devil.</p>

                <p>Manmaga'haga/manmaga'lahi - Plural form of maga'haga and maga'lahi; the women and
                men who held these titles.</p>

                <p>Mannginge' - Kissing the hand of elders as a sign of respect.</p>

                <p>Mannakpapa'- People of low rank or class.</p>

                <p>Mannakhilo'- People of high rank or class.</p>

                <p>Mata'pang - The Chamorro chief of Tomhom in the 16th century who accepted Christianity,
                then later changed his mind. The chief who took Padre San Vitores' life.</p>

                <p>Matua - The highest ranking people in ancient Chamorro society.</p>

                <p>Metate - A flat stone tablet and stone roller used for grinding com.</p>

                <p>Mestisos - A person whose parents are of different races or nationalities.</p>

                <p>Nana - Mother.</p>

                <p>Napu - The imaginary male who was used to help explain how ancient Chamorro society was
                organized. Napu means ocean wave.</p>

                <p>Nipa - The imaginary female who was used to help explain how ancient Chamorro society
                was organized. Nipa is a type of palm tree that grows on riverbanks.</p>

                <p>Niyok - Coconut.</p>

                <p>Nubena - Novena; a religious prayer devotion.</p>

                <p>Pago - A wild hibiscus tree.</p>

                <p>Pika - Peppery hot; also means to chop into small pieces.</p>

                <p>Pugua' - Betelnut.</p>

                <p>Puntan - In Chamorro legend, the man whose body became all the parts of nature; puntan
                also means a point of land, or the tip of something.</p>

                <p>Rasa - A Chamorro clan; also means a race of people.</p>

                <p>Respetu - The Chamorro value of respect for persons, places, things and situations.</p>

                <p>Sakkan - The various times of harvest during the year; also means a year.</p>



                <p>Sasalaguan - In ancientChamorro beliefs, Sasalaguan wasChaife'sdomain in the sky, where
                the spirits of unworthy people went after death. In modem Chamorro, Sasalaguan means
                Hell. It is also the name of a mountain in southern Guam.</p>

                <p>Si - An article in the Chamorro language that always preceeds a person's name.</p>

                <p>Suni - Taro.</p>

                <p>Suruhana - A female healer who uses massage and plant medicines to cure sickness and
                injuries.</p>

                <p>Tano' - Land.</p>

                <p>Taotao - People; also means an individual person.</p>

                <p>Taotaomo'na - Ancestral spirits who continue to guard the land.</p>

                <p>Titiyas - Chamorro tortillas.</p>

                <p>Tokcha' - A place on the southeastern coast of Guam; also means to pierce with a sharp object.</p>

                <p>Trongkon niyok - Coconut tree.</p>

                <p>Trongkon rasa - The "clan tree," the organization of all the various families in a clan.</p>

                <p>Tomhom - An ancient Chamorro village on the northwestern coast of Guam, known today
                as Tumon.</p>

                <p>Ulak - A legendary night bird whose cries are considered omens of misfortune.</p>

                <p>Yu'os - An original Chamorro term now used 10 refer to God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <p>The Political Status Education Coordinting Commission
                wishes to thank Governor Joseph F. Ada, the 20th Guam Legisla-
                ture and the Commission on Self-Determination for their commit-
                ment to the teaching and learning of Guam's political history
                and political quest.</p>

                <p>We are thankful also to the many government agencies and
                employees, and private firms, who took personal interest in our
                project and devoted time to our effort, especially to Senator Fran-
                cisco R. Santos, Chairman, Committee on Federal and Foreign Affairs,
                22nd Guam Legislature; Senator Carl Gutierrez, Chairman, Commit-
                tee on Ways and Means, 22nd Guam Legislature; Dr. Franklin Quitugua,
                Director, Department of Education; Dr. Wilfred P. Leon Guerrero,
                President, University of Guam; Mr. John T. Cruz, President, Guam
                Community College; Mr. Leland Bettis, Executive Director, the Com-
                mission on Self-Determination; Mr. Wilson Ng; Mr. Frank C. Perez of
                the Chamorro Studies and Special Projects Divsion, Department of
                Education; Richard Biolchino, Brian Bell, Mike Shafer, Tom Shafer,
                and Kathy Duenas of Graphic Center; Mr. Steven Serville of M.1.
                Instant Print; Ms. Cherie Wegner of Marianas Electronics; the Historic
                Preservation Office, Department of Parks and Recreation; Ms. Carmen
                C. Santos; Sister Ignacia Sanchez; Mr. Frank San Agustin, Territorial
                Librarian; Mrs. Marjorie Driver, Associate Professor, Spanish Docu-
                ments Collections, Micronesian Area Research Center, University of
                Guam; Ms. Lou Pangelinan, Governor's chief of staff; Mr. Joaquin D.
                Perez, Senator Santos' chief of staff; the Governor's Washington
                Liaison Office, Terrence Villaverde; Mr. Bettis' secretary, Mary L.
                Flores; and to the former members of the Commission, Dr. Robert
                Underwood, Ms. Ernestina A. Cruz and Mr. Pete Perez, Jr.</p>

                <p>The Commission also honors the memory of former member,
                the late Pete Perez, Sr., whose unfaltering enthusiasm for this project
                was inspirational. Tun Pete did not live to see the fulfillment of our
                work, but we know he was always with us in spirit.
                The Political Status Education Coordinating Commission</p>

                <p>Mr. Antonio Palomo</p>

                <p>Chairman</p>

                <p>Community Member</p>

                <p>Senator Pilar Cruz Lujan</p>

                <p>Commission on Self-Determination</p>

                <p>John C. Salas, PhD</p>

                <p>University of Guam</p>

                <p>Mrs. Terry Duenas Hagen</p>

                <p>Guam Community College</p>

                <p>Mr. BiII Paulino</p>

                <p>Mrs. Hope Alvarez Cristobal</p>

                <p>Mr. Carmen Artero Kaspcrbauer</p>

                <p>Department of Education</p>

                
                <p>Katherine B. Aguon, PhD</p>

                <p>Executive Director</p>

                <p>Catherine Sablan Gault</p>

                <p>ResearcherfW riter</p>

                <p>Jeannine Diaz Muna</p>

                <p>Vicente M. Diaz, PhD</p>

                <p>Administrative Assistant</p>

                <p>Historian</p>

                <p>Annie Flores</p>

                <p>Arlina Santos Potts</p>

                <p>Frances T. Lujan</p>

                <p>Artist</p>

                <p>Curriculum Writer</p>

                <p>Production Designer</p>

                <p>Creating Ihe Wustratio,..for this book presented challenges because of conflicting descriptions
                of Chamorro. As far (U we know, tlae Chamorro wore no clothing. We have used discretion
                10 present them without offending those who may object to nudity in a children' book.</p>
            <div type="cover illustration">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
                <head>COVER ILLUSTRATION BY FRANK C. PEREZ</head>
                <p>Printed entirely in Guam by Cruphic Ccnu~r.lnc . MAite</p>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>