<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chamoru Legends: A Gathering of Stories</title>
                <author>Teresita Lourdes Perez</author>
                <editor>Victoria-Lola Leon Guerrero</editor>
                <translator>Maria Ana Tenorio Rivera</translator>
                <affiliation>Insider</affiliation>
                <place>Guam</place>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Taiguini Books, University of Guam Press</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Guam</pubPlace>
                <date>2019</date>
                <availability>
                    <p>All rights reserved. Please respect copyright laws.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <title>Chamoru Legends: A Gathering of Stories</title>
                    <author>
                        <persName>
                            <name>Teresita Lourdes Perez</name>
                            <affiliation>Insider</affiliation>
                        </persName>
                    </author>
                    <publisher>Taiguini Books, University of Guam Press</publisher>
                    <date>2019</date>
                    <idno type="isbn">978-1-935198-33-8</idno>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="contents">
                <head>Contents</head>
                <list>
                    <item>List of Images</item>
                    <item>Editor's Note</item>
                    <item>Foreword</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Editor's Note</head>
                <byline>Victoria-Lola Leon Guerrero</byline>
                <p>The storyteller in CHamoru culture has always been revered...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="preface">
                <head>Foreword</head>
                <byline>Dr. Sharleen Santos-Bamba</byline>
                <p>Traditions, values, and practices among the CHamoru people...</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A Story of Storytellers</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Reflection 1</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A Story of Siblings</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Pontan and Fo'na</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A Story of a Father and a Son</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Boy Who Escaped to Rota</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Love and Obligation</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Two Lovers</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A Mother, a Daughter, and a Nina</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Sirena</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Love and Misunderstanding</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Flame Tree</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Love and Coconuts</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Reflection 2</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>An Elder and a Legacy</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Coconut Tree</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Love and Survival</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Lemmai Tree</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Friendship</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Cow and the Carabao</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Vanity</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Ko'ko' and the Hilitai</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Manipulation</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Okkodo</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A Clever Man</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Juan Måla</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A Mystery</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>The Scented Woman</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>Stories That Live On</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>Reflection 3</head>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgements">
                <head>Acknowledgements</head>
            </div>
            <div type="bibliography">
                <head>Works Consulted</head>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF STORYTELLERS</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>REFLECTION 1</head>
                    <p>Auntie Diddi, my old, maiden aunt, was in the kitchen of her house when a commercial for the movie The Exorcist came on. She told me (I happened to be visiting her, and I was the one watching) that when you watch shows about the devil, the devil is watching them with you. I was covered in goosebumps and immediately thought about an invisible Satan casually sitting next to me on the living room couch, his arm draped around my shoulders.</p>
                    <p>I was hoping that commercials didn't count.</p>
                    <p>For my aunt, however, the very word “devil” sent her on a storytelling trajectory: she launched into a “one day long ago” memory of going to First Mass at the big church in Hagåtña. As she said, “Pre-War, hagå-hu.”</p>
                    <p>She woke up at dawn, which meant that she woke up late for First Mass, and because she was responsible for waking up her baby sister, baby sister was late as well. The rest of the family had already left and the two of them were the only ones remaining inside their home. They were the last ones out of the house and baby sister's tiny strides made them even more late. It was a short walk to the church, but upon nearing some bushes, a demon dog that had been hiding in them jumped out in front of the girls. Demon dog. Those were my aunt's words. It was a dog from hell with beady eyes, deadly sharp teeth, hovering menacingly over her and her little sister, blocking their path. She never explained why a demon dog appeared out of nowhere.</p>
                    <p>I never asked, but I had guessed that the dog was attempting to steer the two little girls away from church. Or, in retrospect, the dog may have been her punishment for not doing her older-sister job very well. Hearing this little horror story, I sat there frozen on her couch, transfixed by the movements of her arms, the expressions of her face, the sound of her voice, and my own mental images of her supernatural tale. In any case, I don't remember the end to the story.</p>
                    <p>Maybe my aunt never ended it.</p>
                    <p>Frankly, I didn't need to know its end. In 2018, I still don't. I choose, instead, to keep the memory of that one minute I was watching TV and of the minute after that, when I feared for the safety of my soul, and of the precious few minutes after that when I was in fear for my aunts' young lives because an otherworldly beast wanted to tear their little bodies to shreds.</p>
                    <p>My aunt was born in 1914. I had found out about the demon dog in the early 1980s. Why did I learn of it at that particular moment? What was her purpose for telling me? And why have I re-told that story to different audiences in many spaces and over many years?</p>
                    <p>When my saina told me stories, typically something in the modern world triggered their memories: a TV commercial, a game show, a lyric sung on the radio. Whatever the thing was, it had some power to shake them up, make them smile, anger them. I don't think storytelling is always didactic, or cautionary. I like to think that my aunt wanted me to share in an experience with her. Maybe she was just allowing me in – to her life, to her family, to her belief systems. As a CHamoru woman, she definitely had the authority to tell me these stories. And I had some sort of inheritance to them. I had the bloodline and the familial tie to her. And maybe in the stories' sparseness, in the questions these stories left unanswered, maybe it is in these gaps that we, the audience, learn and belong and become our own storytellers when we try to fill in the spaces.</p>
                    <p>Just last year, in my retelling of this story to my primu, the eldest son of that sleepy baby sister, he laughed out loud because he remembered his mom telling him about that exact same incident.</p>
                    <p>Our versions did not match perfectly. Nåna, he said, saw a little witch woman.</p>
                    <p>More recently, I told the story again, this time to this same primu's son, visiting the island from the states. This nephew of mine said, “Yeah, grandma told me the story of the witch woman with flowing white hair who screamed and wailed and jumped out of the bushes to scare them.” He then ended the story for me like this – Auntie Diddi overcame her little-girl fear and maneuvered her and her little sister around the supernatural being, whatever it was, and they ended up going to church. The girls waited after mass to tell their mother, my grandmother, all about it. Of course my grandmother's response to her children was that they should not have been afraid because it was just a lost soul. As I listened to my nephew tell his memory, I imagined the whole family, the two sisters most especially, praying for that terrifying, lost soul.</p>
                    <p>And so why have I re-told this story to different audiences in many spaces and over many years? I first shared it in college in the late ‘80s and early ‘90s with my hipster friends in Seattle because, frankly, people there tell fake ghost stories (which are the worst) and mostly because I missed home. In recent years, I have shared it with my cousins so we can remember my aunt, who died in 1993, and because when CHamoru cousins get together, we tell stories to remember. Now, I am sharing it with you as a storyteller who believes our indigenous ways of being and knowing are always linked to the stories we've been told and to the stories we tell, whether these stories are our extremely personal and family tales or whether they are the more commonly told legends that we share with our island community. We are linked to the storyteller.</p>
                    <p>My supernatural story, in the hands of others who tell it, takes on another form and becomes a story of a lesson in faith. But in my retellings, I prefer to keep the demon dog, and, of course, my story does not have an ending.</p>
                    <p>This particular collection of CHamoru legends of Guam has been compiled and retold from a variety of sources: I read from texts in which authors retold the legends; I read from texts which were transcribed stories told by i mañaina-ta; and best of all I listened to oral re-tellings from storytellers, whom I asked to tell or re-tell certain legends, either because I had never read the story in print before (in the case of the legend of Pontan and Fo'na) or because I simply wanted stories to hear.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF SIBLINGS</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>PONTAN AND FO'NA</head>
                    <p>In a time that cannot be traced by our memories, there were two who were brother and sister to each other, who were like gods and roamed the Great Vastness together. But the time for their shared life was to end soon. The brother felt the death of his body and foresaw his sister's grief and impending loneliness, and this caused him deep pain. He did not wish sadness upon her.</p>
                    <p>As he was dying, the brother bestowed upon his sister the knowledge that she contained within her, the powerful gift of creation, but that her life-giving force was of no use without him, just as he could never have given life to anything without her.</p>
                    <p>And as he was dying, Pontan, the brother, said to Fo'na, his sister, “In spite of your sadness, you must promise to use all the power within you combined with the power I leave behind. And only when we meet in this way, will you be able to create. Use my body to this end, and you will not be alone.” Fo'na would not hear of anything to do with his death. She resisted the idea of creating anything. She was already in mourning for her brother.</p>
                    <p>And Pontan's death did indeed come to pass. The Great Vastness expanded with a sigh, leaving Fo'na so alone in a dark space that now held within it a void, a nothingness, which she did not understand. As Fo'na held the empty shell that once was her brother, alone for the first time, she cried tears that flowed down her face to the place where her heart met her brother's head, continuing in a torrent down his chest to the place where her arms met his. And when her hand and tears mingled with his body, she felt the fullness of love. The force of it moved her hand to his back, to the place that once allowed him to stand tall and strong. Her hand, compelled by love, removed her brother's backbone. Once held within her hands, the spine formed into land, i tano', and she placed i tano' into the Great Vastness.</p>
                    <p>Fo'na felt the return of a happiness and a peace that she had believed died along with Pontan. And so with her brother, this is how Fo'na ended her emptiness and continued on with the task of creation:</p>
                    <p>She created the ocean, i tasi, with his blood.</p>
                    <p>She took his eyebrows and made each a rainbow, isa.</p>
                    <p>One of his eyes became the sun, i atdao.</p>
                    <p>The other became the moon, i pilan.</p>
                    <p>Some believe that her tears, which had flowed down her brother's body, formed the ocean currents and even became the stars in the sky, and that perhaps the locks of her hair, ripped from her scalp as she mourned, formed into the grass and trees upon landing on i tano'. Fo'na was indeed pleased with the world that sprang from her and her brother.</p>
                    <p>After the universe was complete, after every piece of the brother transformed through her wishes, and when i atdao shone upon their creation, she saw the breathtaking panorama of this world. To her, the evidence of her great love for Pontan was everywhere, yet he was nowhere. Fo'na had no one with whom to gaze upon this world, with whom to roam this new vastness that was shaped by her, through them. She could not accept this unbearable loneliness.</p>
                    <p>Situating herself where the water met the land, Fo'na took clay from i tano' and saltwater from i tasi, and enshrouding herself in this mixture, she summoned all her power so as to transform herself into a rock. Once formed, this rock firmly planted itself deep within the backbone of its brother earth. The intersection of rock and ground, of brother and sister, rumbled, shaking the earth to its core, and the rock was split in two. Out of the cleft tumbled fully formed beings, who looked very much like Pontan and Fo'na. They stumbled onto the land and shore beneath the sun and sky, and they looked upon the earth with eyes astounded at all that was bequeathed to them.</p>
                    <p>Those who decided to stay on i tano' called themselves i taotao tåno' or people of the land. Those who decided to leave traveled upon i tasi and populated the lands that reached out and away into i tasi from beyond the place of Fuha rock.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF A FATHER AND A SON</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>THE BOY WHO ESCAPED TO ROTA</head>
                    <p>The most physically perfect man in the world lived a long time ago when the tåotaomo'na, the people from before, walked more closely with their ancestors. This most muscular and agile man was surely a gift from these same ancestors, for he was as if a giant among human men, as solid a foundation as the åcho' latte. His superhuman strength protected the island and he had the respect and admiration of all who depended on him. Like this, he was held in high esteem for a long time. And like this, he lived and breathed in this adoration, expecting it, demanding it.</p>
                    <p>When he fathered a baby and the time had come for the birth, the newborn arrived so much larger than any other newborn, as the man had expected. And when the baby boy flexed his infant arms or stretched his infant calves, the man could see contours running along the baby's limbs, contours along muscles that were tiny replica of the very muscles that defined his own adult body. This strongest man was incredibly pleased to find that the child was a miniature version of himself. He marveled at the sight and was proud to have such a child.</p>
                    <p>News of the birth spread. “Surely this babe is a blessing from the ancestors, and surely this neni will be our great protector,” the people observed. The man, upon hearing these murmurings, could not believe how quickly he had been cast aside, how swift the gaze of the island shifted from him to this physically perfect baby boy. And with as much swiftness, hate sadly planted and anchored its seed deep within this man's heart. The strongest man in the world, it so happened, had very weak insides. As the days and years passed, jealousy killed any kind of fatherly love that could have been passed on to the child.</p>
                    <p>Nevertheless, the baby grew strong and fine and happy without his father's care, for the women around the child acknowledged him as a gift ginen i taotaomo'na and saw to the caring of his strength and character. As the baby grew, the man's ears could not hear the joy in his boy's laughter, nor could his eyes see the happiness in his child's smiling eyes. Instead, these interactions fed the man's jealousy. From this jealous place, he observed that the child was faster and stronger than most children; that his forearms were as large as a warrior's arms; that his torso and stomach were marked by the same deep contours found on most grown men. The son, it seemed to the father, was almost as strong as he. Almost, thought the father.</p>
                    <p>One day, walking along the beach, the man happened upon his child at play. Immediately feeling competitive, he sat on a nearby rock to observe his son. He asked the boy, “What are you doing?”</p>
                    <p>The child answered, “I am hunting ayuyu.”</p>
                    <p>The crafty ayuyu was quick, and the boy, although swift, was not as nimble as the crab. The ayuyu disappeared into a hole beneath a full-grown coconut tree. With one hand, the frustrated child uprooted the tree and, stretching with all his might, retrieved the crab with his one free hand. Victory at last! The little boy held the tree and the crab high in the air and rejoicing, looked happily at his father. But the man was speechless at the sight of the boy's achievement. He thought to himself, “Who is this child? Does his strength come from the ancestors? Do they no longer favor me?” Plagued by these questions, the strongest man shuddered to think of what the boy, grown to manhood, would and could do to his absent, unkind, unloving father. Jealousy, rage, and fear overcame the now second strongest man in the world. If any bonds of fatherhood had remained in him before this moment, they were gone.</p>
                    <p>The strongest man stood up and reached out to grab and kill his son.</p>
                    <p>The boy, who loved his father, leaned in toward him, thinking the father was reaching out for a hug. But when he saw the man's cold, dead eyes, the boy let out a pained scream and moved quickly to place himself out of the man's deadly grasp. This young child, who could've engaged in a deadly fight with his father, chose to run for his life. He ran north and kept running until the land ended and he stood at a cliff. Below him was the raging water. Behind him was the raging father. The boy chose to leap from the cliff and he leapt just in time to feel his father's fingers brush the back of his neck. This sweet and strong and smart five year old leapt from the cliff, and because he was so strong, his strength propelled his body all the way to the nearest island of Luta.</p>
                    <p>We cannot say what happened to the boy, if and how his little broken heart healed, nor do we know what happened to the cruel father. But for all time, the power and sacrifice made by this young child is etched into the landscape of this land. To this day, the imprint of the foot of this perfect boy, who was forced from his island home, can be seen on that cliff line, that place known as Pontan Påtgon. Its partner footprint can be seen at the place called Hinapsan Beach in Luta, reminding us that selfish pride can destroy even the deepest bonds.</p>
                </div>
            </div>  
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF LOVE AND OBLIGATION</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>THE TWO LOVERS</head>
                    <p>Romance does very little to ensure survival, CHamoru people in the days of the Spanish used to think. Who cares that you have love? Love cannot feed you. It is land that guarantees survival, and it is respect from the community that will help you maintain your status in life. In this story, our CHamoru heroine was born into a social class that granted her all the security the island could offer toward her survival – security ensured by the amount of land her family owned, by their reputation as benefactors to their village, by her father's Spanish ancestry, and most of all, by her beauty. Her beauty was famous. Many young island men sought after her. These suitors whispered to each other about her. They imagined staring into the warmth of her deep brown eyes, and some dared to imagine their hands resting on the generous curves of her hips. They wondered if she smelled of jungle flowers and what her dark black hair always tied up in the tightest bun looked like unbound and loose in the wind. Unfortunately for them, their whispers traveled beyond the confines of their social circles.</p>
                    <p>Word of the young woman's beauty reached the ears of a Spanish captain, and once he saw her himself, this captain decided that he must have her for his own. To the captain, this engagement was very advantageous for him: she was land rich, of European blood, and was indeed a great beauty. He confidently approached the girl's parents and asked for her hand. He knew her parents would consent. Their union would elevate the family's social standing. Had she lived in ancient times, our CHamorita would have had more of a say over her love life. Unfortunately, decisions during her lifetime required the approval of her mother and father, and her parents believed that aligning with the Spanish was the wisest form of security for their family and descendants. Her parents had their land to think of and a reputation to maintain, after all. So, mother and father granted the captain the hand of their precious daughter.</p>
                    <p>Despite their desire to shelter her, the family could not protect the girl from something with a pull more powerful than safety and security: the youthful innocence of a heart in love. It seems that the girl, unknown to her parents, responded to a very different type of suitor. She fell hard in love with a CHamoru boy, as young and beautiful as she, but who, as fate would have it, was poor. He did not have land. His family did not have the same reputation as hers. And because his poverty could never be sanctioned by the girl's family, the two lovers insisted upon living out their love in secret. They were confident in love's ability to protect them. They met with each other under the cover of night, holding hands with precious minutes to spare, making desperate pledges of love.</p>
                    <p>When the girl was summoned to a meeting with her mother and father, and the Spanish captain himself, she was told of the captain's desire to wed her. Stoically, bravely, she accepted his proposal in front of the family. In her heart, however, she hid a deep terror and a growing anger.</p>
                    <p>Under cover of night, again, with the few minutes she had to spare to be with her love, she told him, “I would rather die than marry that captain!”</p>
                    <p>And her love told her, “I would rather die than not be with you!”</p>
                    <p>When the day of her marriage came, instead of going to the wedding, she met with her love. The two ran to the place called Tomhom, which, with its dense jungle and secret caves, was a good place to hide. Once there, they chose a cave that could keep them hidden from view for at least a few days, during which time, they believed, the commotion would die down. And the cave was indeed a place for them to hope, because once inside and settled, they were able to nurture their dreams. They discovered the joy of being unfettered by the demands of family, the demands of the Spanish Crown, the demands of the village, their community, the island. In the cave, they were beholden to no one but each other. They walked upon the living earth amid the roots and leaves of the lush jungle that welcomed them; they slept in each other's arms, in the warm embers of their love. The private demands she made of him and he of her were not demands at all, but were words like honey and music like birdsong. The two lovers had built a home, however transitory, in that Tomhom cave.</p>
                    <p>In the world outside, a search party was assembled. It was not made up of concerned family members. Instead, angered by the girl's abandonment and sensing that she did not want him after all, the captain arranged for his armed troops to comb the island for his bride. The soldiers, skilled in fighting and hunting down enemies, eventually tracked the young lovers to the area in which they had sequestered themselves. Upon hearing their approach, i dos amåntes ran as fast as their feet could take them. The jungle floor gave way to a clearing that seemed to climb upwards and they slowed down their pace ever so slightly. Higher and higher they ran and closer to the edge of the island they came, the captain and his troops relentlessly pressing on them from behind. The lovers reached the edge and saw that they could run no more. The soldiers were at their heels. They looked at the whitewash of the rough water and the sharp, jagged rocks jutting up from below. What could they have been thinking at that moment? That love doesn't ensure survival? That the land will indeed take care of them? Or that they would never be apart from this day on?</p>
                    <p>It has been said that she took her hair, loose and flowing in the wind, and tied it to his long hair, and perhaps as a symbolic wedding of their own, they took each other's hands and leaped long and free into the saltwater depths of i tasi.</p>
                    <p>Although with no winners in this story, as death and sadness poisoned the tides that wedding day, perhaps it can be said that since the story lives on to this day, in some way, love does ensure survival.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF A MOTHER, A DAUGHTER AND A NINA</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>SIRENA</head>
                    <p>A mother has a tone in her voice, a certain sound that signals to her children that it is time to work: maybe to cook, to clean, or to run an errand. Maybe it's a cadence that is displeasing to the child's ear, because she contrasts that tone to the gentle sound of waves against rock or to the call of the Kingfisher flying near shore. The child longs for nothing more than to remove herself from the harsh sounds of motherhood and run toward the solace of the rocks, toward the beauty of the bird in flight, toward the peace of the water. It was this kind of beauty that proved to be too much for a young CHamoru woman named Sirena to bear. She often chased down the sounds of the shore in lieu of listening to her nåna. She often ran to the water, to feel it, to swim in it for hours and drown out the reality of chores and errands that needed completion. She swam knowing her nåna would be upset, and she felt some guilt about it.</p>
                    <p>Sirena hated disobeying and displeasing the woman who took care of her. But since she lived near the water and smelled and breathed and listened to it, Sirena wanted to swim. The desire, she felt, was harmless enough. She instinctively knew that each time she fearlessly swam against the ocean currents and swam as quick as the sea birds flew in the sky, she knew that i tasi gifted her with its deep knowledge. The ocean had powers to wake her soul. In the water, she was free. And she was home. Nothing in her life made her happier.</p>
                    <p>But every afternoon, Nåna called out to her young daughter. Nåna knew that with every moonrise, the time to bear children and run a household was encroaching upon the girl. Sirena was on the verge of adulthood and needed to listen when called to do chores. For her part, Nåna worried that Sirena would not be ready to lead a family. She imagined her long-limbed and long-haired daughter, wild and free, and she shook her head in disdain, thinking, “Her wild ways will do her no good!” Nåna was intent on teaching her daughter to take care, pay attention, be mindful, prepare and plan. Sirena did not want to plan. Nåna would scold and say things to her like:</p>
                    <p>“What kind of daughter forgets to clean?”</p>
                    <p>“What kind of household will you manage?”</p>
                    <p>“You do not listen to me, Sirena, and you will come to some trouble!”</p>
                    <p>These admonitions happened daily, and yet Sirena still did all her chores absent-mindedly. If Sirena washed clothes by the river, she found the temptation of the water running down her wrists too strong to resist. Even the tiny droplets called to her, and then she would end up wet, rising up out of the river with the wash only partially done. If Sirena went to fetch niyok for charcoal burning, she picked the trees closest to the shore and still came home empty handed, or worse yet, with wet coconuts that couldn't possibly be lit for the evening meal.</p>
                    <p>One afternoon while Sirena was sent on another errand, Nåna shared her worries with Sirena's nina. In despair, Nåna complained to the godmother. “What do I do with this one? She acts like a child all day playing in the water. What is this laziness?! What is this selfishness?! Has she no sense of duty? What is she?” Nåna placed her head in her hands.</p>
                    <p>Sitting next to her, Sirena's nina calmly said, “Sirena is a happy girl, and a happy heart should be celebrated.”</p>
                    <p>“Happiness does not feed a family. What are you talking about?”</p>
                    <p>“Sirena knows what she needs. She knows what her gifts are. She's smart, mali'. Even though she is not my blood, I am telling you, I know her. Sirena is good and kind.”</p>
                    <p>“Yes! No doubt! Sirena is kind. But I am raising a selfish, disobedient, careless child who won't think of the future, but who smiles at me with love, her eyes innocent and sparkling with hope! Yes. Yes I know. She is good. She walks in half-naked from the beach. Hah!! But then she'll only half-wash our clothes! She forgets to bring in the coconuts! She won't sweep the corners or behind the chairs! She refuses to kill the chickens and won't slice open the fish to clean them!” Nåna, her heart racing, stood up. As she stood, Nåna saw her daughter, a small shape from the window, languorously walking towards home, once again, hair falling loosely, dripping wet. Nåna could see from far away that Sirena was smiling and she noticed that once again, the laundry had not been done.</p>
                    <p>Sirena's nåna felt an anger, a grief, and a disappointment grow and turn around inside her womb, a grief and rage that only mothers can know. As soon as Sirena stepped into the house, the firestorm of rage that was growing in Nåna leapt from her heart and out her mouth. Nana's voice thundered as if it came from someone else. “Since you love the water so much, live there until you die there! You will never have children. You will never have a home!” At that unbearable moment, the echoing boom of these words threatened to tear down the walls of the house. Nåna's admonitions pierced Sirena's ears with a stabbing pain and clouded her eyes, blinding her. Sirena's instinct was to flee from a heartbreak that she didn't recognize. She blindly backed out of the house, turned and ran instinctively toward the smell of the ocean.</p>
                    <p>Sirena's nina watched her goddaughter run away from her home, toward the shore. Facing the ocean, the godmother's voice rang out cool and calm after the girl: “I claim your heart, Sirena, your mind and your heart, and because of that, I claim your womanhood for you in the places where your mind and your heart live. Your nana has taken children from you, but she cannot take the ocean from you.”</p>
                    <p>Sirena couldn't have heard the peace in her godmother's wish for her, for once in the water, she panicked. The ocean, it seemed, was rejecting her and she feared that her mother's words were going to kill her. The water raged all around her. Her arms flapped up and down; she no longer remembered how to swim and could not keep her torso or head afloat. She gasped in short spurts of breath taking in both water and air, coughing and choking. But worst of all were her legs. She lost control of her legs. They felt as though they were on fire. Had she scratched them up against the ocean rocks? She wasn't near enough to the coral reef yet, but the burning was insistent. The pain moved from her toes to her knees. She tried to use her legs to swim, but found that the fire spread to her joints, stiffened her knees, and tightly locked them in an immovable position. She was sure she would sink to the ocean floor.</p>
                    <p>Yet Sirena didn't sink. Instead, the current swept her closer to the reef, where the water cruelly (she thought) dragged her over the jagged edges of coral. She felt the flesh of her thighs grating upon those edges and wondered if she were being sliced into quarters by the sea. “The ocean wants me in pieces,” she thought desperately to herself. And it was only at this point of feeling immobile and severed that she finally cried. Her tears fell for the pain she felt, for the pain her nåna felt, and for the loss of home and of life. Sirena gave up fighting and surrendered to the ocean. Her tears mingled with the waters all around her, and when they met the ocean, the ocean calmed. Her heart gathered up a deep mournful moan for this pain and when that moan came out her throat and into the world, she thought she heard dolphins.</p>
                    <p>Sirena stopped fighting. She closed her eyes, and lay floating on the water as if to sleep. She focused on the feel of the water on her arms and back and neck. She felt the coolness of the wind hitting her wet cheeks, and the pain subsided. She opened her eyes.</p>
                    <p>Sirena noticed there were no dolphins. She noticed that the clouds were missing from i langhet. She noticed that its deep blue color merged with the blue of the ocean. She noticed these things, yet she didn't notice the ease with which her body cut through the water or how far and how fast she had swum. She didn't notice the scales, the green, silvery sheen where her legs once were. The glimmer of green she did see, she mistook for the silver-blue glare that ocean waves make in the sun. If her heart refused to let go of Nåna's hurtful words, then all Sirena wanted was for the peace of the ocean to be there with her. The ocean did not, in fact, tear her to pieces. The ocean wrapped her up and tucked her into its earth-sized blanket of serenity. And she felt as if she were the only thing that mattered in that moment. Again, she closed her eyes.</p>
                    <p>Later, much later that evening, as Nåna searched the naked horizon with an aching heart, she deeply regretted her words, because like all moms, who sometimes say regrettable things, Nåna only wanted what she thought was best for her Sirena. And although Sirena could never go back to her home, the young girl lived out the rest of her days half fish, half woman, in the body preserved for her by her godmother and in the form given to her by her Nåna, a form that most captured her spirit.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF LOVE AND MISUNDERSTANDING</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>THE FLAME TREE</head>
                    <p>Every year, as the island transitions from dry to rainy season, the Flame Tree bursts forth in blossoms the color of an otherworldly orange. In its fullest bloom, the flame tree is on fire like the brilliance of the afternoon sun, and every branch is covered in the overlapping delicacy of flower petals.</p>
                    <p>Walk up to a tree. Rest the cluster of petals in your hand; each one fans out like an open palm. Upon closer inspection of the orange petals, you will notice an oddity that can't be seen from afar: delicately interlaced in the fiery orange of a rogue petal or two are paint strokes of white – a white the color of tropical clouds, or sea foam. Or the white of a lace mantilla.</p>
                    <p>One young woman owned just such a mantilla given to her by her suitor. Up until the evening he presented this gift, the young girl used, instead, her deceased mother's mantilla to cover her head during morning prayers. Inside her little village church, as was her routine, this young woman, Elena, recited morning vespers; she prayed most often to the Virgin for her family's safety in the water, for them to have a successful catch that morning, for the daily strength to keep her home clean (sa', ai her brothers are filthy), and for skilled hands to prepare a good meal for her family. And on certain mornings, she prayed for peace and quiet to still the bad feelings that existed between her family and another family who also lived in their village.</p>
                    <p>Some nights, when her father and brothers returned home from a particularly bad day on the water, they would say things like, “That family sabotaged our fishing boats!” Or if they were particularly gloomy, they would report to her how, “that family must have paid a kakåhna to give us bad luck with the fish and winds today!” Such superstition, thought the young woman. She wondered how long this hate between families could go on. The origin of the hate was unclear, even to her. Were they really bad people? That particular family, these days, consisted only of a father and his son, Jose. She couldn't believe that those two had the ability to wreak some vague vengeance on her and her family. She had heard that her grandfather had started feuding with Jose's grandfather many years before and that maybe the feud was about land. But exactly who got cheated out of what had never been made clear to her. What was clear, however, was that her father hated Jose's father. Her brothers hated Jose.</p>
                    <p>For his part, Jose knew very clearly who Elena was. If prizes were given to the strongest heart, the bravest heart in the village, those honors would go to Elena. Her mother passed just as Elena was entering womanhood. As the only surviving female, she was tasked with taking care of a household of grown men and the entire family had to start all over again with a new captain on board. But she took on this serious responsibility with such passion and energy. She wove guåfak for their beds. She made soap to clean their clothes. She woke up earlier than her fishermen to pack their lunches neatly and securely in their pandanus bundles. Elena fed them well, keeping their backs strong to haul the talåya, to bring back fish enough to påtte with the village and to sell or trade for other food items. She budgeted the household expenses, being careful to ignore the silken white lace or fragrant oils for sale. All of her deeds and tasks, even the smallest gestures, were witnessed by the village and admired and commented upon by her neighbors.</p>
                    <p>“Elena is such a good girl.”</p>
                    <p>“What would those men do without her?”</p>
                    <p>“She is truly the head of her household!”</p>
                    <p>Jose admired her qualities as well. He noticed how her eyes radiated warmth like i tano. Her mouth was the color of a ripe mansanita. Elena, most importantly to Jose, was the kind of young woman who didn't know just how beautiful she was. Her humility shone above her beauty.</p>
                    <p>It was this humility that helped Elena accept a life that proceeded day to day in quiet predictability. She was quite happy to take care of the men in her family. She became so adept at sustaining their lives that, unbeknownst to her, her father and brothers often wondered how they would survive without her. But no one said a word directly to her. Her brothers and father loved her, and did not want to displease or upset her – she who had so much responsibility in their home and over their wellbeing. The last thing they wanted was to make her feel bad, but the truth was, they didn't want her to find love. They feared that love would make her leave them. Her brothers therefore resolved that the man her heart would choose, whoever he would be, would make his living from the sea, would be kind, yet fearless, and would make her laugh. In that way, the brothers thought, she could never think to leave them, for there were few men in their village good enough for her, or as good as they were.</p>
                    <p>Elena, however, knew of at least one who was more than good enough for her. As she waved her father and brothers off to work every morning, she would linger a little bit longer at the door to watch Jose walk the same path. Jose was known as a skilled talayeru, but he would also take the boats out into the water and fish in the deeper parts of the ocean. He was the strongest swimmer in the village (stronger even than her brothers, she had to admit) and was known to have saved a few other fishermen from drowning. Elena loved how most of all, he took tender care of his father, a widower for many years now. They, unlike her own family, had no woman to help them with the house. She often wondered what their home looked like – could it be a mess? No. She saw him wearing clean pants, a humble shirt and a woven hat to keep the sun from his eyes. She wondered if he wove the hat himself.</p>
                    <p>Her gaze, initially, portrayed only a casual interest. However, as time passed, she looked at him more intently, searching for answers about the mystery of who Jose was. And so she watched him more and more. She watched his movements – strong, agile; his walk – graceful and sure, wise like a turtle that always knows its way home. Elena, naïve as she was, remained unaware of the conflict that was growing inside her, a strange tension that was new to her. She didn't know that her daily life would cease to be enough for her.</p>
                    <p>One morning, while Jose walked to the shore as was his routine, he felt as if someone's eyes were accompanying him down the path. The feeling was so strong he turned around quickly to catch whoever it was. Behind him, Elena stood in her doorway. She shifted her gaze to the ground, ashamed at being caught, and rushed back inside her home. Jose grinned, his heart jumping for joy. He knew at that moment that what he had wanted to happen was something that she might want as well.</p>
                    <p>The next morning, instead of going fishing, Jose did a very risky thing: he went directly to the church to make sure he would be there when she arrived for prayers. As she walked in and saw him at the back of the church, she gasped and thought to herself, “Ai! What is he doing in here? What do I do?” Without realizing she was doing it, she adjusted her skirt, her mantilla. “I have to pray. I … I … have to stay,” she convinced herself. So she knelt nervously in the front row and prayed. Jose respectfully waited a few minutes. He knew what he was about to do was incredibly foolish.</p>
                    <p>“Our families hate each other,” he thought to himself. “Oh, but her smile.” And he smiled at the thought of her. Emboldened, he moved into the pew behind her. Speaking to the back of her head, he broke the silence: “I know who you are.” He heard her inhale sharply. “I'm sorry. I don't mean to frighten you. I just … I only really wanted to meet you,” he stammered, “I'm Jose.”</p>
                    <p>Elena should have left the church immediately. Instead, his presence gave her a strange comfort. His shyness made her feel strong. She tried so hard not to look at him and not to think about him, but he distracted her from her prayers. She kept uttering the Virgin's name, “Sånta Maria, Nånan Yu'os, tayuyuti ham …” She heard him breathing. In her mind's eye, she imagined the outline of his shoulders as he inhaled and exhaled and she'd give out a little cry in her mind, “Ai, Yu'os!” And again, “Sånta Maria, Nånan Yu'os tayuyuti ham …”</p>
                    <p>Jose was respectful enough of her and of Santa Maria to wait for Elena to end her prayers. And when she stood to light a candle, he remained a few feet behind her. She still had not said one word to him. And when she held the taper to the wick, he echoed her movements, found another taper and another candle to light while leaning in close enough to smell her freshly washed mantilla. He whispered to her, “I know your name. The whole village knows who you are.” She looked around to see if anyone was in the church before finally addressing him, “Hunggan, Jose.” She remained staring at the Virgin, her hands held in prayer. “I know that the village talks about me, so we can't be seen together.”</p>
                    <p>Her shaking voice forced Jose to think of a way, a safe way for her to talk with him. “I will leave messages for you, right here under Her statue. Elena, put fabot, will you take them?” And Elena, shyly looking down at her feet, nodded without a sound and consented in her heart to read whatever words he would write to her.</p>
                    <p>Over the next few days, Jose would enter the church before her and leave little pieces of paper with a simple message of love or a scribbled question. He offered a, “Si Yu'os un gineggue Maria, bula håo gråsia…” to the Virgin, and would quickly depart the church. Elena would walk in a few minutes later, kneel at the pew and utter her morning prayers. After lighting a candle, she'd snatch the paper from underneath the Virgin and hold each message tightly to read once outside the church.</p>
                    <p>Soon though, Elena started to look at the statue and wonder about the feel of Jose's hand. And Jose found himself staring at his catch of the day and not seeing fish, but thinking of her eyes. He took to sneaking behind the garden wall of Elena's home to whisper to her. She would casually linger a little too long by the vegetables to hear his gentle voice tell her about his adventures in the water that day. The two lovers knew, of course, that the path of love was incredibly stupid and hopeless. Reckless. Maybe even dangerous. But once ignited, love cannot die.</p>
                    <p>During one of their garden wall conversations, Elena's brother, looking out a window, saw his sister opening her mouth in silent prayer among the kalabåsa in the backyard. “Odd,” he thought. “Is she praying?” But he saw her smile and move her hand to cover her mouth. “She's far too happy to be praying,” he thought. The curious brother went out the front door and around to the back yard. Her giggles were louder now as were her promises of love to an invisible other. And when he peeked around the corner and saw Jose, he felt his legs ready to pounce; it took all his strength to rein in his arms and fists, to quiet his legs. He remained silent and listened to Jose's frustrated whispers:</p>
                    <p>“We cannot keep meeting like this, Elena. This hiding. This wall. The secret messages. I cannot even see you. We treat our love like it is basula! But I love you so much. And I know you love me!”</p>
                    <p>“We cannot meet in public. Jose, you know this!” She put her face in her hands, but she couldn't even cry. Not in the garden. Jose hated to hear her so upset. “Here,” he carefully threw, over the wall, a beautiful lace mantilla, as white as the sea foam. “I got this for you.” She gasped with delight, quickly took the mantilla and hid it in her skirt pocket.</p>
                    <p>“You must wear it tonight,” he continued. “As soon as your father and brothers retire for the evening, go out to the edge of the village. We will meet in the center of that grove of large trees.” Elena nodded. She knew that grove. “Wear the mantilla. It will glow in the moonlight, and I will be able to see you, even from afar.”</p>
                    <p>The brothers, crouching low to the ground, couldn't see Elena very well but recognized the scent of her clothes, and they panicked; Elena was early for her rendezvous. At that exact moment, in the middle of their panic, the brothers heard snorts, scuffling hooves, the rustling of brush and leaves, and the cracking of branches beneath heavy feet. Whatever was making that noise was behind them in the bushes. The brothers turned around just in time to see a big and very angry, wild babui making ready to attack. Eye to eye with the pig as it charged at them, the brothers took it down with their machetes, slashing at it to save their lives, yet desperately trying to stay quiet, to suppress any yells so Elena would not hear them. But of course Elena heard the struggle. She saw the round back of the babui appear above the bushes. It was huge! Its squeals and quick, wild thrashings in the nearby bushes frightened her. She ran from the grove, back to her home. In fleeing the scene, Elena did not feel the delicate, white, lace mantilla slip silently off her head.</p>
                    <p>The brothers watched her escape, and feeling proud that they had done their job in scaring her off, also went back home satisfied in knowing that Jose would arrive to a lonely grove. After the brothers left, the wounded and bloodied pig slowly made its way out of the bushes and into the open grove. It lumbered over to the tree and in its dying throes, smelling Elena's scent on the mantilla, ripped it to shreds, perhaps in anger at dying.</p>
                    <p>Jose, who had been detained by his father and cousins, snuck out of his house and showed up well past the appointed meeting time. He hoped against hope that she would be there waiting for him. As he approached the grove of trees, all he saw were the remnants of a lace mantilla torn to shreds and covered in blood. Jose stopped breathing. “What is this?” he wondered, picking up pieces of the veil and looking around to see the babui tracks and the flattened and crushed leaves and bushes where the pig had been. He screamed into the air and cursed his rash heart. He felt his spirit die inside him, because he believed that his impulsive desire to be with Elena had been the cause of her death. She was in the jungle because he told her to meet him there. “It's my fault that she is dead,” he cried in despair. He decided he would die with her. Blinded by his tears, he felt for his fishing knife. He grabbed it from his belt and stabbed himself deep, deep in his heart. He fell on top of the shreds of bloody lace. He didn't die immediately, but bled on the tattered veil, inhaling Elena's scent, the last few traces of her like a dream, as he slowly fell away from the world.</p>
                    <p>Hours later, with her brothers and father sleeping soundly and secure in their beds, Elena snuck out of her house hoping against hope that Jose showed up and decided to stay even though she was not there. Maybe he'd be asleep in the grove, dreaming that she would return. Brave Elena arrived in the dead of night to the grove and found her beautiful Jose asleep, nestled within the thick roots of one of the largest trees there. She smiled and her heart leapt. She felt alive and ready to be held by him and to fall asleep under the stars. But when she got closer and spotted what looked like little streaks of white covered in red, she feared that her brothers had done something drastic. She slowed down, walked carefully toward her love, her bare feet covered in the stickiness of the bloodied leaves, and saw the fishing knife stuck deep in his chest. She knelt beside him. Elena did not scream out loud. Her eyes widened in terror and she calmly whispered to him, “Hu guaiya håo, my love. Oh Jose, I know you can hear me. Hu guaiya håo, asaguå-hu.” She glanced one more time at her beautiful Jose, brave and kind and strong. She pulled out his knife and plunged it deep inside her heart, where she, too, bled a river of sadness and loneliness that covered the shredded lace mantilla, the roots of the tree, and the earth all around them.</p>
                    <p>The men in both of these families, upon waking at the usual hour to go fishing, discovered their missing children. “But she came home, Tåta. We saw her!” The father immediately went to Jose's house and angrily pounded on the door, “Jose! Where is my daughter? Elena will never belong to you!” The door flew open, Jose's father stood strong, an arm holding a club. “Your daughter isn't here and neither is my son!” Elena's father grew anxious. “Come with us, then. They must have spent the night in the grove.”</p>
                    <p>The men ran toward the lovers' meeting place to put a stop to what they feared had already happened. What if they were too late? As they edged closer to the trees, the brothers recognized the grove from the night before, but it looked and felt different. “They were supposed to meet next to that large tree up there, Tåta, but…” Their thoughts were interrupted at the sight of the tree, which was no longer old and withering, but lush and fuller than it was the evening before. Did it look alive? The men immediately felt fugu. They stopped running towards the tree. From where they stood, it looked as if it were dripping red. The brothers were so sure that this was the place, but they approached the center of the grove more slowly, cautiously. Something was wrong. They spied the lovers lying next to each other under the tree, but they also noticed how the earth was covered in a sea of orange-red petals. And as they got closer, they saw that the petals weren't petals after all, but rather the ground, the rocks, the jutting roots, the grass all covered in a pool of blood. The tree, seemingly alive and breathing, appeared to be soaking in the red and bloodied earth. When they were within arm's reach of the lovers, Jose's father dropped to his knees, and Elena's father and brothers cried, no longer inflamed by anger, the fire in their own blood put out by their tears.</p>
                    <p>The brothers carefully picked up the bodies of the lovers and returned to the village. The fathers remained alone, standing beneath the tree, staring at each other in disbelief and regret, their eyes glancing away to the bloody ground. What did they understand at that moment? That their hate ended their children's lives? How could they survive the rest of their own miserable lives?</p>
                    <p>The time the old men spent together started simply enough: they would bump into each other on the street, and whenever they did, they talked of Elena and of the meals she prepared or of Jose and all the fish he would catch. Then the meetings became planned occurrences: once a week, twice a week, card games three nights a week. The conversation moved from Elena and Jose to old wounds that didn't even belong to them. And the two talked about the tree, every April or May, as the seasons changed and it started to bloom; they talked about how beautiful the tree was and how strong it stood in the center of that grove.</p>
                    <p>Many people in the village, for many years after, smiled as they watched the two old men walk together every morning to their boats to fish together. The village chatted excitedly over the brothers' routine visits to Jose's old home, where they offered their strength and services to the lonely old man there. And forever after, the two families met in forgiveness and laughter and sometimes in sadness and regret.</p>
                    <p>Over the years, the petals on that tree in the center of that grove turned from the bright red of blood of the lovers to the vivid orange of the flaming afternoon sun.</p>
                </div>
                <div type ="section">
                    <head>REFLECTION 2</head>
                    <p>Nothing tastes worse to me than Almond Joy: thin and sad, gooey shreds of coconut, uniform in size and shape, encasing a usually stale almond, and all of it wrapped in something that tastes like mediocre chocolate. I hate it. If anyone watched the grace and beauty of real coconut flesh fall delicately from the sun-shaped kåmyo grater, if anyone ever sunk their fingers into the light, snowy mound of freshly grated coconut to take a generous chunk of that sweetness into their mouth, that person, too, would hate Almond Joy.</p>
                    <p>In fifth grade, Mrs. Garcia, my CHamoru teacher, showed the class a film, one of those post-WWII documentaries. This one happened to be about the coconut tree. The film opened with a generic-looking island boy, skinny and brown, wearing nothing but a loincloth against an equally standard, all-purpose beach. He was skillfully climbing up a tree to pick the nuts. The class giggled since, in 1978 Guam, we didn't know anyone who dressed like that. Maybe most of us didn't know anyone who still climbed coconut trees with such agility, and we all had no idea if the island in the film was Guam or not. As my classmates and I tended to do with films about islands, we started looking for landmarks we could recognize so we could yell out things like, “Oh hey! Is that Ipao?” or “That guy looks like my uncle when he was young!” The cinematography, in short, was mostly forgettable. What made an impression on my young mind was the image of lush, green coconut trees lined in neat rows, gracing the sandy shoreline. It was very postcard-like, and in 1978, the people I knew weren't taking me to seashores that looked so thick, so jungle-dense.</p>
                    <p>Hypnotized by the image, I remember the man's voice-over speaking about the fibers of the husk. The beach image cut away to a dark brown, thick-armed woman using the husk to squeeze out every ounce of milk. I was hooked. What was that? And that tree, according to the voice-over, produced food, clothing, shelter, and all the basic necessities of life. These images, exotic and ironically new to me, got me thinking about the magic of the coconut – one species of tree meant survival. Just one tree. Of course I knew things about the coconut. The obvious things like its use as food, as material for weaving. In fact, the only hand fans we owned were made from coconut leaves. But to build homes? I remember after that CHamoru class telling my CHamoru father, who was dying of cancer in 1978, all about the varied uses of the coconut. “And you can make houses out of them!” I exclaimed. He laughed at me, telling me that his sister, Diddi, was the tree-climber in the family; she prided herself on being able to scale any tree. He smiled, as he lay bedridden. That smile really fueled my elementary school obsession with the coconut. Plus, my love for my Auntie Diddi got me thinking about the absolute coolness of such an all-purpose tree of life.</p>
                    <p>I took great pride in my coconut tree drawings in art projects (landscapes with a western-style home and a coconut tree off to the left). I begged to kåmyo the coconut, and I paid close attention as I stood behind my grandma's little body at the stove, to see how she made the oil. I scoped the perimeter of our backyard and helped my mama nurture the little palms that sprouted, quite accidentally, from the old nuts that fell to the ground.</p>
                    <p>That was dreamy-eyed me in elementary school. In high school, the tree became white noise. Other teen, nerd-girl things became more important than my mother's backyard. I lost interest in the kåmyo and grew to dislike the old-lady smell of the oil, but the coconut continued to do its thing in the daily lives of the women in my family. Whenever her machete came out, I knew it was time for my mama to get the nuts from her midget trees. She grated them on a weekly basis and used coconut milk that she squeezed out of the grated flesh in much of her cooking. She kept the shells, picked clean and washed, for a prep bowl or an emergency mortar. She burned the husks to smoke out the bugs that threatened her trees. My grandma would fry the grated coconut down to make her oil; she'd rub it in her hair and assured me that I wouldn't get any gray if I did the same. She put it on her rheumatoid knees and it warmed her sore joints wrapped in my old t-shirts and an Ace bandage. The coconut was medicine. It was food. It was beauty product and kitchen utensil. The presence of the coconut meant life was proceeding normally. And normal, for an Americanized, high school CHamoru girl, was boring.</p>
                    <p>Away at college, clueless statesiders I'd meet from time to time, upon finding out my island roots, would utter “coconut tree” to me, weird, sultry looks on their faces, as if the phrase's very syllables left the flavors of a Mai Tai or the memory of pineapple on their tongue. I often wanted to grab them by their shoulders, give them a good shaking, and tell them to quit putting a coconut shell bra on me. It was those moments in the big city that I fell out of love with the tree, which they had turned cliché, even though I insisted that it was so much more than a symbol of idyllic escape, of exotic, sexed-up natives, and of vacation from their gray office walls. The coconut tree they conjured was no longer the “normal” I knew and took for granted. It grew ugly in my mind, an oversimplification of the complexities I knew about it. I didn't know any Gilligan, I assured them, and there was no Ginger making a coconut cream pie in an evening gown! I rejected words like “tropical” at a time in the mid-to-late ‘80s when all around me the hyphenated American writers and their stories screamed cultural identity and slapped every Anglo in the face with knowledge of the other. I, however, protected my identity stories. I kept silent. Who wants her or his life reduced to palm trees and grass skirts? I didn't. And frankly, I felt the truth of my island was none of anyone's business.</p>
                    <p>At the start of another millennium, I decided that I wanted to go home. And I wanted to stay home. I had become a mother.</p>
                    <p>When I came home with my newborn, the trees weren't sick yet. I happily introduced the baby to his grandma's backyard. He crawled toward and propped himself up on all of the trees in the yard: the åbas, the åtes, the lemmonchina, the kalamansi, and the three coconut trees. My mom still had them, and she still used them (grandma was long gone). For this baby, the coconut was neither white noise nor cliché. It was a gift of touch, of experience, of smell, of cool breezes and of shade. He associated the tree with love and life. Every morning, I had my baby crawl and sit and lie, skin to soil, in our backyard.</p>
                    <p>And when the backyard became too small for the boy, when the green and the brown earth became normal for him, I obsessed over the idea of lush, green, coconut trees and empty beaches. I kept him away from Tomhom (Tumon), which had become a shadow of its former self to me – the coconut trees replaced with towering hotels. And I knew I needed to go up north to Litekyan (Ritidian). I selfishly needed to see the coconut trees, thick and plentiful on the perfect shoreline. I needed them badly. And I needed my baby to see and know them as well. But this is the part of my story where I can no longer explain why I needed this tree. I took our beat-up car and braved the crazy, bombed-out road to Litekyan, just me and him, this little guy, back home for good, so we could sit in the hot, white expanse of sand under the nurturing gaze of the old woman tree, the trongkon niyok.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF LOVE AND COCONUTS</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>A STORY OF AN ELDER AND A LEGACY</head>
                    <p>The children of Fo'na who had remained on the island lived together, forming clans in order to increase their chances of survival in this new and beautiful land. They made shelter in caves and had little need for clothing, but shivered in the rain and in the evenings. They fished and hunted what animals they could find with finely carved stone tools. And when hunting and fishing grew scarce, they would eat roots and fruits, giving the land time to regenerate.</p>
                    <p>Within one of these clans, there were a brother and sister who lived on their own. At the beginning of their lives, they had a tåta and nåna who loved and cared for them dearly. But their tåta and nåna died when they were quite young. Tåta, they were told, was killed during a clan fight. And nåna died of a fever soon after him, although many knew that she, in fact, died of a broken heart. It seemed she passed on her broken heart to her children, who were greatly affected by so much loss. Afraid of their situation, the young brother and sister, too old to be taken in by others, vowed to take good care of each other and to watch out for each other, for they felt they were all they had in the world. Their survival rested solely on each other, which meant that despite what little practice time he had with his father, the brother needed to kill small animals and fish to feed the both of them. The sister, with the little training she received from her nåna, was able to forage with her brother, prepare the food well enough, and take charge of the general domestic needs of their dwelling.</p>
                    <p>They remained hidden in their cave in the daytime, keeping to themselves and coming out only from time to time to hunt and forage. And where was their clan? The clan would have done their best to help the brother and sister, yet the two, out of fear, innocence, and sadness, isolated themselves. Their clans-people understood that the two were deep in mourning and from time to time, quietly and without ceremony, delivered to the mañe'lu what little fish and fruit they could give to help them get through their days. No clan member expected any food in return, especially under such tragic circumstances.</p>
                    <p>One day, returning from a foraging trip, the two entered their cave and found an old woman huddled inside. She was frail and shriveled, naked except for her long white hair covering her body. She looked like a cornered wild animal, yet her eyes were kind and sparkled at the two when she first saw them. They felt such sorrow at seeing her; everything about her looked so brittle and weak. She never said a word to them, not one explanation as to who she was. Was she from their clan? The siblings had never seen her before. Yet, strangely, as shy as they were, as fearful of the outside world, their two hearts broke for the old woman in her awful state. They took her in and fed her what food they could offer. Because she was so delicate, and to help her build strength, they gave her the sweetest parts of the fruits they had, and the choicest sections of meat. They set her up to sleep in the warmest spot in the cave for her old bones.</p>
                    <p>They housed her for days, but not one word did the old lady utter to the brother and sister. Nor did they try to talk with her. In fact, the mañe'lu did not complain about the lack of conversation with this new companion in their cave home, for she had kind eyes. After her first meal, she started to smile. And with her smile and her eyes, the old woman lit up that dark dwelling. As the old woman grew stronger in their care, the brother and sister grew happier. The light from her eyes, the sweetness in her smile, caused the orphans' hearts to grow stronger each day she remained with them.</p>
                    <p>After three days, they needed more food, so the brother and sister left the cave on another foraging and hunting trip. They left early in the day and returned late in the evening. Setting foot inside, they found the biha asleep. Thinking she must be hungry, the brother went to wake her up to eat. He gently tapped her on the shoulder, but her eyes stayed closed. He then cradled her in his arms to sit her up. Her body, still warm to the touch, fell limp in his arms; it felt as if she were made of bird feathers. Incredible that having been hurt so much by it in their short lives, the young children still couldn't recognize when death was hovering nearby. Once they understood that she was dying, however, the two began to cry over her. The sounds of their cries kept the old lady from slipping away; she opened her eyes and turned her head to face them. “Children, you have been so good, so kind to me,” she said. “I want to give you a gift.” It was then that the two noticed that the whole time they had been holding her, her right hand had been balled into a tight fist. When she opened her hand, inside it was a seed. She had been grasping it tightly, as if it were her life. She placed it in the sister's hand. “Bury this seed with me, and my spirit will take care of you both for all your lives,” she instructed and closed her eyes again.</p>
                    <p>The sister and brother, who had foraged for many things in the jungle outside their cave, had never before seen a seed like the one the biha had given them. The sister closed her fingers tightly over it, just like the old woman had done. They kept vigil by her side throughout the night. In the morning, when the biha no longer acknowledged the sound of their voices, when her skin felt cold to their touch, they yelled out for her in the only name that seemed to fit, “Nånan Biha!”</p>
                    <p>Surprisingly, these two, whose hearts had been so broken by the deaths of their parents, did not collapse into helplessness. The mañe'lu, so isolated from people, gained a gentle and quiet confidence from having eased the hunger of the old woman, from having kept her cold bones warm. They gained bravery from the kindness in her eyes and generosity of spirit from her mute gratitude. Later in the day, after cleaning her body and preparing her burial, the brother and sister, without a trace of fear or trauma, walked out of the cave carrying their nånan biha to the seashore. They dug a resting place for her deep in the earth next to the sand. The sister, following the dying woman's wishes, placed the seed in the grave with her.</p>
                    <p>Not long after, the mañe'lu visited the biha's grave. Upon reaching her gravesite, they gasped at the sight of a little sapling jutting from the place where the seed had been buried. “Atan ha'!” the girl exclaimed. “The seed is already growing into something. Let's see what it will become.” They returned every day and made note of how quickly the sapling grew. Within the week, it sprouted into a tall tree, with leaves that reminded them of the old woman's hair, and a slender, pale-gray trunk, reminiscent of her complexion. But the trunk was strong, perhaps remembering the strength she had in her youth. At the sight of the young niyok, the mañe'lu knew that their nånan biha had kept her promise. She had not really left them and they would make sure that she would be with them forever. Not a day went by without a visit to the tree, both of them talking to its roots and its leaves, and touching the tender green blossoms that appeared in the place where the leaves gathered.</p>
                    <p>It wasn't long after the tree was fully grown that the brother and sister saw the blossoms give way to the first fruits. The brother climbed the tree and poked at the smooth outer covering of the fruit. With some difficulty, he pried the fruits off their stalks and dropped them to the sister. They discovered they could pull the outer covering away. It gave way to rough fibers, revealing a round, little, brown nut. The mañe'lu grew more excited. They wondered what they would find inside this round, little nut.</p>
                    <p>The brother gathered enough of these fruits and cleaned away the outer husk of each one to bring back home a nice collection of nuts. Each nut looked like a face, two black circles for eyes, and one below for a mouth. They were almost the size of the sister's little head. Hard like it, too. The brother and sister smiled at each other again, the faces on these nuts were another reminder of their nånan biha's presence.</p>
                    <p>They hauled the nuts to their cave and took turns throwing them on the stone floor to crack them open. Although rock hard, once opened, the furry nut yielded a soft, white flesh. The mañe'lu smiled; the flesh was creamy and smooth in their mouths, its mild sweetness able to satisfy hunger. Out of some of the nuts, a clear, tangy sweet juice burst forth, quenching their thirst. “How could this be?” they wondered to themselves. This nut provided both food and drink for them. In their short lives, they knew of no other food in the jungle like this one. The mañe'lu thanked their guardian nånan biha, for not only was she still with them, she would provide for them and give them nourishment for as long as they lived. Their nånan biha would take care of them in this way for many years.</p>
                    <p>The fruit yielded food not just for the brother and sister alone. For at the moment they discovered its taste and learned of the gift that was given to them by the biha, the mañe'lu felt that she would have wanted them to share the tree with their clan. Instead of returning to the loneliness and darkness of their cave home with all the fruit they could ever want, they opened their hearts and left some nuts for their clan members. Many weeks later, when the time came for the clan to go to the brother and sister and thank them for the fruit, the mañe'lu told their clans-people about the old woman and how, thanks to her kindness, they had been given this tree of life. “We must always care for the tree,” said the sister. “For it is through our kindness and caring that the tree takes care of us,” added the brother. When they all returned to the shore that day, instead of seeing just that one tree, the clan saw that this mother tree had given life to other coconut trees, all of which had grown in number along the seashore, each one yielding many fruits.</p>
                    <p>That night, the clan went to sleep full from the sweet clear liquid and the delicious fruit from the blessed tree. In the time that followed, their growing knowledge of the tree helped them live lives away from their caves. They made new homes from its strong trunk, and wove their roofs and guåfak to sleep on from its leaves. They burnt the nut's fibers for fire and warmth. The fruit was used in food and for oils. Its roots ground and made into medicine.</p>
                    <p>With the clan forever sustained by the tree of life, they cultivated and cared for these trees with the same love that the mañe'lu showed to their nånan biha. The coconut tree, like the biha, gave the brother and sister new life, gave life to their clan, and provided for all who lived and cared for it.</p>
                    <p>I trongkon niyok is not a loud tree; it does not sparkle in brightly colored blossoms; it is still and quiet, modest and thin – leaves, sparse in their appearance; all masking the legacy of an abundance of life, the legacy from our nånan biha.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>THE COCONUT TREE</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>A STORY OF LOVE AND SURVIVAL</head>
                    <p>In the days after Fuha rock and the first people were formed, two clans settled the north and south of the island. Two of the strongest and smartest men were selected to be caretakers and leaders of these clans. These two, who were brothers, ruled the island peacefully. The younger brother took care of the southern half of the island, while the older brother established his rule up north. In this way, the two clans thrived for many years, living off the land, prospering and growing families and friendships.</p>
                    <p>However, after so many years of living off the bounty gifted by Fo'na and her brother, the southern people sensed a shift in the direction of the winds and wondered when i trongkon niyok would bear fruit. The rains refused to come one season, and then another season, and another. And the heat refused to leave one season, and then another season, and still another. Without the rains and without the cool air, the mahi and the wahoo were thrown off the natural course of their cycles; they stopped swimming in the southern waters. And with all of these marked changes, the southern kingdom found itself on the verge of famine.</p>
                    <p>The concerned women of the village struggled to perform their daily tasks in the midst of all these unnatural rhythms. These southern maga'håga met with each other and decided what needed to be done. They met with the southern chief, who listened intently to their concerns, their worry about the suffering, their fear of needless and impending death. The maga'håga gave him counsel: he needed to leave the south and find food. It must be his goal, they advised him, to seek out other food sources – maybe the trees were blossoming elsewhere on the island – and thus, he must travel as far north as he could. The chief respectfully agreed with the maga'håga. Maybe the north had rain and trees that bore fruit. Maybe the mañåhak found refuge in the cooler northern waters. If he couldn't find food, he knew his older brother would gladly share whatever bounty he and his people had with the people of the south. He was certain of his brother's generosity, certain of their great love for each other.</p>
                    <p>So the southern maga'låhi and three of his strongest men packed very little food and prepared to travel north. No one from the village had ever traveled so far before and no one knew what to expect. The southern maga'håga advised the chief to bring along a makåhna, who would be sure to utter the proper blessings and prayers throughout the journey, as the need might arise. “You may have to communicate with our ancestors,” the maga'håga insisted. “You may have to say prayers or make offerings.” The chief nodded solemnly in agreement.</p>
                    <p>When the day came for the journey and the group of travelers made their way out of the village, the maga'låhi was stopped by his three young children. With their little packs of food and little spears, the children, two boys and a girl, pleaded, “May we go with you? We can help find food.” The southern chief thought for a second and looked at his three young children, smiled and said, “Well, maybe now is the time for you three to journey with me.” The maga'håga blessed them, and with that, the three children, the makåhna, the three strongest men in the village, and the southern chief made their way north to save their village.</p>
                    <p>Their journey was not promising. Trees along the jungle path were thin, branches were drooping. The grass in the higher plains was still beautifully long, but brown and stiff, no longer bending gracefully with the wind. The soil, cracked and thirsty, was no longer a rich, dark brown. The landscape will surely change, the men each desperately thought. The children, despite sensing the tension in their elders, stayed hopeful, as young children have the gift to do. Everyone's hope grew when after two days of such tragic scenery, they reached the narrowest point of the island. They marveled at seeing both shorelines at the same time. The coasts were so close together, so narrow, that the travelers knew an enchantment must have caused this carving of the land. As they took some solace in the ocean's beauty, in the possibility of a blessing that could save their lives, they noticed figures on the horizon beyond them, figures at times obscured by brown sword grass.</p>
                    <p>The travelers counted seven small figures coming from the opposite direction, from the north. As this new group of travelers came nearer, the southern chief planted his eyes on the most imposing one in the group. He saw arms as thick as tree trunks and a forehead as wide and round as his own. As this new group approached, the southern chief recognized very well that proud gait; he remembered copying those movements, hoping to grow up to have a similar walk. The southern chief knew at once who the figure was. His brother was walking with three other men and three young children, two girls and a boy, probably his very own. When the travelers finally met up, the young cousins rejoiced in meeting each other. Most of all, the brothers rejoiced in seeing one another after so many years apart.</p>
                    <p>“Brother, why are you this far south?” asked the younger chief.</p>
                    <p>“I am traveling south to look for you, che'lu-hu. My people and I have grown hungry. The trees are not bearing fruit. The land creatures are dying. The fish are not coming to our nets. The land is withering away. Soon, so will we. My hope is that you will help us save our people. But you? Why are you this far north? Had you heard of our crisis? Were you on your way to help?”</p>
                    <p>The big and hopeful heart of the southern maga'låhi broke into many pieces when he answered his brother with words that he knew would be very hard for the northern chief to hear. For all the joy the young children felt at meeting their kin, the brothers and the other men could not hide their despair. The nighttime turned somber. The six children were given the little food that was left. They were then made to sleep while the adults stayed frightfully awake, silent, hopeless, joyless, and worried about the future. The brothers, as smart and as strong as they were, could not find a way to solve their shared problem. It was a very long night for them.</p>
                    <p>When dawn broke, after very little sleep, the brothers went to wake the children to prepare them for the long and sad journey home. But upon calling for them, the children would not move. They would not open their eyes. The fathers each approached closer. “Lachaddek, we must journey home children!” But there was no movement. The makåhna from the south and the makåhna from the north looked at the still bodies, touched all of them, shook them gently, then harder. The fathers bent closely, held their hands to their children's mouths. There was no warmth, no breath. The fathers caressed the arms of each of their children and ran their fingers along each little cheek. Every time, the skin felt cold to the touch. All six children had died during the night. The fathers fell to their knees, their kinsmen standing behind them in horror. “How could we have let this happen?” they all cried to themselves. Throughout the night they recalled how not a single child made a sound. Not one of them mumbled or complained in pain. What was this curse? The makåhna siha of north and south looked at the maga'låhi siha and said, “Fear not. Look at their faces. Your children did not die in pain. They did not suffer. See?” They pointed at one of the children. “See how she smiles. Their deaths were not due to ancestral displeasure.” The fathers heard their healers speak, but were inconsolable at the loss. The makåhna of the north said, “The ancestors have their reasons, and we must abide by them.”</p>
                    <p>It was decided that these children would be buried exactly where they were, at the midpoint of the island, where south met north, where east coast almost met to touch the shores of the west. The fathers felt that this place would always be the marker for their precious six who came along on the journey to help their people. The kinsmen searched for lime to quarry, to fashion the haligi and tåsa for six latte for the six children. The fathers wiped each of their children's bodies and took their little spears and slingstones to be buried at the foot of each latte. For three days, the makåhna siha prayed to the ancestors, arranged the burial preparations, and prayed for help and healing. The northern and southern chiefs stayed reverent in their mourning, and often spoke with each other:</p>
                    <p>“Oh, they would have made splendid leaders!”</p>
                    <p>“Oh, they would have made splendid mothers and fathers!”</p>
                    <p>They shared memories of their children. And they spoke about the sadness they felt. And in three days, because of their strength and grief and love, the strongest men from the north and south fashioned i acho' latte in that short time. On the third night, the tired and sad men slept each one to a latte. They laid their heads at the foot of the stones. The fathers sobbed silently. Then, spent from the grief that had spilled onto the land from their hearts, the two brothers slept for the first time since their children's deaths.</p>
                    <p>That next morning, the brothers, still lying on the ground, opened their eyes to the sound and feel of still air, to a windless silence. Their hearts beat fast in the strange, chilly, morning air, in the absence of birdsong. These strong men, who had never feared anything, shuddered from where they lay, the hairs on their arms standing on end. When they finally got the courage to get up and look around, they all gasped at what befell them. Next to each of the six latte stones stood six beautiful, fully grown trees, as tall as they were wide with leaves bigger than the hands of the grown men. Scattered upon the trees, hanging off each one of the many branches, were what had to be fruit. They looked to be the size of a child's head. “Is that …?” the brothers wondered to themselves. No one spoke, except the makåhna siha. They offered prayers of thanksgiving to the ancestors, to the children. They prayed over the trees, a miracle offering from the children.</p>
                    <p>The men stood staring at the fruit – it was the color of the sun and the green grass mixed together. None of them had ever seen a fruit that color. As they walked up to the trees, they each held a fruit in their hands, careful not to twist it off from its branch, instead paying attention to the feel of it. Its little body was covered in tiny, coarse bumps as if to protect it from damage, as if the fruit were built to survive a long journey home. Although the fruit was not beautiful, to these men, it glowed with the beauty of the sun. After the makåhna siha blessed the fruit and offered six to each of the six children, the men moved to break open the fruits, not even thinking about the possibility of poison, for how could a miracle borne from the graves of these children be anything but wholesome and delicious and good.</p>
                    <p>The travelers ate until they could eat no more. It tasted sweet and peeled off in pieces, begging to be shared. It felt creamy and smooth on their tongues. The fruit, unlike any other fruit these men had ever known, gave all of them, it seemed, a renewed strength and purpose. They felt ready and excited to journey back home. So after mourning over their children and feasting on this miracle, the brothers held onto each other for a long time. They did not know when they would next meet; they did not know how they would tell this story to their women, to their respective villages. They did, however, know that as they bid farewell to each other, their survival was due to the love their children had for them. Among all who journeyed north and all who journeyed south, these children possessed the greatest strength of all.</p>
                    <p>After many goodbyes, the fruit was joyfully brought back to both villages, and the people welcomed each group home with both sadness and celebration. Both the northern and southern villages planted their own miracle trees, and the trees grew and thrived, ending the time of famine and saving the lives of the island people. And that is how the children of the north and the children of the south took the love between mañe'lu and caused that love to multiply into a bigger kind of love, a love that spread as far and as wide as the branches of the lemmai tree to feed all the people on the island. It is said that famine can never hurt the island of Guam as long as the lemmai tree stands and provides.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>THE LEMMAI TREE</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>A STORY OF FRIENDSHIP</head>
                    <p>Cow and Carabao were great friends but had some difficulty trusting one another. Some say their trust issues developed when both of them belonged to the same farmer. In those days, neither of them wanted to be turned into kelaguen, that was for sure. So, worried for their lives, they each displayed to their owner their capabilities as beasts of burden. Cow had a difficult time proving her strength, because although she was bigger than the other animals, she was by her estimation a tiny bit smaller than Carabao. And while she was only able to carry very few loads, she was far more nimble than her counterpart, a matter of which Cow always made sure to let Carabao know whenever she arrived at a destination first. She'd toss her head up in the air, moo loudly, and repeatedly tap at the dirt, shaking up the dust in the road, very grandly announcing her arrival to whomever could see her, glancing very prettily at that big beast, himself, lumbering toward her, guaranteed to be far off in the distance. Then, when Carabao arrived inevitably second, he made sure to sidle up right next to Cow so she would hear the farmer's amazement at the amount he carried and at how much time he had saved. Carabao may not have been fast, but he was sure to carry a load safely and securely to its destination. Oh, but Cow never had to worry. The farmer knew that her true value lay in her milk, which was sweet and could be traded for the best fish or vegetables. In these ways, their survival on the farm was ensured.</p>
                    <p>Unfortunately, by the time they each realized their unique value to their owner, it was too late for them to change the competitive nature of their relationship. It seems these two became so accustomed to their rivalry that toward the end of their stay at the farm, both Cow and Carabao resorted to squabbles over the more superficial aspects of their existence – whose eyes had longer lashes, whose hooves stayed remarkably cleaner and who had fewer flies buzzing around his or her tail. Thankfully, it was in this way, too, that both Cow and Carabao were able to develop their friendship. One would mention how brilliantly the sun's rays reflected off of her or his skin and the other would snort in disbelief. Pretty soon, the disbelieving snorts gave way to giggles and laughter at their shared silliness, and then to more serious conversations and complaints about their lives on the farm. The two found that they in fact liked each other very much. They were able to maintain their friendly distrust, their amiable competition, even after the farmer had sold each one of them to different farms. Luckily, the farms were not too far from one another, and Cow and Carabao managed to meet up with each other on days when no loads needed carrying and the milking was all done.</p>
                    <p>On one of these days, the two met and decided that it was too hot to do anything besides swim. Now, Cow and Carabao had gone swimming with each other a few times before, but since they had this natural inclination to distrust one another, they had developed a sort of ritual to their sunbathing activities, a ritual designed to guard against any competitive nonsense from the other. So, when they got to the river, they immediately went to their respective trees to undress. Cow initially claimed i trongkon niyok for herself, because of its built-in security measure of falling coconuts. Carabao envied Cow's coconut-falling security system, but he was satisfied that his banana leaves were large enough to protect his hide from any sudden rainfall. If needed, the shade would provide immediate respite from the glaring heat of the sun.</p>
                    <p>Beneath their respective trees, they each very carefully removed their skins. Cow folded her hide nicely and neatly, careful with the creases she made; the hide was tough to fold, coarse and scratchy, but it protected her from bug bites, and she admired the color – the deep, deep brown of the earth. It wasn't often she was able to stare at her skin from this perspective, she thought. She carefully placed it under the protection of a coconut tree by the bank, keeping Carabao in her sights the entire time.</p>
                    <p>Carabao, on the other hand, had a hide as creamy white as the clouds in the sky. To annoy Cow, Carabao would often liken the color of his skin to the sweet milk Cow produced. He, too, knew to take good care of his skin and folded it very nicely and placed it beneath the banana tree, keeping Cow in his sights the entire time. After this ritual of undressing and folding and placing, they each took their exposed pink bodies and finally immersed themselves in the cool river. Once in the refreshing water, the two skinny-dipped happily beneath the hot afternoon sun, laughing and playing, only every now and then stopping to look at each other out of the corner of their eyes, checking to make sure the other one was not up to anything. They swam and played like this through the waning of the afternoon, never thinking once to glance not at each other, but at their precious skins.</p>
                    <p>As dusk approached, a young man on his way home came upon the bathing beasts in the river. “What a strange sight!” he observed of the two frolicking animals. “What is this enchantment?” he wondered. Stopping in his tracks, seduced by their laughter, he moved closer to the riverbank and spied on the creatures for a moment longer. The young man observed the area around him with some fear and suspicion. Could there be duendes hiding in the nearby trees? Taotaomo'na? He shuddered, took in his surroundings more keenly and then noticed the coconut and banana trees and what looked like animal skins beneath them. Feverish from the excitement and strangeness of the moment, the young man impulsively decided that of course, he must be here for a reason and that maybe, just maybe that reason was to play a trick on these two animals. He thought, “Why not take full advantage of this magic?” So the young man quietly snuck over to the coconut tree first, took the carefully folded gray bundle beneath it, and placed it under the banana tree. Then, he took the carefully folded white bundle beneath the banana tree and placed the soft hide under the coconut tree. This prankster, worried about getting caught, slid off into the darkness hurriedly, not waiting to see the results of his mean trick. Further down the path, he let loose a loud booming laugh and chuckled all the way home, imagining what he would see the next day.</p>
                    <p>The sinahi moon had risen high in the sky when Cow and Carabao decided they were tired and it was time to go. They got out of the river, went to their respective trees, and put on their nice and neatly folded attire. The moon was not bright enough for them to see that their hides had been exchanged. And the two, too drunk from conversation and laughter, went home happily without competition, without a care in the world.</p>
                    <p>In the morning, Cow woke up feeling out of sorts. When she went to pasture, her movements were slow, her gait was heavy. She walked around her farm without her usual nimble gestures. She felt as if her farmer had loaded her down with a burden to carry. How was this possible? Cow lumbered along sluggish and unsteady. Her skin was hanging loose off her bones. Similarly, at Carabao's farm, he awoke feeling miserable. Instead of feeling loose and wobbly, he felt as if he were being squeezed; his entire lumbering body was stiff. His joints popped back and forth so quickly as if wound on a spring. But once he became accustomed to the tightness of his skin, his muscles felt compelled to burst out of it. He ran, racing faster than the other carabao near his home all the way to Cow, who looked at him perplexed.</p>
                    <p>“You have my hide on!” Cow cried. “My beautiful, beautiful hide!” And Carabao saw his milky white skin hanging limply on the bones of Cow and laughed! “It is right that you have the milky skin,” said Carabao, who had already fallen in love with the feel of his new self. “The outside of your body matches the inside. The skin you carry will remind people of what you are capable of making, and my skin will help me carry my loads more quickly.” Cow wondered momentarily, “Is he trying to deceive me?” But because of her friendship with Carabao, Cow was able to consider his perspective. “Perhaps you are right, my friend. Maybe just by looking at me, people will think of the sweet milk I make.” And Cow was ok to temporarily let him borrow her hide.</p>
                    <p>The two stared at each other in amazement, getting used to the little bit of each other that they had acquired. Eventually, Cow grew to love the attention she was getting for being so pretty, and never once tried to get back her skin. However, whenever they went swimming, they were both careful to always swim with their clothes on. And what about our trickster? Had he ever seen the outcome of his prank? If he had, he would have been disappointed to see two dear friends, again, too drunk from their conversation, from their laughter, swimming in the happiness of their renewed selves, without competition, without a care in the world. To this day, the descendants of Cow have skin the color of their milk, and the descendants of Carabao are the swiftest beasts of burden on the island.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>THE COW AND THE CARABAO</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>A STORY OF VANITY</head>
                    <p>Little hilitai was born into a cave-dwelling lizard family that cared for her very much. Her nåna nurtured her and made sure to shelter her from the dangers of the wild world of the jungle outside their cozy home. Every morning and night, as that little hilitai's nåna cleaned her and fawned over her, she would coo, “You are the most beautiful hilitai in the jungle, my precious baby. Your singing is the most beautiful sound in all of the land.” Little Hilitai would smile—smug, satisfied, and secure.</p>
                    <p>When the time came for Hilitai to meet the world, her nåna worriedly reminded her of a long list of things to do for her protection and care. “Hagå-hu, use your speed to hide. Use the sun for energy. Use your tail to fight. There are beasts outside our home that will want to hurt you.”</p>
                    <p>“Nåna doesn't need to worry,” thought Hilitai to herself. “The world will be happy to see me!” In truth, Hilitai was excited to meet the sun and feel its heat on her skin. She was eager to climb the highest trees and scamper over their limbs and to inhale deeply the living scent of fresh leaves and grass. So she scuttled out of her cave home, down the jungle path, and when she was too far to see the entrance to her home, she stopped and looked around her. Hilitai sang from deep in her heart a greeting to the sun and to the outside world. She slowed her scuttling to a leisurely and casual stroll, continuing to journey away from home. As she ventured deeper into the jungle, she sang to the things she found: to i flores gaosåli, to the leaves of i trongkon lemmai and i trongkon niyok, and to the blue of the sky, oblivious to everything except what she was able to see in front of her.</p>
                    <p>Hearing the singing, a tiny chichirika immediately flew to find the source, wondering who would have the nerve to disturb a perfectly peaceful morning. Chichirika hovered over Hilitai high enough to be taken for a little fluttering cloud. The bird flapped her wings furiously, trying to stay suspended above the lizard. She wondered, “What is this lizard doing? Why is it singing so loudly?” She observed Hilitai and hung about her listening for some time, but when Chichirika grew tired of this game, she finally spoke up, annoyed. “Your voice is lovely enough, little Hilitai, but you are not very pretty to look at.” And the chichirika laughed, its piercing little chirp crying out “ugly Hilitai” as it flew away.</p>
                    <p>And pierced it did: little Hilitai's heart was stabbed all the way through. She was stunned. What was this about not being pretty? She immediately stopped singing and noticed a pain inside her chest crawling up to her throat. “What was this pain?!” Frustrated, her tongue flew rapidly in and out of her mouth. For the first time in her life, Hilitai was presented with meanness, and this meanness presented a problem, and the problem caused Hilitai to want to hurt that silly bird. But the silly bird was gone and now Hilitai just wanted the pain to go away.</p>
                    <p>Hilitai did some dirt kicking and grass stomping all the while hissing as loudly as possible before her feelings subsided, calling to Chichirika, long gone, to come back and to try to say those words to her again. After her anger subsided, Hilitai was left with another feeling she didn't recognize. She lay motionless on the ground, exhausted from her outburst, absorbing heat from the sun, her legs and body unwilling to move, her heart heavy. And then more confusion overtook her: how could something so wonderful like being in the sun not fix the way she was feeling? Hilitai was pinned to her spot. All her energy was suddenly drained from her. She longed for her cave.</p>
                    <p>As Hilitai lay outstretched, fretting over a solution and quite uneasy in the sun, a ko'ko' bird walked carefully past her. Hilitai didn't see her, but Ko'ko' had heard from far away the ruckus of the stomping and the kicking and the hissing. Ko'ko' was hoping Hilitai would cry, for maybe that would make her feel better. Ko'ko' trotted past her again. And again. And pretty soon, little Ko'ko' trotted confidently in circles around Hilitai. Ko'ko' was curious. She, too, had been warned by her nåna to stay away from beasts who looked dangerous and to flee as quickly as possible whenever one was near. But she wouldn't flee from this one. This little beast here, which looked like an eel but uglier, was not even interested in her. In fact, Hilitai looked like she was frozen in time, staring into space. “What's wrong with you?” Ko'ko' asked, growing impatient. “Are you sick?”</p>
                    <p>“No, I'm trying to figure out how to stop a pain I have that I can't see. I am very confused. How can one have a pain that doesn't bleed?” Hilitai responded as if speaking to a Ko'ko' was the most natural thing in the world.</p>
                    <p>Ko'ko' grew more curious, “Oh please, please let me help you stop this pain. Where is it?” Ignoring the question, Hilitai needed another opinion and so asked her new companion if she was pretty, then added, “Oh, but you can't answer that; you aren't very pretty, yourself.” Hilitai was not being mean. She didn't know how to be mean. She was merely being honest. “You can't know very much about beauty, I guess.”</p>
                    <p>“I see beauty every day,” Ko'ko' responded, indignant at Hilitai's words. She had been away from home a lot longer than her new friend. “Are you or are you not in pain? What is this talk about ‘pretty'? I am so confused!” At this point, any sensible nåna would usher their child away from this situation and remind her to leave people to their business. But Ko'ko' was kind and brave, in addition to being dreadfully curious, so she ignored the voice of her own mother in her head and kept prying.</p>
                    <p>Hilitai heard the distress in Ko'ko's voice and craned her long head to look more closely at this, well, this new friend, who wasn't mean, someone who was offering help. So she took a risk. “Well, a flying creature smaller than you told me I was ugly and immediately after that I felt pain.”</p>
                    <p>Ko'ko' looked at Hilitai carefully. You see, Ko'ko' understood the desire to be beautiful. Although she had beautiful feathers, she was brown. Brown as the dirt, and thus her beauty was muted as she traversed the jungle floor. Ko'ko' also noticed that Hilitai was brown. As brown as the cave she dwelled in. But not only that, Hilitai possessed a very disturbing (at least to Ko'ko') long tongue that spurted suddenly out of her mouth as she talked. “Yes,” Ko'ko' thought, “Hilitai is not very pretty.” But as she was thinking, and because Ko'ko' was indeed a bit more worldly than Hilitai, she came up with a solution that would help all parties involved.</p>
                    <p>“I know what to do, Hilitai.” Ko'ko' offered. “We will take one of my feathers and I will paint you. I've seen some beautiful green moss on the rocks over by a river that isn't too far from here. I have seen that green and let me tell you, if the sun could choose a color to be, the sun would choose this green! And then after we paint you, you can paint me the color of the red achiote seed. I will gather all the materials, so all you really have to do is wait for me to return.”</p>
                    <p>Hilitai only had to hear the word sun and was convinced that yes, she wanted to be this green, and yes, she would do whatever she had to do to become beautiful.</p>
                    <p>Ko'ko' worked hard to gather the materials. She went to the riverbank and used her talons to collect all the moss from the rocks. The moss, with their different hues of green, would provide Ko'ko' with a gorgeous palette from yellowish greens to the darkest verdant hues in the jungle. She knew that Hilitai was so low to the ground that she should blend in with the world around her. For her very own feathers, Ko'ko' thought of the sky and of all the things she couldn't ever reach, like the sun and the friendliness of the clouds above her. Ko'ko' wanted to shine! She dug up the roots of the noni tree and pecked at them until she had enough of their yellow juice to carry back with her. She gathered achiote pods and picked at them to take their seeds. She went to the limestone forest to quarry the white, powdery lime. Finally, she went to the ocean shore and used her talons to gather the shallow water spume. At the ocean, she carefully scooped up water and carried it in her narrow beak, for Ko'ko' very creatively knew exactly what was needed to make the colors work.</p>
                    <p>Back at their spot, Ko'ko' worked to mix the colors. She blended the åfok with the white froth from the ocean to make a milky white paint. She took her sharp beak and pecked at the achiote seeds soaking in water until they released the prettiest orange-red hue and mixed that beautiful orange-red with the noni root juice to yield the color of the sun. For Hilitai's colors, Ko'ko' soaked the dark green moss to make a deep-hued jungle green, and then created a soft, sun-kissed green using the pale-colored moss. She smiled at her brilliance. “The green looks kissed by the sun! How perfect for the lizard,” thought Ko'ko'. Hilitai, watching her work, scurried about, looking for sticks for stirring, and empty coconut shells for containing the paint. At the very end, Ko'ko' allowed Hilitai to very carefully pluck two of the bird's longest feathers. The two friends looked at all the colors on the ground and they grew nervous.</p>
                    <p>“Ok. I'll paint you first, because I have a plan for your colors already. And honestly, I'm tired of you moping about in your sadness,” Ko'ko' teased. In truth, Ko'ko' was too nervous to let Hilitai paint her, and Hilitai was too nervous to start painting first. Ko'ko' continued, “Plus, you're the one who is suffering so.” In truth, all the activity with her new friend had improved Hilitai's mood incredibly.</p>
                    <p>The bird spent the rest of the afternoon painting every nook and cranny of Hilitai, first with the beautiful dark shade of moss green, and then with the lighter, almost pale yellow moss she found near the deep-green moss. The yellow-green shade Ko'ko' carefully painted as delicate dots along the back and tail of Hilitai. Ko'ko' was very careful to place these dots evenly across her friend's back. When the painstaking task was over, Ko'ko' stopped, stepped back and admired her work. Hilitai was impatient. “How do I look?” she asked. “What did you do?” She twisted the top half of her body and saw the lovely dots and the new shade of green that she had on and Hilitai sang. Her beautiful song filled the valley. Ko'ko' was pleased with her work and raised her chest very proudly. She now handed the other feather to Hilitai and said, “Yes. You do look lovely, but now it's my turn. And we must hurry, because we are losing light.”</p>
                    <p>Ko'ko' had to give instructions: “Use the white first.” Hilitai, preoccupied in her new skin, stretched her head to her left, to her right, and back around to her left, all the while staring at her lovely, tiny dots. While admiring herself, she grabbed the feather and absentmindedly dipped it heavily into the milky white paint that was so lovingly made from the lime and the ocean spume. Hilitai, while turning her head to admire herself, loosely held the quill in her tiny claws, and as she made to beautify Ko'ko', as she took the quill and aimed for her friend's exposed brown breast, Hilitai decided to take one more quick glance to her left to see her yellow dots and the deep, deep green of her new skin. But as she did so, the feather quill slapped thick coats of white paint onto the breast of Ko'ko'. The thrashing caused long white stripes, almost like gashes, across Ko'ko's wide chest. Some of the paint splashed upon the poor bird's beak and that was the moment that Ko'ko' shrieked, “What are you doing?!” Hilitai, shocked by her friend's tone of voice, dropped the quill suddenly. Upon seeing the paint splatters and splotches on the bird's back, Hilitai felt another pain she didn't know (we can call this one guilt) and scampered all the way back home to her safe cave.</p>
                    <p>Poor Hilitai. She didn't mean to mess up her friend's coat, but she was just so excited about how pretty she looked that she wasn't thinking about anything or anyone else.</p>
                    <p>Poor Ko'ko'. All that hard work for sloppy white stripes. She had all that lovely color and no extra claws to help paint her. Angered, sad, and feeling betrayed and disrespected, she decided to get back at that lizard. She sat and thought and asked herself, “How can I give her back that pain she felt earlier?”</p>
                    <p>That night, when Hilitai was asleep in her cave, not so close to her nåna anymore, Ko'ko' approached her. She waited patiently for Hilitai's tongue to make its appearance. It was bound to come slithering out, she was positive. And sure enough, Hilitai's long, thin tongue unfurled during one of her little snores. And when it unfurled, at that moment, Ko'ko' took her sharp beak and split that tongue almost all the way in half.</p>
                    <p>Hilitai yelled, “Aiiiiiii!” But all that came out was the sound of guttural croaks. Ko'ko' jumped up and down and laughed as she said to her rival, “You may be a very pretty looking Hilitai, but thanks to me, you will never sing your beautiful songs again!”</p>
                    <p>And how does this sad story of friendship-gone-awry end? To this day, descendants of Hilitai croak shrill, ugly songs in their beautiful speckled skin of green while the descendants of Ko'ko', who carry the splattered white stripes given to them so carelessly by Hilitai, hide their eggs from the vengeful eyes of their now, forever-sworn enemy.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div typ="chapter">
                <head>OKKODO</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>A STORY OF A CLEVER MAN</head>
                    <p>JUAN MÅLA</p>
                    <p>Juan Måla woke up hungry in his shack next to the Hagåtña swamp. He walked barefoot all around the dirt-floor of his home, lifting up the pandanus mats, looking for pesos. He counted ten. And telling his growling stomach to quiet down and stop worrying, he pulled on his only pair of cut-off pants and walked down to the mud pools to retrieve his skinny old carabao. “Look here, lazy beast,” he talked to the sleepy-eyed animal, “you are going to finally make me some money today.” With that, Juan made his poor carabao swallow the ten pesos he found in his home. “Be patient with me beast,” Juan said to the animal, “For by the end of today, you and I will both be fed!”</p>
                    <p>On the road, astride his carabao, Juan whistled a happy, morning tune, bouncing up and down to the lilt of his song. Dressed in his cut-off pants and dirt-stained face, Juan made quite a sight coming down the traveller's path. Indeed, he was a vision to a local, wealthy rancher, who was traveling the same road that morning in the opposite direction. The rancher caught sight of the happy Juan. He approached him and yelled out laughing (for what would a poor, dirty man have to be happy about, he wondered), “Lahi-hu, why are you so happy today?”</p>
                    <p>“Siñot, it just so happens that I am the richest man on island!”</p>
                    <p>Surprised, the rancher said, “Oh really? And how, lahi-hu, did that come to be?”</p>
                    <p>“Why,” said Juan, “would you believe me if I told you that my carabao here has made me rich? You see, after I make him walk in circles about 20 times and then give him a sound whipping, he spits out coins.” Juan patted his whip made of the spines of coconut fronds and winked at the rancher.</p>
                    <p>Naturally, the rancher was doubtful, so Juan demonstrated. Juan took his lazy beast by the rope and lead him around in circles more than 20 times. Round and round the two went, and the poor animal, who could barely walk straight by then, drunkenly lurched from side to side watching his master laughing and whistling at him the whole time. Juan kept one eye on the wealthy rancher and the other eye on his beast, and just when the carabao was on the edge of passing out completely, Juan took his whip and whipped the beast good. The poor animal was struck so hard that he threw up, and because the only things the poor creature had eaten all morning were the coins, all ten of them came spewing out as projectiles from his mouth.</p>
                    <p>The rancher stood with his eyes wide and his jaw slack at the sight of ten coins. His greedy mind was racing.</p>
                    <p>“How much would you be willing to part with this animal?” the rancher asked Juan.</p>
                    <p>Juan coyly said, “Why siñot, you couldn't expect to have me part with this carabao for mere pesos? The fact that he spits out pesos for me, well….” But the Rancher was hoping that Juan really was just a poor and therefore stupid CHamoru man. He offered Juan 10 gold coins for surely, the rancher thought to himself, that carabao would make up tenfold for his loss!</p>
                    <p>Juan, who had more of a weakness for gold than the pesos, gave the lazy, starving beast to the rich old rancher. And both men parted ways in their opposite directions, clapping hands and whistling their happy tunes. Juan whistled and walked away, perhaps just a little bit faster than the wealthy man in case he was found out sooner rather than later.</p>
                    <p>When far enough off the main road, Juan, still dirty and shirtless in his cut-off pants and full pockets, wisely thought that he should perhaps hide all his newly acquired gold. He headed for the beach, and on the way, he broke off a thick lemmonchina branch for a påla. He knew he'd have to do a bit of digging in the sand, wouldn't he?</p>
                    <p>Juan found a perfect spot on the beach with clear landmarks. He used his stick to dig up a hole and then to flatten the mound once he was done. He stamped his feet around to mess up the spot. Satisfied, Juan turned his stick over and over and tapped on rocks or tree stumps along the shore. He walked away from his loot, thinking about what he could buy with his coins. He bumped into a fisherman, who, with an empty net slung over his shoulder, noticed Juan fiddling with the stick. The fisherman, lifting his eyebrows in judgment, mockingly asked Juan Måla, “Is that stick so precious to you?”</p>
                    <p>“Oh this?” Juan held it between them. “Why, this helps me find money hidden in the ground.”</p>
                    <p>The fisherman almost fell over laughing. He expressed great doubt at Juan's words. Unfazed, Juan said, “Look.” He held up the stick, focused his gaze on it, and the stick, as if something were pulling it, pointed back toward the direction from which Juan came. And Juan, grinning at the fisherman, turned around to follow the stick, his arms outstretched. The fisherman ran up behind him, and the two men, guided magically by the stick, made an abrupt stop. Through some magic, the stick pointed at a seemingly random mound of sand. Of course, when Juan crouched to dig up the area, lo and behold, the fisherman stood transfixed at the sight of gold coins that had been buried beneath. Juan scooped up the gold coins like grains of sand; they fell through his fingers as he smiled at the fisherman. It was indeed a miraculous sight to behold.</p>
                    <p>“I will give you 200 pesos for that stick!” exclaimed the shocked man. Juan Måla, at first reluctant, eventually let the fisherman have the magic stick for 200 pesos.</p>
                    <p>Now with his pockets fuller than before, Juan went back to the village to buy some clothes. He needed pants with deeper pockets, and maybe even a bag for his gold coins. The shopkeeper, who knew Juan, was slightly disgusted by his filth as he walked in the store, but changed his demeanor when he saw all the money that Juan pulled from his pockets. “What can 200 pesos buy me?” asked naïve Juan, who had never set foot in that shop before. Delighted, the shopkeeper showed him some fancy European pants, and a clean, white, cotton shirt with shiny buttons. He also presented Juan with some leather shoes, “like the ones the fancy caballeros wear,” the shopkeeper insisted. Juan, who only cared a little to know what the Spanish or CHamoru gentlemen wore, politely played along and asked the shopkeeper if the shoes were made in Spain. The shopkeeper said that he only carried the finest and most well-made items, as he was tying the laces on Juan's shoes. Finally, the shopkeeper brought Juan a very distinguished top hat, “To complete your look, Siñot. It will go well with the shoes.” But in reality, the shopkeeper was hoping the hat would hide the fact that Juan's long, curly hair had not been combed or washed for what looked like days.</p>
                    <p>The shopkeeper, happy that Juan was willing to be rid of so much money in his store, really was trying to help Juan look his best, so he tied the wild mane back for Juan. In the mirror, the shopkeeper remarked that the white shirt with the blue pants complemented his dark skin very well. Juan was seduced as well by what he saw. With his makeover complete and his 200 pesos spent, Juan left the store looking nothing like the shirtless, shoeless dirty man who had walked in there for the first time. He now looked the part of the land-rich.</p>
                    <p>Outside the shop, the Spanish Gubetnadot came trotting by Juan on his horse. The Gubetnadot noted this gentleman, so proper and fine, and concluded that he must be one of those wealthy natives and was therefore of a reliable and trustworthy sort. “Perdon, Señor, but have you heard of Juan Måla, the trickster?” the governor asked him.</p>
                    <p>“Juan Måla!” exclaimed Juan Måla. “But of course, I know him very well. The whole village knows of him. He is shameful, that fool! What has he done this time?”</p>
                    <p>“That petty thief, always tricking people out of their money! I've never been able to catch him. But this time I've received two complaints about him today, one from a wealthy rancher and the other from a good hardworking fisherman,” the Gubetnadot sighed heavily and shook his head in extreme disapproval.</p>
                    <p>Juan shook his head in unison with the distinguished man. “I am not surprised at this news, Señor. But still, how very sad.” And Juan suddenly had an idea, “Señor, I know of some places where this Måla is known to hide out. His hideouts are all very far from here, but I can go and try to get him for you, Gubetnadot.”</p>
                    <p>“Oh, yes please. Oh, if I can bring him to justice, just imagine how much honor España will give me,” the Gubetnadot said and his face brightened immediately. Indeed, it was quite good fortune for him to have bumped into this fine young gentleman with his brilliant idea.</p>
                    <p>“If you lend me your horse,” said Juan, “I will bring him back to you much faster.” Juan bent at his waist in an at-your-service sort of manner, gracefully waving his arm in front of his face. The governor, overjoyed, easily complied with this request.</p>
                    <p>The villagers looked on in awe as they watched Juan slowly mount the beautiful, proud beast. The village dropped their jaws as he safely rode the Spanish Gubetnadot's horse right in front of the Gubetnadot himself and outside the village borders. The Spanish Gubetnadot clapped throughout the whole scene, yelling “Biba!” to this fine young man on his lovely horse riding off into the sunset at the horizon. The Gubetnadot imagined his award ceremony for bringing that Juan Måla to justice, but what the Spanish Gubetnadot did not imagine was that he would see neither Juan Måla nor his horse ever again.</p>
                    <p>Juan Måla now had fine clothes and a fine horse and some gold coins. He was clearly a happy-go-lucky young man, but there were a few things that irked him; one in particular, was the phony Caballero. He was known in the village as one of those mestizos, those half CHamorus, who profit from the Spanish being on island, yet who need the locals to be kind to him, to like him, to want to be friends with him. He showed off too much. He was always dressed in the finest, most colorful and modern fashion of the day. But he still managed to look bad in the clothes. He walked around the village, sometimes with his nose in the air, the brightly colored threads of his pants and shirt glistening in the sun, blinding the villagers.</p>
                    <p>But the locals knew the Caballero talked too much. “Åbladot,” they'd say of him often. He'd walk the village eager to let people know just how fabulous he was. If the Caballero only barely knew a person, he would stop him and talk about how he had to turn down the prettiest girls in the village. “Did you know…” he would start off his story. Then he'd continue with, “these women just won't leave me alone.” Then he'd throw his head back, laughing at the seeming nuisance of being chased by beautiful women. Any subject was fair game for the Caballero. He would talk to whomever happened to be in his path that day. Sometimes he would ask an innocent bystander, “Did you know that I've been asked to advise the Gubetnadot on certain local matters? Ai, he doesn't know how to handle the natives.” The Caballero would add, “The Gubetnadot knows that I know all the goings-on in the village and that I know very well how to handle the ignorant locals.”</p>
                    <p>Ignoring the deep look of insult on the face of the poor victim to whom he was talking, the Caballero would snort out a crude laugh – a laugh that if he was in the vicinity of it, caused Juan Måla's spine to bristle and his fists to ball up and tighten. Thus, as good fortune would have it, while Juan was rushing off back to the beach with the Gubetnadot's horse, he rode quickly past the Caballero, who was taking a long walk outside the village on one of his regular evening constitutionals. Juan, dismounted at shoreline, tied off his beautiful steed, and quickly got into position at the base of a steep and imposing cliff that butted the shoreline. In this instance, Juan was bent over at the waist with his arms stretched out, pushing up against the side of a tall cliff. At first glance, Juan looked as if he were going to throw up. When the Caballero finally approached the cliff, amused, nosy, and with no intention of helping him, the Caballero asked, “What are you doing?”</p>
                    <p>“I'm holding up the cliff,” Juan's voice was shaky. The Caballero noticed Juan Måla's legs quivering, his feet dug deeply into the ground. He saw that Juan's outstretched arms were shaking and that Juan was breathing hard, almost panting. In truth, Juan felt he was a tad bit overdressed for the beach. Sweat beads had formed on his forehead. “No. Really. What are you doing?”</p>
                    <p>Juan repeated himself with urgency, almost yelling this time, “I'm holding up the cliff. Didn't you see me rush past you on my horse? The Gubetnadot notified me about the danger of the cliff and has held me responsible for taking care of it. If I don't hold it up, the entire cliff will come tumbling down, and what a disaster that would be for any and all passersby!” As if on cue, or as if si Yu'os gi langhet were helping Juan out, a few pebbles from up above the cliff got dislodged and fell the entire length of the cliff, landing at the feet of the Caballero, who jumped back.</p>
                    <p>Juan continued, “This cliff needs the strength of at least two men to keep it from falling. I am really running out of strength, Señor. I am running out of strength!” Juan yelled and turned his head to face the Caballero. He gasped at the sight of the gentleman. “Señor, you look strong, as if you have the power of two men! Señor, you are the strongest man I've seen!” Juan continued, “Surely, Señor, if you held up the cliff alone, it would be easy for you, and I could run back to the village and get some help for us down here!” The Caballero looked at Juan and then at his arms and thought to himself, “Of course I can hold up this cliff alone!”</p>
                    <p>Because the Caballero considered his not being informed of this village emergency as an affront to his standing among the locals, he rudely told Juan, “Move over!” The Caballero was confident in his muscles. Juan carefully removed one hand while the Caballero moved into position. Then Juan carefully removed his other hand from the side of the cliff. The Caballero dug his feet into the ground. The cliff, surprisingly, felt light as a feather to the gentleman, and without any effort, he yelled out to Juan, “Go now. Get some more men to figure out this problem! But no rush. I will be fine.”</p>
                    <p>“Yes. I am sure you will do just fine,” said Juan Måla smiling to himself. And when Juan untied and mounted his beautiful horse, he looked back in complete satisfaction to see that the Caballero had settled in for the long haul and was indeed very happy to hold up a cliff that really didn't need any holding up.</p>
                    <p>Thus, at the end of the day, Juan Måla had rid his village of the village jerk, earned ten gold coins, got himself fancy, new clothes, and a beautiful horse, but still had nothing for his hungry stomach to eat.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF A MYSTERY</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>THE SCENTED WOMAN</head>
                    <p>An American sentry smelled the subtle aroma of flowers. “Rose?” he wondered. On second thought he realized, no. Not on the island. Not roses. The fragrance that lingered in the air was quiet, not as sweet as rose. His nose puzzled over it, and puzzling, the scent grew, enveloping the sentry's post. “Ohhhhhh,” barely audible, he sighed to himself, “ Lemons.” He closed his eyes and tilted his head back to inhale the earthiness of the fragrant air around him.</p>
                    <p>With his eyes shut, he didn't see from a few yards away, the softness of a misty figure floating by.</p>
                    <p>In the days of the Spanish, people talked of a mysterious woman who traveled nightly down the same mountainside near where that pretty American sentry stood protecting his military base, whose nose caught wind of her in a more modern time when he couldn't have known the origin of the scent. Really, no one on the base knew anything about the woman, and very few of the locals knew of her except the old timers, and even they were left to speculate. She was probably from Hågat, they'd say, from Hågat by the waters where she loved to swim, although she must have lived in the untamed jungles high in the hills above the village.</p>
                    <p>But once upon those long ago Spanish times, the scented woman was observed, quite often, travelling down the path from those hills for her nightly bath in the freshwater pools by the reef. The people then, as now, did not know her name, only that she came out in the evenings and that she traveled the same path without fail.</p>
                    <p>The curiosity became nightly amusement for one family who got into the habit of waiting and watching for her to approach and to later return. They lived in the only home on that hill, halfway up from the beach, ideally positioned to be her private spectators. The first time, the children saw her as they played from their yard, where they, as children do, tried to eke out whatever bits of daylight remained. They saw her walking, almost gliding, down the hill, wearing a simple white dress, her hair pinned up and knotted into a ball modestly at the nape of her neck. She was ghostly thin, and brown as the dirt they played in. Naturally, the kids wondered where she came from, who she was, what her name was. But they grew tired of their own questions even before Nåna called them all back inside. The sun had set. The children forgot.</p>
                    <p>In the house, the entire family, resting after dinner, smelled her before they saw her. “Nåna, are you cooking now?” said Tåta.</p>
                    <p>“No. It's just the smell of lemmonchina,” said Nåna.</p>
                    <p>The scent of the lemmonchina used to make kelaguen, preceded this strange woman as she walked back up the hill, her hair now undone, long and slick behind her back. She was still wearing the same white dress she had on earlier, the children noticed in surprise. Had she gone swimming or bathing, they wondered. Where was she going now? And that was their first night.</p>
                    <p>And like clockwork, the family got into the habit of gathering in their yard to watch her walk down the hill and then to catch her, to guess her arrival, to be hypnotized by a scent that for all intents and purposes was mundane, but seemed like the most luxurious perfume, which followed her and filled their entire home.</p>
                    <p>The father was especially curious about the woman. He imagined that after bathing, she rubbed her skin with lemmonchina. He knew the practice was common among women – to combat the dirt of ranch life left on their skin. He imagined that the lemmonchina trees were the reason she was up in the hills. They grew wild up there, wild and in great abundance. He imagined that she picked several before her bath and that she hiked there undetected every afternoon to spend time in the wildness of the hills. He reasoned that the scent from this particular strain of fruit must be special for her, because as soon as she'd pass their home and the family caught that great whiff of lemon, his entire brood would return to their evening activities smiling. His wife would hum as she finished sewing. The children acted like appeased wild beasts, calm. Except Tåta. He was left feeling restless. Tåta wanted to know why the woman returned to the hills after dark.</p>
                    <p>One evening, after the woman passed by and the family returned to their evening lives, Tåta did not retire with them. When she walked past the shed at the edge of his property, he ran to hide behind it and to follow her path with his eyes at first. She glided past the shed and traveled further up the hill. Tåta saw that she was going back into the jungle, beyond where the kaskåhu ended. The closer to the jungle she got, the faster she moved, like she was floating. And as she approached the edge of the jungle, she seemed to be fading from his view. She was harder to follow, because it was harder for him to see her. And so in a panic, he started to run after her. She entered the jungle into a clearing, and he followed right behind her. And as soon as she stepped into the clearing, he watched her and her white dress disappear into the stillness of the night air. Tåta walked into the clearing and spun around in circles looking for any signs of her. There were none. She was gone.</p>
                    <p>And so our young sentry smelled her every night, and one night when he kept his eyes open, he caught sight of a thin woman with long hair dressed in a very simple, white dress, the softest color of white he had ever seen. And because he could not leave his post, he tried to figure out ways to get her to come over to him.</p>
                    <p>One night, he readied his flashlight once he caught the scent of the lemons in the air. And when she passed and he shined the light on her speaking in a somewhat harsh tone, “Halt, who goes there?” his light revealed nothing. She was gone.</p>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>REFLECTION 3</head>
                    <p>How do I begin to tell you of the spirits here, of the taotaomo'na that are all around us, of the abandoned lots or dense jungle areas that are alive with them, of the trees that keep them anchored, trees shrouded in mystery? How do I tell you of the way my aunts and uncles spoke of these taotaomo'na, of their great anxiety and excitement, of the way my father, an educated man, conversed with them as if they were flesh and blood men and women; how he asked them to please stop bothering our dogs at midnight? How do I tell you that the dogs stopped barking at midnight? Or that the feel of goosebumps when I'm in my backyard is at once frightening and comforting? How do I tell you that the ghost girl who twirls around my friend's home at two in the morning remembers the pathway upon which the living room rests, that our ancestors have memories that last long after death?</p>
                    <p>If I do try to tell you, especially if you are not from here, you will not understand. Or you will try to understand and call it Magical Realism. Or you will call it archaic and primitive. Unsophisticated. Or worse, you will call it precious.</p>
                    <p>If you were from here, you would know that the realm of spirit is wrapped up in everyday flesh-and-blood living, tied to the senses. And these deeply complex and powerful ways of knowing govern, even slightly, how you would live. Many people, if raised on this island, if CHamoru (and many times, even if not), share this knowledge, and it is unbound by age or social class, or by the number of academic degrees achieved. The ancestors call upon all of us to ask permission, to ask for forgiveness, to acknowledge, and to respect them. And they tell us through the stories they give us.</p>
                    <p>From these stories, I know certain truths: I know to ask si guello yan si guella to allow me to pass through their jungle. I know not to cut down or otherwise harm very old trees. I know to avoid bringing babies and little ones out after dusk. I know not to interrupt the peace of a wide-open space or an enclosed jungle area. I also know, upon even the slightest transgression, to partake in rituals of atonement on their terms and their terms alone.</p>
                    <p>My grandfather, a God-fearing man, must have had the Sight. My cousins often talked of how he kept a nunu tree in his yard, untouched, and of how he spotted duendes from the kitchen of his Sinahånña home, a home he built behind the Church after the war expelled his family from Hagåtña.</p>
                    <p>He likely passed his sixth sense on to my Auntie Diddi, who later inherited the home and told us of her name being called in the middle of the night from the first floor. From that night and every night after until her death, she left every light on in the house. And I mean every light. To prove this to my friend, we drove by the home at 1 a.m., and indeed, the house was lit up like a light-house guiding lost souls home.</p>
                    <p>My first ghostly encounter with the Sinahånña home was really not with the home itself, but with the nunu. I was maybe four years old, and I, so I've been told by aunts and uncles, loved playing around the tree. But a little four-year-old really had no business playing at the foot of the nunu, and I became feverishly sick, my entire body covered in welts. In my story, I hallucinate and have fever dreams of floating just above the floorboards of my grandpa's home, moving through the hallways like a ghost, eavesdropping on the adult murmurs of my uncles at the dinner table.</p>
                    <p>But these memories were ephemeral at best. I don't have any hard timeline of the events or any solid memory of pain. According to my aunts and uncles, I reported playing with children, whom no one else saw. The sickness was a result. The taotaomo'na, they surmised, must have liked me. In anger, my father cut the nunu down, burning its roots, leaving nothing left of that old, old tree. The next day he was struck down with a mysterious fever that lasted weeks. The rest of the story is unclear. I have heard that my suruhana auntie, first cousin to my father, was called in to help. I've also heard that a local dermatologist cured my rash. The details have never been clarified. But the story's end is not what's important, rather it is the lesson that matters: trees have power. Since then, I have carried this truth inside me in a variety of contexts and communities. It followed me at 12, for the most practical and helpful of reasons, to our new house in Tutuhan (Agana Heights), a central village on the island. It helped me navigate my fears.</p>
                    <p>My very first evening at this home, I took a container of Morton salt and poured it around the perimeter. I had remembered hearing from somewhere that salt serves as a barrier between this world and the world of the taotaomo'na. And our home had the boonies for a backyard. It wasn't dense at all, but I was afraid and unwilling to take chances. Afterwards, a little bit embarrassed, I put a near-empty container of Morton back on the kitchen shelf. When my mother went to use it the next day, she expressed her surprise at the lightness of it; after all, she had just bought it. I told her what I did. She was quiet and said, “Put it on the grocery list for next time.”</p>
                    <p>Almost 40 years later, I am thankful for the boonie jungle that exists untouched behind my Tutuhan home. A heaviness still hangs around, but it has ceased being imposing for many years now. The spirits there and I have an understanding, and I stay out of their way. I have passed this truth of the trees and the jungle on to my son, who, although raised with a healthy respect for the aniti and the taotaomo'na, unlike me has not really established clear boundaries with that backyard.</p>
                    <p>At 16, he decided that, even though we had two bathrooms inside our house, peeing in the great outdoors was what men did. He turned our backyard into his private bathroom, specifically a little spot that was almost directly beneath my bedroom window. I grew anxious that he did that. I told him to say, “dispensa yu” at the very least. He did do that, of course, he assured me. He also assured me that he wasn't going in the boonies, just in the backyard. My anxiety eased up a little. My mother, however, was very angry about it. He did it with such regularity that the little patch of soil became dry and cracked. Her grass wasn't growing back. He'd better stop, my mother warned him. But he refused, and as long as he said “dispensa yu',” I didn't really care. Until one night after dinner.</p>
                    <p>My son left to walk the dogs, a nightly task of his. My mom was outside the house cleaning up after the dogs, and I was inside washing dishes. Suddenly and without any reason, I felt compelled to turn and look behind me. And when I did, at that moment, outside one of our windows, I caught a quick glimpse of my tall son's sideview; he was a blur, but it was my boy, kind-of blondish, wearing a white t-shirt (but I hadn't remembered him wearing a white t-shirt earlier). I was so sure it was him that I scolded him, “Hey! Can you actually walk the dogs around the village and not just around the house! Quit being so lazy!” He didn't respond.</p>
                    <p>My mother, who was now sitting on the porch outside, asked, “Who are you scolding? Your boy's walking the dogs.”</p>
                    <p>“No,” I got confused, “I saw him. Just seconds ago. He's on the other side of the house.”</p>
                    <p>And my mama laughed. “Your boy left about five minutes ago.” She assured me that what I saw was a taotaomo'na. As soon as she said that, she continued, in a more serious tone, “You know. The last few nights, I've been hearing a little baby crying outside my bedroom window.”</p>
                    <p>I remember my reaction at the kitchen sink. “How many nights mom?”</p>
                    <p>“Just the last two nights.”</p>
                    <p>The neighbors don't have a baby, and my kid was NOT wearing a white t-shirt. I stopped my washing, dried off my hands to reach for the salt and the box of matches. I went to another room and grabbed the Palm Sunday leaves. First, I burned the palms and used them to såffe the perimeter of the house. Then, I poured the salt, again, around the perimeter. But with the Morton salt in hand, and as I reached the exact area where the grass no longer grew, a thought came to mind: “The boy needs to stop peeing here.” The thought was not my own. Instinctively, in the same way that I know how to breathe, I knew that they were speaking to me.</p>
                    <p>When he got home, in a green shirt, I told him, “I thought I saw you at the window, but it wasn't you and now grandma is hearing crying babies. You better stop peeing outside.”</p>
                    <p>“But I always say ‘dispensa yu','” he insisted.</p>
                    <p>“Well, asking for permission doesn't mean that permission has been granted,” I replied.</p>
                    <p>My son understood completely. He was a bit freaked out, a bit apologetic, but without another word, he marched straight to the nearest bathroom inside the house. Afterwards, he said to me, “Do you think they're mad at me?”</p>
                    <p>“No. They just want you to stop. They've had enough and they just don't know how to communicate it to you.”</p>
                    <p>My mom didn't hear a baby cry that night or on subsequent nights.</p>
                    <p>And since then, no more doppelgangers of anyone have been seen, so far. We know that the spirits are still there. The truth is they will be there long after I am gone. And my son. And his children. The truth is I know that they have more to tell us. You see, the tales don't ever really end.</p>
                    <p>Endings don't exist.</p>
                </div>
            </div>             
            <div type="chapter">
                <head>A STORY OF STORIES THAT LIVE ON</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS</head>
                    <p>The editor, Victoria-Lola, and translator, Siñora Rivera, my co-authors – the writing could not have ended without their thoughts.</p>
                    <p>Siñora Flores, CHamoru language copy editor, who made me feel less insecure about what I had written.</p>
                    <p>Jose Cruz, Jr., who passed on to me his sainas' Juan Måla story. Without their words, I could not have loved Juan Måla the way I love him now. And I could not have written him down.</p>
                    <p>The super staff at MARC, thanks for digging deep and finding stuff.</p>
                    <p>Camacho, Olympia. Legends of Guam. Agana, Chamorro Studies and Special Projects Division, 1988.</p>
                    <p>Cruz, Jose, A. Jr. Estorian si Juan Mala yan i Kabayeru. 2019, Collection of Jose A. Cruz, Jr., Mangilao.</p>
                    <p>ESAA Project Chamorro Language and Culture Program. Legends of Guam. Agana, Department of Education, 1981.</p>
                    <p>Flood, Bo, et al. Micronesian Legends. Honolulu, The Bess Press, 2002.</p>
                    <p>Guerrero, Lagrimas P.L. “Sirena.” The Guam Recorder, vol. XIII, no. 7, Oct. 1936, p. 7.</p>
                    <p>Hemplon Nana Siha: a collection of Chamorro legends and stories. Department of Chamorro Affairs, Division of Research, Publication, and Training, Hagatna, 2001, The Hale'-ta Series.</p>
                    <p>Hornbostel, Gertrude C. (Trudis Aleman). “The Strong Man of Guam.” The Guam Recorder, vol. 1, no. 4, Jun. 1924, p. 4.</p>
                    <p>Hornbostel, H. “Ucudo.” The Guam Recorder, vol. 2, no. 19, Oct. 1925, pp. 197 and 215.</p>
                    <p>Night High School, Composition. “The Quail and the Iguana.” The Guam Recorder, vol. 2, no. 22, pp. 304-05.</p>
                    <p>Rios, Jose L.G. “Legends of Guam: Two Lover's Point.” The Guam Recorder, vol. XVI, no. 5, Aug. 1939, pp. 203-04.</p>
                    <p>Taitano, Carlos, et al. Legends of Guam (As told by old-time Guamanians). Agana, Tuberculosis and Health Assoc.</p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>